How important is this tariff situation?
关税形势有多重要？
It has the potential to be the biggest
它有可能成为最大的
economic story of our lives. People are
我们生活的经济故事。人们是
losing a lot of money on tariffs and
在关税上损失了很多钱，
you're probably a matter of weeks away
你可能还有几周时间。
from empty shelves. And there's a button
从空荡荡的货架上。这里有个按钮
on the president's desk that says, "End
总统办公桌上写着：“结束
it right now." So, can you tell me what
现在就告诉我。”那么，你能告诉我什么吗？
a tariff is? I'll keep this very simple.
关税是什么？我会尽量用最简单的方式解释。
Morgan Hel is the money mindset guru
摩根·赫尔是金钱观大师
who's shaking up everything you think
谁在颠覆你想象的一切
about wealth and how to achieve it. I
关于财富以及如何获得财富。我
looked at the most Googled questions
查看了谷歌搜索量最高的问题
around money and one of the most popular
围绕金钱展开，也是最受欢迎的话题之一。
is how to achieve freedom financially.
就是如何实现财务自由。
It is largely a mindset. You have an
这很大程度上是一种思维方式。你有一个
obligation to understand how money works
有义务了解金钱运作方式
and how to manage it. And it's one of
以及如何应对。它是其中之一
many topics in which you're going to
你将要涉及的许多主题
learn the best by experiencing the
实践出真知
downside. And I'll come back to that.
缺点。我稍后会再谈到这一点。
The next question is how to save money.
下一个问题是如何省钱。
So most people view saving money as it's
所以大多数人把存钱看作是……
just wasted sitting there. But you need
就这么浪费时间坐在那里。但你需要
the cushion so that when the economy
缓冲机制，以便在经济衰退时发挥作用。
goes south and there is a recession, I
如果情况恶化，出现经济衰退，我
want to have a level of control over my
我希望对我的事情有一定的控制权。
ability to support my family. So how
有能力养家糊口。那么，如何
much money do you think it's sensible to
你觉得多少钱才算合理？
have saved? This is a bad answer that no
已经存钱了吗？这是一个糟糕的答案，没有
one's going to like. But when you look
你会喜欢的。但当你仔细观察时
at all these people through history that
纵观历史，所有这些人
have generated great wealth, are there
已经积累了巨额财富，是这样吗？
like certain strategies they've
比如他们采取的某些策略
deployed? One thing that virtually
已部署？几乎
everyone listening to this could learn
所有听到这段话的人都可以学习
from is they were way more patient and
他们更有耐心，
had way more endurance than anyone else.
他的耐力远超其他人。
Also, I wanted to understand investing
此外，我还想了解投资。
and this idea of compounding interest.
以及复利的概念。
So, compound interest is the most
所以，复利是最主要的。
misunderstood thing about investing
关于投资的误解
because that's what builds wealth. If
因为财富就是这样积累起来的。如果
you look at like Warren Buffett, he
你看他像沃伦·巴菲特，他
wouldn't want to get haircuts because if
不想理发，因为如果
he invested that money and leave it
他把那笔钱投资了，然后就离开了。
alone for 50 years, in his mind, a
独自一人生活了50年，在他心中，
haircut would cost $10,000. And then do
理发要花1万美元。然后这样做
you recommend people try and buy houses
你建议人们尝试买房
or is it just to rent those houses? So
还是只是为了租房子？所以
the truth is
真相是
this has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信。
bit. 53% of you that listen to this show
少量。 53% 的听众收听了这个节目
regularly haven't yet subscribe to the
经常还没有订阅
show. So could I ask you for a favor
展示。我能请你帮个忙吗？
before we start? If you like the show
开始之前？如果你喜欢这个节目
and you like what we do here and you
你喜欢我们在这里做的事情，你
want to support us, the free simple way
想支持我们吗？免费又简单的方式！
that you can do just that is by hitting
你可以通过点击来做到这一点。
the subscribe button. And my commitment
订阅按钮。我的承诺
to you is if you do that, then I'll do
对你来说，如果你那样做，那么我也会那样做。
everything in my power, me and my team,
我和我的团队将竭尽全力
to make sure that this show is better
为了确保这个节目更好
for you every single week. We'll listen
每周都为您准备。我们会听的。
to your feedback. We'll find the guests
感谢您的反馈。我们会找到客人。
that you want me to speak to, and we'll
你想让我跟谁谈谈，我们就会
continue to do what we do. Thank you so
继续做我们正在做的事情。非常感谢
much.
很多。
In 2020, my older brother Jason came to
2020年，我的哥哥杰森来到
me after spending more than a decade
我花了十多年时间才做到这一点。
working in the finance industry. And he
在金融行业工作。而他
said to me, Stephen, there is one book
斯蒂芬对我说，有一本书
you need to read to understand money.
你需要读书才能了解金钱。
And that was your book, The Psychology
那就是你的书，《心理学》。
of Money. And that's how I came into
金钱。这就是我进入这个行业的经过。
your world and understood who you were,
你了解了你的世界，也理解了你是谁。
what you think. And really, this book
你认为呢。这本书真的……
has shaped how I think about money ever
它塑造了我对金钱的看法。
since. And this is why I loved having
自从。这就是我喜欢拥有的原因。
you on the show last time, but I was
你上次上过节目，但我当时不在。
insistent to speak to you again with
坚持要再次和你谈话
everything that's going on with the in
所有与“in”有关的事情
the world right now. Morgan, what is the
当今世界。摩根，什么是
most important thing we should be
我们应该做的最重要的事情是
talking about at this present moment
谈论此刻
based on I guess the subtitle of this
我猜是根据这个标题来的
book, Timeless Lessons of Wealth, Greed,
书籍，《财富、贪婪的永恒教训》
and Happiness? Thank you, Steph. It's so
幸福呢？谢谢你，斯蒂芬。真是太
so good to be back. I think what's what
很高兴能回来。我想这就是答案
I like about what you just said, and
我喜欢你刚才说的那些话，而且
thank you for for that, is that you said
谢谢你，你刚才是这么说的吗？
the book changed how you think. Mhm. And
这本书改变了你的思维方式。嗯。和
that's important because the book does
这一点很重要，因为这本书确实
not tell you what to do. Nowhere in the
不会告诉你该怎么做。在任何地方
book do I say this is how you should
书中我该如何说你应该这样做呢？
invest your money. This is how you
投资理财。这就是你的方法
should spend your money because you're
你应该花钱，因为你
different for me and everyone else.
对我来说和对其他人来说都不一样。
We're all different. I've always just
我们每个人都不一样。我一直都只是
been interested in how people think.
我一直对人们的思维方式很感兴趣。
Like what's going through your head when
比如你当时在想什么
you're making investing decisions. And
你在做投资决策。和
if you can understand greed, fear, risk,
如果你能理解贪婪、恐惧和风险，
envy, jealousy, those topics, that is
嫉妒、羡慕，这些话题，就是这些。
way more important than anything they
比任何东西都重要得多
will teach you in a PhD finance course
将在博士金融课程中教授你
at Harvard. Not that the the technical
在哈佛大学。并非技术方面的问题。
stuff doesn't matter, but the
物质的东西并不重要，重要的是……
psychological stuff with money is
金钱中的心理因素
everything. I mean, so much so many
一切。我的意思是，太多太多了
money problems in the real world have to
现实世界中的金钱问题必须
do with impatience, envy, greed. That
与急躁、嫉妒、贪婪有关。那
that's it. It's not that people don't
就是这样。并非人们不这样做
know the formulas, don't know the data,
懂公式，不懂数据
don't know, you know, how to calculate
不知道，你知道，怎么计算
compound interest by hand. None of that
手动计算复利。都不是。
matters. It's envy. It's in it's
重要的事情。这是嫉妒。它在它的
impatience. And so that as a writer,
不耐烦。因此，作为一名作家，
that's was I was always interested in.
那正是我一直感兴趣的。
Like I'm tired of people giving advice
我已经厌倦了别人给我提建议。
and saying these are the stocks you
并说这些是你的股票
should buy and here's what the econom is
应该买入，以下是当前的经济形势
going to do next quarter. I was like no
下个季度要做。我当时就想：不
one was any good at it. But I was always
其中一个很擅长。但我一直
just fascinated in what's going on in
我对正在发生的事情非常着迷
people's heads. And you asked why is
人的头部。你问为什么？
that important right now? Well, I think
现在这么重要吗？嗯，我觉得
it's always important like those topics
像这些话题一样，它始终都很重要。
of you know the subtitle is timeless
你知道，字幕是永恒的
lessons because I think a lot of these
因为我认为很多这些课程
things were as true a thousand years ago
一千年前，情况也是如此。
as they will be a thousand years from
因为他们将距今千年
now. Like greed and envy and impatience
现在。比如贪婪、嫉妒和急躁
is just ingrained in how people think.
这只是人们思维方式中根深蒂固的一部分。
It always has been. And so you see
一直都是这样。所以你看
what's going on right now with tariffs
目前关税方面的情况如何？
in the economy. Stock market's gone up a
在经济方面。股市上涨了
lot. Bitcoin's gone up a lot. So these
很多。比特币涨了很多。所以这些
points have always been true, but a lot
这些观点一直都是正确的，但是很多
of them are magnified right now. A lot
现在，它们中的一些被放大了。很多
of people have made a lot of money on
很多人通过这种方式赚了很多钱。
Bitcoin. A lot of people are losing a
比特币。很多人都在失去
lot of money on tariffs. So greed, fear,
关税收入很高。所以，贪婪、恐惧、
envy, it all kind of just collides. It
嫉妒，这一切都交织在一起。它
is right now. How important is this
就是现在。这有多重要？
tariff situation that we find ourselves
我们所处的关税形势
in? Because we're seeing all over the
在？因为我们到处都能看到
news everywhere. Tariffs. Trump's done
到处都是新闻。关税。特朗普已经完成了
this 10% here. blanket tariff here. Does
这10%在这里。这里实行一揽子关税。做
it matter? And maybe more specifically,
这重要吗？更具体地说，
does it matter to the average person? It
这对普通人来说重要吗？它
has the potential to be the biggest
有潜力成为最大的
economic story of our lives. It doesn't
我们生活的经济故事。它不
have to be. One thing that's very
必须如此。有一件事非常
interesting about the tariff story is
关于关税的故事很有意思。
that if you compare it to 9/11 or COVID
如果把它和9/11事件或新冠疫情相比的话。
or 2008, the banking crisis, the tariff
或者2008年的银行业危机、关税
issue that we're going through right now
我们目前正在经历的问题
can be ended in one minute. There's a
一分钟内即可结束。有一个
button on the president's desk that
总统办公桌上的那个按钮
says, "End it right now." And even you
他说：“立刻结束它。”甚至你
know if that did happen there would
我知道如果那件事真的发生了，会
still be some lingering damage in terms
某些方面仍会留下一些后遗症。
of trust and reputation but there was no
信任和声誉，但却没有
button on the president's desk for co
总统办公桌上的按钮用于合作
that said end this all right now it
话虽如此，现在就结束这一切吧。
didn't exist and 911 and Lehman Brothers
当时并不存在，911事件和雷曼兄弟公司也不存在。
in 2008 once those risks hit we just had
2008年，一旦这些风险来袭，我们就……
to deal with them through their finish.
通过他们的结局来处理他们。
This is different because it it can and
这不一样，因为它可以而且
is changing by the day. So when people
每天都在变化。所以当人们
have a take on what's going on right now
对当前局势发表一下看法
that might that take might be stale an
那可能意味着那件事已经过时了。
hour from now but it's absolutely true
虽然还有一小时，但这绝对是真的。
that the global economy to an extent
全球经济在某种程度上
that I think people don't appreciate
我认为人们并不欣赏这一点。
enough is a very complicated intricate
足够是一个非常复杂精细的问题
machine and most economic problems come
机器和大多数经济问题都源于此。
when people like try to fiddle with that
当人们试图摆弄它的时候
machine a little bit. They're like ah
稍微用机器处理一下。他们就像……啊
let's turn this dial by one degree and
让我们把这个旋钮转动一度，
see what happens and then like oh it
看看会发生什么，然后就像，哦，它
blows up. Oh I shouldn't have done that.
爆炸了。哦，我不该那样做的。
Tariffs is like let's hit it with a
关税就像让我们用……来打击它
baseball bat a couple times. Let's hit
用棒球棍打了几次。咱们开始吧
it with like a crowbar and see and see
用撬棍之类的东西撬一下，看看效果如何。
what happens. Like the global economy is
会发生什么。就像全球经济一样
so interconnected and if you go to your
如此紧密相连，如果你去你的
local grocery store, Target or Walmart,
当地杂货店、Target 或沃尔玛
whatever it might be, and and go around
不管是什么，然后四处走动
and look at where that stuff was made.
看看这些东西是在哪里生产的。
It's I mean, and it's all over the
我的意思是，到处都是
world. It's like very like it's it's
世界。就像……非常像……
everywhere. And once you shut that down
到处。一旦你关闭了它
and put barriers on that, it can become
如果设置障碍，它就会变成
a a big problem very quickly. One thing
很快就出现了一个大问题。一件事
I've noticed in the last couple weeks
我注意到最近几周
that I think is very interesting are the
我认为非常有趣的是……
number of educated and smart friends
拥有许多受过良好教育且聪明的友人
that I have who send me a text or a call
我认识的人会给我发短信或打电话。
or an email and say, "Hey, can you
或者发封邮件说：“嘿，你能……”
explain what a tariff is? I see this
请解释一下什么是关税？我看到了这个
word, but I don't really know what it
这个词，但我真的不知道它是什么。
is." And I think that's important
“是的。”我认为这很重要。
because I don't think the average person
因为我认为普通人
understands what can happen to the
明白会发生什么
economy if this persists for a long
如果这种情况持续下去，经济将长期受到影响。
period of time.
一段时间。
I'm so glad you said that because I've
我很高兴你这么说，因为我
been waiting for weeks now to ask
已经等了好几个星期了，终于可以问这个问题了。
somebody like yourself who studied
像你这样学习过的人
economics to explain in a simple way
用简单易懂的方式解释经济学
what a tariff is. And feel free to use
什么是关税？请随意使用
an analogy. I I think about 50% of
一个类比。我认为大约有50%
people have no idea what a tariff is.
人们根本不知道关税是什么。
Yeah. And then on a sort of an
是的。然后，在某种意义上的
incremental scale um people's clarity
逐步扩大规模，提高人们的清晰度
gets better and better to I would
越来越好，我会
estimate about 5% of the general
估计约占总人口的5%。
population could articulate what a
民众可以清楚地表达什么是
tariff is. 5% or less. So, can you tell
关税是。 5%或更少。所以，你能说出来吗？
me what a tariff is? The first I would
什么是关税？首先我会
say is tariffs have been used for
比如说关税已被用于
hundreds of years and there is there can
几百年了，而且一直存在。
be a very good useful purpose for them
对他们来说，这将是一个非常好的用途。
in the economy. I think as they're
在经济方面。我认为他们
structured right now in the United
目前在美国的结构是这样的
States, it's a huge mistake. It has a
各州这样做是一个巨大的错误。它有一个
potential to be a catastrophe, but they
有可能酿成灾难，但他们
can be a useful thing in the economy.
在经济中，这可能是一件有用的事情。
This is not a black and white thing.
这并非非黑即白的问题。
What a tariff is is, let's keep this
关税是什么，我们先来说说这个。
very simple. The United States buys a
非常简单。美国购买了
bunch of computers that are made in
一批在……制造的计算机
China. Bunch of iPhones that are made in
中国。一堆在……制造的iPhone
China. They're on a container ship. They
中国。他们在一艘集装箱船上。他们
ship them to United States. When they
将它们运往美国。当他们
get to the port in the United States,
抵达美国港口，
the importer, which is Apple, bringing
进口商是苹果公司，它带来了
the iPhones in that are made in China,
那些中国制造的iPhone
an American company, has to pay the
一家美国公司必须支付
tariff. Oh, that's put on it. And a lot
关税。哦，已经放上去了。而且很多
of people, and it's it's very
人，而且非常
understandable why they would think
可以理解他们为什么会这么想
this, would say, well, no, in that
这么说的话，嗯，不，就那样而言。
situation, China pays the tariff. And
在这种情况下，中国支付关税。和
there could be a situation where China
可能会出现这样一种情况：中国
starts discounting the iPhones. The the
开始对iPhone进行折扣促销。的
the company that's making the iPhones
生产iPhone的公司
would discount it. Like, there can be
我会忽略它。例如，可以有
some offset, but the person who's paying
有一些补偿，但付款人
that tax is the importer. So often we
这项税收是针对进口商的。我们常常
think about we've applied the tariff to
想想我们已经对……征收了关税
China, right? So what's happening is
对吧，是中国？所以现在的情况是：
China having to spend the 10% or I think
中国必须花费那10%，或者我认为
the tariff currently is like 125 145.
目前的关税大概是 125 到 145。
The number doesn't matter because trade
数字并不重要，因为交易
will eventually will just stop at those
最终只会止步于此。
levels. It just won't happen. So if
级别。这绝不可能发生。所以如果
Apple import an iPhone now with that
现在苹果公司进口的iPhone就是这样的。
tariff level, then Apple would have to
如果关税达到一定水平，那么苹果公司就必须……
pay the 145% when it arrives at the
到达目的地时支付145%的费用。
shore. Correct. The United States. I
支撑。正确的。美国。我
mean, here's here's an example that most
我的意思是，这里有一个例子，大多数
people will understand. Sales tax. You
人们会理解的。销售税。你
know, in in most states in the United
我知道，在美国大多数州都是如此。
States, it's uh six to 10%. If you go to
各州，呃，是 6% 到 10%。如果你去
the store and buy something, you add the
在商店买东西时，你加上
sales tax to that. VAT in the UK. Ex.
还要加上销售税。英国增值税。前任。
Yeah. Fair. Who pays that is not the
是的。公平的。谁来支付这笔费用？这不是……
store, it's the customer. So even if the
商店，顾客才是最重要的。所以即使
tax is put on the seller, the seller
税款由卖方承担。
passes it on to you, the customer, and
并将其传递给您，也就是客户，
it says right on your receipt, you
收据上写得很清楚，你
bought something for $10 and then there
花了10美元买了东西，然后就……
is a there's your sales tax and here's
这是你的销售税，这是……
what you're going to pay in the end. And
你最终要付出的代价。和
so it's similar from that. Now that let
所以情况和那方面类似。现在让我们
me explain this why there would be a
让我解释一下为什么会有这种情况
very useful case for tariffs to show
这对于关税来说是一个非常有用的案例。
that this is not black and white and
这件事并非非黑即白。
this is not oh all tariffs are bad this
这并不是说所有关税都是坏事。
this happened in the United States
这件事发生在美国。
during co we were virtually 100% reliant
在合作期间，我们几乎100%依赖于
on mass N95 masks uh that were made in
大量生产的N95口罩
China and Korea and not in the United
中国和韩国，而不是美国
States and so when you have a medical
各州，所以当你有医疗需求时
crisis in the early days of co and we're
公司成立初期的危机，以及我们……
like we need hundreds of millions of
就像我们需要数亿个
masks yesterday they're all made
昨天做的口罩都做好了。
somewhere else we do not want to be in
我们不想去其他地方
that situation So it would absolutely
这种情况，所以绝对会
make sense to have a tariff on masks to
对口罩征收关税是合理的。
make sure that they are so expensive to
确保它们贵得离谱
import overseas that we have to start
我们必须开始从海外进口。
making them in the United States. That
在美国制造。那
makes sense. Same with military
有道理。军队也是如此。
equipment. You do not want to go to war
设备。你不想打仗
with a country and be reliant on that
与一个国家合作并依赖于它
country to make the your military gear,
国家制造你的军用装备，
your bullets and your bombs and your
你的子弹、你的炸弹和你的
tanks and whatnot. Absolutely makes
坦克之类的东西。绝对如此
sense to have a tariff on that to make
对此征收关税是合理的。
sure they're made in the United States.
可以肯定它们是美国制造的。
That said, so this is it's not black and
也就是说，所以它不是黑色的，而且
white, but to have a blanket tariff and
白色，但要实行一揽子关税，而且
say everything that comes from any
说出所有来自任何地方的事情
country anywhere in the world and
世界任何地方的国家和
China's going to be this to an extreme
中国将会把这种趋势推向极致。
degree is going to have a tariff on it.
学位是要收费的。
And whether that's between 10% for all
而这是否意味着所有人都占10%呢？
countries or 145% from China that you
来自中国的国家或地区，或145%来自中国，你
know I I've used this analogy before
我知道我以前也用过这个比喻。
that if you talk to dieticians there is
如果你和营养师交谈，你会发现……
a huge amount of debate over what's the
关于什么是……存在大量的争论
best diet should you eat? Should you be
最佳饮食方案是什么？你应该
uh keto? Should you be vegan? like
呃，生酮饮食？你应该成为素食主义者吗？喜欢
everything in between they don't there's
他们不做中间的一切。
so much debate all of them agree that
经过一番争论，他们一致认为：
processed sugar is bad nobody nobody
加工糖不好，这一点毋庸置疑。
thinks processed sugar is good and
认为加工糖是好的，
tariffs are that with economists like
关税是经济学家们所关注的。
there is so much debate among economists
经济学家之间存在着很多争论。
on what should the tax rate be what
税率应该是多少？
should subsidies be should we you know
补贴是否应该？我们是否应该知道？
like you know like free market versus
就像你知道的，自由市场与
subsidies there's so much debate no
关于补贴问题，争论很多，没有
serious economist thinks that you should
严肃的经济学家认为你应该
have a trade war and the thing is this
打贸易战，问题是这样的
is not new we've been doing this for
这并非新鲜事，我们一直都在这样做。
hundreds of years. And it's very well
数百年。而且非常好
known that in the 1930s, the Great
众所周知，在20世纪30年代，大革命
Depression, we took put huge tariffs on
大萧条时期，我们对……征收了巨额关税
in the early days of the Great
在大帝时代初期
Depression, uh they didn't know it was
抑郁症，呃，他们当时并不知道那是抑郁症。
called the Great Depression back then
当时被称为大萧条
because we put them on and it shut down
因为我们把它们装上后，它就关机了。
global trade. And it's easy to think
全球贸易。而且很容易想到这一点
that if you put tariffs on your own
如果你自行征收关税的话。
country, that will make it easier to
该国，这将使……更容易
manufacture. Like all those jobs that we
生产。就像我们从事的那些工作一样
shipped overseas of building cars,
出口海外的汽车制造设备
they're all going to come rushing back
他们都会蜂拥而至。
to America. And it it very rarely
去美国。而且这种情况非常罕见
happens like that when you have a trade
当你进行交易时，这种情况就会发生。
war. But what I mean by trade war is we
战争。但我所说的贸易战是指我们
put tariffs on China, they respond to
对中国加征关税，他们会做出回应
put tariffs on us and you just go tit
对我们征收关税，你就等着瞧吧
fortat and it's and you go back and
fortat，然后你回去，
forth and it's like mutually assured
向前，就像相互保证一样
mutually assured destruction in economic
经济领域的相互确保摧毁
terms. So why is Trump doing it then in
条款。那么，特朗普为什么要这样做呢？
your view? Because he's given lots of
你的看法是什么？因为他付出了很多
reasons. He said that they're ripping us
原因。他说他们正在剥削我们。
off. He says lots of countries have been
离开。他说很多国家都……
ripping off the United States. How do
敲诈美国。如何
you unpack what he's saying there? And
你来分析一下他说的那些话是什么意思？和
what do you believe the true reason is
你认为真正的原因是什么？
underneath there? To his credit, Trump
下面呢？值得称赞的是，特朗普
has been very consistent on this for
在这方面一直非常一致
literally 40 years. You can go go on
足足40年。你可以继续
YouTube. He gave an interview in I think
YouTube。我想他接受过一次采访。
it was 1986. He went on Oprah in 1986
那是1986年。他于1986年上了奥普拉的节目。
talking about how free trade wasn't free
谈论自由贸易并非自由
and that Japan and other countries were
日本和其他国家
ripping us off and that the solution to
敲诈我们，而解决办法是
it were tariffs. So he this is not a new
那是关税。所以这对他来说并不是一件新鲜事。
view. This has been a lifelong quest
看法。这已成为我毕生的追求。
that he's had. I would say not
他曾经拥有过。我会说不
necessarily Trump's views, but I would
不一定是特朗普的观点，但我会
say it absolutely makes sense that there
可以说，这完全合乎逻辑。
is a large chunk of America that looks
是美国很大一部分看起来
back to the period of 1950s, 1960s when
回到上世纪五六十年代
we were a manufacturing powerhouse and
我们曾是一家制造业巨头，
says that was better than what we have
他说这比我们现有的要好。
now and we should go back to that. I get
现在我们应该回到那个话题。我明白了
why people would say that because it's
人们之所以会这么说，是因为……
true that we've lost a lot of
确实，我们失去了很多
manufacturing jobs in the last 50 years.
过去50年制造业就业岗位。
I think manufacturing jobs peaked in the
我认为制造业就业岗位在……达到了顶峰。
late 1970s and we've lost something like
20世纪70年代末，我们失去了类似的东西。
10 million manufacturing jobs that we
我们创造了1000万个制造业工作岗位
had, you know, versus what we had back
你知道，和我们以前拥有的相比，现在的情况截然不同。
then. And I get why if I was in that
然后。如果我身处其中，我就能理解为什么了。
situation, I would probably feel the
在这种情况下，我可能会感到
same. Where I would push back is the
相同的。我反对的地方在于……
situation that we had in the 1950s and
我们在20世纪50年代遇到的情况以及
1960s where it was just America
20世纪60年代，那时只有美国。
manufacturing powerhouse were a very
制造业巨头非常
unique period that I think is virtually
我认为这是一个独特的时期，几乎是
impossible to bring back. And I'll tell
无法挽回。我会告诉
you why. At the end of World War II,
你为什么？二战结束后，
1945, Europe and Japan were in rubble.
1945年，欧洲和日本满目疮痍。
They were decimated from the war,
他们在战争中损失惨重。
America was not decimated whatsoever.
美国根本没有遭到毁灭性打击。
And so we had basically a a global
因此，我们基本上拥有了一个全球性的
manufacturing monopoly for a period of
制造业垄断时期
time. China was not in the equation.
时间。中国不在其中。
South Korea was not in the equation.
韩国不在其中。
India, Bangladesh, those they were not
印度、孟加拉国，那些他们不属于的地方
in the in the equation. It was basically
在等式中。基本上就是这样
Japan, the United States and Europe, two
日本、美国和欧洲，两个
of which were just struggling to feed
其中有些甚至连吃饭都成问题。
their citizens. And once they got that
他们的公民。一旦他们得到了那个
under control, it was like we have to
在控制之下，就像我们必须……
rebuild the damage from the war. So
重建战争造成的破坏。所以
America had about 20 years from 1945 to
从1945年到1946年，美国大约有20年的时间。
the mid 1960s of we have a manufacturing
20世纪60年代中期，我们拥有制造业
monopoly. And then we had 16 million US
垄断。然后我们有1600万美国人
soldiers come home from the war. And
士兵们从战场归来。和
there was so much pent-up demand for
人们对……有着非常大的需求。
them to buy homes and washing machines
让他们买房和洗衣机
and cars and radios and all these
还有汽车、收音机以及所有这些东西
things. And all of them were built in
事物。它们全部都是在……中建造的。
America because nobody else could build
美国，因为其他国家都无法建造
them. And that created a really special
他们。这创造了一种非常特别的氛围。
time when like because we had a
就像我们曾经有过那样的时光
manufacturing monopoly, it was just like
制造业垄断，就像……
factories everywhere. We built up so
到处都是工厂。我们逐渐发展壮大
many factories during the war, there was
战争期间有很多工厂，
endless demand for those products. And
对这些产品的需求永无止境。和
this is this is an important part too.
这也是很重要的一部分。
Whitecollar workers during that period
那段时期的白领工人
didn't make that much money relative to
相对于其他方面来说，赚的钱并不算多。
what they did before or since. And that
他们之前或之后做了什么。而那
was important because the wages that the
这一点很重要，因为工资……
bluecollar manufacturing workers were
蓝领制造业工人是
earning felt great by comparison. So, if
相比之下，收入感觉好多了。所以，如果
you were an auto worker in Detroit and
你曾是底特律的一名汽车工人，
you compared your wage in 1955 to the
你将1955年的工资与……进行了比较
local accountant or dentist or doctor,
当地的会计师、牙医或医生
by comparison, relative to today, you're
相比之下，与今天相比，你
like, "Oh, that's it's pretty good."
比如，“哦，这还不错。”
Yeah, the doctor makes more than me, but
是的，医生的收入比我高，但是……
not that much more than me. You know, I
比我强不了多少。你知道，我
drive a Chevy, he drives a Cadillac, his
他开雪佛兰，他开凯迪拉克，他的
is a little bit nicer, but we're living
稍微好一点，但我们仍然住在这里。
mostly the same lives. And so I think
大多是相同的生活。所以我认为
that was a lot of the feeling of
那是一种很深的感受。
prosperity in the 50s and 60s was this
五六十年代的繁荣就是如此。
very unique period of manufacturing
非常独特的制造时期
monopoly as Europe and Japan were
欧洲和日本的垄断地位
rebuilding and by comparison to other
重建以及与其他重建的比较
workers. It felt amazing. And then at
工人。感觉棒极了。然后是
about the 1970s, Japan and Europe had
大约在20世纪70年代，日本和欧洲都曾有过这样的情况。
gotten themselves back together from the
他们重新团结起来
ravages of World War II and they became
第二次世界大战的蹂躏使他们变成了
manufacturing dynamos in their own
他们自己制造发电机
right. And I don't think we really
正确的。而且我认为我们真的
understood this in America until three
直到三年后，美国人才明白这一点。
companies came in, which were Toyota,
参与竞争的公司包括丰田公司。
Honda, and Nissan. And they started
本田和日产。他们开始了
selling cars in America. And at first,
在美国销售汽车。起初，
it was very easy to be like, look at
很容易就能像这样，看看
these little like lawnmower toys that
这些像割草机玩具一样的小东西
they're importing, cuz you you compared
他们正在进口，因为你比较过。
like an early Honda Civic to like a
就像早期的本田思域一样
Chevy Camaro in the 70s. And it was like
70年代的雪佛兰科迈罗。感觉就像
you can't even compare them. So, at
它们根本无法相提并论。所以，在
first, the reaction of American car
首先，美国汽车的反应
companies were like, "These guys are a
公司当时的想法是：“这些人是……”
joke. No one's going to buy these little
开玩笑。没人会买这些小东西
cars." But then gas prices surged in the
汽车。”但随后汽油价格飙升。
70s and 80s and all of a sudden the cars
70年代和80年代，突然之间，汽车
that Americans wanted was the tiny
美国人想要的是一个微型的
little Honda Civic that got really good
那辆小本田思域性能真不错
gas mileage. And then once they started
燃油效率。然后，一旦他们开始
buying them, they're like, "Hey, this
买的时候，他们会说：“嘿，这个
Toyota, this Honda, this Nissan, it's
丰田，这辆本田，这辆日产，都是
actually a pretty good car. It's
其实这车还不错。它是
actually pretty well built." And I think
实际上，它的建造质量相当不错。”而且我认为
there was a lot of denial among that
其中有很多否认的声音。
among a man American manufacturers that
一位美国制造商
other these other nations that we that
其他这些国家，我们也是如此。
didn't exist for 20 years in terms of a
就此而言，它在过去20年里并不存在。
global manufacturing source. We're
全球制造资源。是
actually pretty damn good at it. Now and
实际上他做得相当不错。现在和
then one other thing happened to to wrap
然后，还有一件事需要处理。
to wrap this up and this might be the
最后总结一下，这或许就是……
most important part of it. The reason
其中最重要的部分。原因
that you cannot reasonably expect the
你不能合理地期望
manufacturing powerhouse to come back as
制造业强国将重振雄风
it was is yes, we did ship jobs to China
是的，我们确实承接了运往中国的货运业务。
and Mexico and Canada and India that
还有墨西哥、加拿大和印度。
used to be in America and that has
曾经在美国，而且
contributed to the massive decline in
导致了大幅下降
manufacturing employment. But a bigger
制造业就业。但更大的
factor in there is automation. And if
还要考虑到自动化这一因素。如果
you look at a mon like I I I would
你看着一个男人，就像我……我会
challenge people to do this. Go on
鼓励人们这样做。继续
YouTube and look at a Tesla assembly
在 YouTube 上搜索特斯拉的组装过程。
line in the United States. I'll put it
美国境内的线路。我会把它放上去。
on the screen. It is what you will see.
在屏幕上。这就是你将看到的。
It's amazing. It is a miracle of
太神奇了。这是一个奇迹
engineering. What you will see are
工程。你将会看到……
armies and armies of robots and very few
成群结队的机器人，以及极少数的……
people. And if you compare that to the
人们。如果你把这和……比较一下
1950s assembly line, what you see are
1950年代的流水线，你看到的是……
biceps and backs and people hauling
二头肌、背部和搬运重物的人
around material. So because we got so
围绕材料。所以因为我们得到了这么多
good at automation, even if we bring
擅长自动化，即使我们带来
manufacturing back to America, and that
制造业回流美国，以及这一点
we still do a lot of manufacturing in
我们仍然在很多地方进行制造。
America, it doesn't require the amount
美国，它不需要那么多钱。
of employment that it used to. Doesn't
它曾经的就业机会。不
require the amount of manpower. And the
需要一定数量的人力。以及
people who do work on Tesla
从事特斯拉相关工作的人
manufacturing lines by and large are
生产线总体上是
working on computers overseeing the
负责电脑操作和监督
robots. I mean, here's one stat that I
机器人。我的意思是，这里有一个统计数据……
thought was always interesting to me. In
我一直对思考这个话题很感兴趣。在
1950, there was a US steel plant in
1950年，有一家美国钢铁厂
Gary, Indiana. It produced 5 million
印第安纳州加里市。它生产了500万
tons of steel and had 30,000 workers.
使用了数吨钢铁，拥有 3 万名工人。
Today, it's still operating. It produces
如今，它仍在运营。它产生
8 million tons of steel and has 2,000
800万吨钢铁，拥有2000个
workers. So, it's producing more steel
工人。所以，它正在生产更多的钢铁。
today than it was in the 1950s. And they
如今的情况比上世纪50年代要好得多。他们
went from 30,000 workers to 2,000
员工人数从3万人减少到2000人
because what used to be done with biceps
因为过去对二头肌的处理方式
and backs and shoulders is now done with
背部和肩部的训练现在已经完成了。
machines and robots. And it's no
机器和机器人。而且并非如此
different than what happened in
与之前发生的事情不同
agriculture where a farm 200 years ago
200年前的农业农场
was rakes and shovels and today it's
以前是耙子和铲子，现在是……
tractors and combines. Like that same
拖拉机和联合收割机。就像那样
thing happened to assembly. So to wrap
装配线出了点问题。总结起来
all that up like I understand and I
我明白了，而且我把所有这些都说清楚了。
empathize with people who say we need to
理解那些认为我们需要……的人
bring back manufacturing to America. We
让制造业重返美国。我们
lost what we once had. I get that and I
我们失去了曾经拥有的一切。我明白了，而且
respect it. But I think the unique
尊重它。但我认为独特性
circumstances and automation makes it
环境和自动化使其变得如此。
just extremely unlikely to ever happen.
这种情况发生的概率极低。
How did China get in there? And why are
中国是怎么参与进来的？为什么会这样？
they the factory of the world? What are
他们是世界工厂吗？什么是
the core components that went into them
构成它们的核心部件
being able to produce all of the things
能够生产所有这些东西
that we use on a daily basis at a
我们每天都在使用
fraction of the price that they're able
他们能够以远低于市场价的价格出售
to produce them here? Tim Cook of Apple
在这里生产？苹果公司首席执行官蒂姆·库克
gave a really interesting interview a
接受了一次非常有趣的采访
couple weeks ago. And he said, "You
几周前。他说：“你
might think that we manufacture iPhones
可能会认为我们生产iPhone
in China because it's it's cheap labor."
在中国，因为那里的劳动力成本低廉。
And he said, "That's not really true
他说：“那并非事实。”
anymore. It used to be, but China is not
不再是了。过去是这样，但中国不再是这样了。
the cheap cheap labor country anymore.
廉价劳动力国家已不复存在。
that's moved on to Bangladesh and
这件事已经转移到孟加拉国了，
Cambodia and other places. The reason
柬埔寨和其他地方。原因
they manufacture in China is expertise.
他们在中国生产的是专业技术。
And I think it's okay to admit and
我认为承认这一点是可以的，
people should admit that your country
人们应该承认你的国家
and also your company and you
还有你的公司和你
individually can be very good at some
个人在某些方面可能非常出色。
things and not very good at others.
有些方面不太擅长，有些方面则不太擅长。
China is just extremely good and
中国真的非常优秀，
extremely talented at particularly like
极具天赋，尤其喜欢
low-end manufacturing. Low-end can be
低端制造。低端产品可能是
anything from, you know, inflatable
任何东西，你知道，比如充气的
swimming pools to on up to like basic
游泳池，就像基本款一样。
basic electronics. They're they're
基础电子学。他们是 他们是
extremely good at it. I was talking to a
非常擅长。我当时正在和……
CEO a couple weeks ago and he said uh
CEO几周前说过，呃……
and he's generalizing here, but he said
他在这里是在以偏概全，但他说道
if you go to a a Chinese factory and you
如果你去中国工厂，你
say, "I want this part made and here's
例如，“我想要制作这个零件，这是……”
step one, step two, step three on how to
第一步、第二步、第三步，教你如何
make it, they will do it better than
让他们去做，他们会做得更好
anybody in the world." Nobody can beat
世界上任何人。” 没人能打败
them at that. But if you go to that same
就这样。但如果你去那里
factory and you say, "Please go design
工厂，然后你说：“请去设计。”
me a new part." They're not very good at
给我一个新的零件。”他们不太擅长
it. Americans are way better at that.
它。美国人在这方面做得更好。
And that's why the back of your iPhone
这就是为什么你的 iPhone 背面……
says, "Designed in California, made in
上面写着：“加州设计，美国制造。”
China." Like it's just specialization of
中国。” 就像是专门从事……
labor. And I think America is the best
劳动。我认为美国是最好的。
in the world at a couple things.
在世界上，有几件事。
Entrepreneurship, technology, services,
创业、技术、服务
and like high-end manufacturing like
就像高端制造业一样
planes and rockets. And we're not the
飞机和火箭。我们并非
best in the world at low-end
世界低端市场最佳
manufacturing. And that's okay. That's
制造业。这样也没关系。那是
not an insult. That's not a put down.
这不是侮辱。那不是贬低。
There's specialization of labor. And and
存在劳动分工。而且
so I I think I think China just got very
所以我觉得中国变得非常
good at one thing during a time when
在某个时期擅长做一件事
we've always been very very good at at
我们一直都非常非常擅长
at different things. And I think that is
在不同的事情上。我认为这就是
why global like why for a lot of people
为什么是全球化的？为什么对很多人来说都是如此？
not for everybody. So if you disagree
并非人人适用。如果你不同意
with this I I get it by why the economic
有了这一点，我就能明白为什么经济……
system works so damn well over the last
过去一段时间，这套系统运行得非常出色。
30 years is because we really got good
30年是因为我们真的进步了很多。
at specialization of labor. You design
在劳动分工方面。你的设计
the iPhone, you make the iPhone, we're
iPhone，你们制造iPhone，我们制造iPhone。
both better off for it. I want to play
双方都因此受益。我想玩
that clip you're talking about with Tim
你提到的那段和蒂姆一起拍的视频片段。
Cook because I remember seeing it as
库克，因为我记得看到过它
well and it did. It was a bit of an aha
确实如此。这有点像是恍然大悟。
moment for me. For anybody that doesn't
对我来说，这是一个难忘的时刻。对于任何不了解的人来说
know, Tim Cook is the CEO of Apple and
众所周知，蒂姆·库克是苹果公司的首席执行官。
he's been at the helm of Apple for more
他执掌苹果公司已有多年。
than a decade. And as you know, most of
超过十年。正如你所知，大多数
Apple's products from what I understand
据我所知，苹果的产品
are made in China. There's a confusion
中国制造。这里存在一些混乱。
about China that uh and let me at least
关于中国，呃，至少让我说说我的看法。
give you my
给我我的
opinion. The the popular
观点。热门
conception is that companies come to
概念是公司来到这里
China because of low labor cost. I'm not
因为中国劳动力成本低。我不是
sure uh what part of China they go to,
当然，呃，他们去中国的哪个地区？
but the truth is China stopped being the
但事实是，中国不再是……
low labor cost country many years ago.
多年前劳动力成本低的国家。
And th that is not the reason to come to
而这并不是来这里的理由
China from a supply point of view. The
从供应角度来看，中国。这
reason is because of the skill and the
原因在于技能和
the quantity of skill in one location
某一地区的技能水平
and the type of skill it is like um the
而这种技能的类型就像……
products we do require really advanced
我们需要的产品确实非常先进
tooling and the the precision that you
工具和精度
have to have in tooling and working with
必须具备工具和工作能力
the materials that we do are
我们使用的材料是
state-of-the-art and the tooling skill
最先进的技术和工具技能
is very deep here. You know, in in the
这里很深。你知道，在
US, you could have a meeting of tooling
美国，你们可以开一个工具会议
engineers, and I'm not sure we could
工程师们，我不确定我们能否做到。
fill the
填写
room. In China, you could fill multi. I
房间。在中国，你可以填写多个。我
think when I watch that, I think I can
我看那个视频的时候，觉得我可以
understand why there'd be a natural
理解为什么会自然而然地
reaction for people to be like, "No, if
人们的反应可能是：“不，如果
they can do it, we can do it, too." And
他们能做到，我们也能做到。”
again, I I don't think it's an insult
我再次强调，我不认为这是一种侮辱。
when to say like countries are like
何时说“像国家一样”
we're really good at some things and
我们在某些方面确实很擅长，
less good at others. How could that not
其他方面则不太擅长。怎么可能不是
be true? Are they on a different living
是真的吗？他们过着不同的生活吗？
wage from what I understand? Oh yes,
据我了解，工资是多少？哦是的，
absolutely. I mean, so much of it is,
绝对地。我的意思是，很多事情都是如此。
you know, in, you know, if if you asked
你知道，在，你知道，如果你问
Americans to work those for those wages,
美国人从事这些工作却只拿这些工资，
they they absolutely refuse to do it
他们绝对拒绝这样做。
just because of the expectations we
仅仅因为这些期望，我们
have. And that's a good thing. We should
有。这是件好事。我们应该
be proud of that that we have a standard
我们拥有标准，我们为此感到自豪。
of living, which does not uh does not
生活，这并不，呃，并不
allow or or people would not put up with
允许或人们不会容忍
earning $5 a day or whatever it would
一天赚5美元，或者其他什么收入
be, which means that the products can be
是，这意味着产品可以是
made cheaper. Yes. Significantly
价格更低了。是的。显著地
cheaper. Right. Right. And you know,
更便宜。正确的。正确的。你知道，
this is where I I understand why people
这就是我理解人们为什么会在这里出现的原因
might raise an eyebrow at this, but so
可能会对此感到惊讶，但确实如此。
much of why of what the modern system,
现代体系的许多原因，
how it's supposed to work is when you
它的正常运作方式是当你
have that specialization, products
拥有那种专业化的产品
become cheaper and then the iPhone costs
价格会下降，然后iPhone的价格也会下降。
$1,000 when in any other world it would
在其他任何世界里，这都会是 1000 美元。
cost 4,000 if we're building it in the
如果自己建造，成本为 4,000 美元。
United States at, you know, paying wages
美国在支付工资方面，你知道的
that people would put up with in the
人们会容忍的事情
United States. So, what's the impact on
美国。那么，这会对什么产生影响？
the average person listening to this
普通听众
now? And if this trade war continues, if
现在？如果这场贸易战继续下去，如果
these tariffs continue, what is the
这些关税持续存在，这究竟意味着什么？
impact they're going to see in their
他们将会看到的影响
life? It's so unpredictable because as I
生活？这太难以预测了，因为……
said earlier, it can literally change an
如前所述，它确实可以改变一个
hour from now. So anyone giving firm
一个小时后。所以任何给出坚定承诺的人
predictions of, oh, here's what's going
预测，哦，事情是这样的
to happen next. That that's not how any
接下来会发生什么？事实并非如此。
of this works. But you can you can say
这部作品。但是你可以说
though that if the tariffs last, one of
然而，如果关税持续下去，其中之一
two things will happen or both of these
两件事会发生，或者这两件事都会发生。
two things will happen. things that we
两件事将会发生。我们
import will get much more expensive or
进口成本将会大幅上涨。
what's more more likely in places like
在类似这样的地方，更有可能发生什么呢？
China if it's 145% is we'll just the the
如果中国是145%，那我们就……
trade just stops and then you're
交易突然停止，然后你就……
probably a matter of weeks away from
可能再过几周就……
empty shelves at at certain for for
某些时候，货架空空如也。
certain products in certain cases. I
某些产品在特定情况下使用。我
mean if you're buying you know a pair of
意思是，如果你要买的话，你知道一双
slippers from China for $1 and now all
中国产拖鞋1美元一件，现在全部
of a sudden they're $245. If you're if
突然间，它们的价格涨到了 245 美元。如果你是如果
you're an importer for a lot of those
你是很多这类产品的进口商。
situations they'll say like we're just
他们会说，这种情况就像我们只是
it's just not going to work. Or if the
这根本行不通。或者如果
iPhone that used to cost $1,000 is now
以前售价1000美元的iPhone现在
going to cost $2,500. Apple might just
费用为2500美元。苹果或许会
say there's not really a market for
假设实际上并没有这样的市场
that. We can't really sell those. Let's
那。那些东西我们根本卖不出去。我们开始吧
just pause and wait for things to
暂停一下，等待事情发生。
happen. We were already seeing that. Um
发生。我们早就看到了这一点。嗯
I'm sure this news will change by the
我相信这条新闻很快就会改变。
time this airs. This is moving so
播出时间。这正在发生改变
quickly. But our shipping container
迅速地。但是我们的集装箱
imports from China have plunged in
来自中国的进口大幅下降
recent weeks, which is exactly what you
最近几周，这正是你所看到的。
would expect when you put that high of a
当你把价格定得那么高时，你会预期会得到这样的结果。
tax on it. I mean, if you were buying a
对它征税。我的意思是，如果你要买一个
house for a million dollars and all of a
价值一百万美元的房子，以及所有的一切
sudden they put on 145% tax on that,
突然间，他们对这笔税征收了145%的税。
you're probably not going to buy the
你可能不会买
house. And that's what's happening now.
房子。而这正是现在正在发生的事情。
You'd be dumb not to wait, right? I was
不等岂不是傻瓜？我当时
sat here yesterday with the CEO and she
昨天她和首席执行官一起坐在这里。
said to me that she gets the majority of
她告诉我她得到了大部分
her products, pretty much all of them
她的产品，几乎所有产品
from China. And when she's looking at
来自中国。当她看着
the tariff situation, she's figured out
她已经弄清楚了关税问题。
that if she buys those products and
如果她购买了那些产品，
sells them at her current price, she's
她按现在的价格出售它们。
losing money on every unit. So she's
每卖出一台都赔钱。所以她是
like, I'll lose $9 on importing a for
比如，我进口一个东西就要损失9美元。
example like a dress. It's like I so I
例如一件连衣裙。就像我一样
have no incentive now to continue to
现在没有动力继续下去了
sell that dress. And if my only choice
把那件裙子卖掉。如果我唯一的选择
is to raise the price by like 150% to my
就是把价格提高150%左右。
customer, right? The two likely outcomes
是顾客，对吧？两种可能的结果
if it persists are much higher prices
如果这种情况持续下去，价格会更高。
and empty shelves and then I don't think
货架空空如也，然后我就不这么认为了。
anyone knows when or to the extent that
有人知道何时或在多大程度上
could happen and the button on the desk
这种情况可能会发生，桌子上的按钮也可能会起作用。
that says end this all could be pressed
那个说要结束这一切的按钮可能会被按下。
before that happens. But if it persists,
在此之前。但如果这种情况持续下去，
that's what's likely to occur. What
这种情况很可能发生。什么
about the impact it has on trust in the
关于它对信任的影响
United States? Because yeah, it's huge.
美国？因为，是的，它非常大。
I mean, can you explain that to me?
我的意思是，你能给我解释一下吗？
Trust is hard because you don't know how
信任很难建立，因为你不知道该如何去做。
valuable it is until you lose it. But
它很珍贵，直到你失去它。但
once you lose it, you're like, "Oh, that
一旦失去了它，你就会想，“哦，那个……”
was everything." And you know, foreign
就是一切。”你知道，外国的
investors, people who don't live in the
投资者，那些不住在……的人
United States have $30 trillion invested
美国投资额达30万亿美元。
in America. That's just in stocks and
在美国。那只是股票市场的情况，
bonds. That's not housing or office
债券。那不是住房或办公楼。
buildings, just in stocks and bonds. $30
仅指股票和债券中的建筑物。 30美元
trillion that they've invested. And a
他们投资了万亿美元。以及
lot of the reason they do that, well,
他们这样做的很多原因，嗯，
there there's many reasons. One of which
原因有很多。其中之一
is because it's by and large seen as a
这是因为它在很大程度上被视为一种
trustworthy economy, a stable economy,
值得信赖的经济，稳定的经济
an economy of rules and predictable laws
规则和可预测法律的经济体系
and trusts that you could not say the
并相信你不能说
same about Russia. And so when when
俄罗斯的情况也一样。所以，当……
global investors are looking where to
全球投资者正在寻找……
park their money, it is this has been
他们把钱放在那里，这就是一直以来的情况。
the case for the last 80 years, America
过去80年来，美国的情况一直如此。
is usually at the top of that list.
通常位列榜首。
There's also a thing where a lot of the
还有一点，很多……
reason that they invest money in the
他们投资的原因
United States is because they have to
美国之所以如此，是因为他们不得不如此。
because they have a trade deficit with
因为他们与……存在贸易逆差
us. So, if China is selling us a lot
我们。所以，如果中国向我们出售大量产品的话。
more stuff than they're buying from us,
他们买的东西比他们从我们这里买的东西多，
like we're importing a lot more from
就像我们从很多地方进口了更多东西一样
China than we're exporting back to them,
中国比我们出口回他们的产品更多，
they're going to end up with a lot of US
他们最终会拥有很多美国人
dollars. And what they need to do
美元。以及他们需要做什么
something with those dollars. They have
用那些美元做点什么。他们有
they have to invest them somewhere. And
他们总得把钱投资到某个地方。和
historically, that's been in Treasury
历史上，这一直由财政部负责。
bonds, which lowered our interest rates,
债券降低了我们的利率，
and that was good for everybody. And
这对大家都有好处。和
what's a treasury bond? It's debt that
什么是国债？这是债务
the government issues from the federal
联邦政府发布的
government. So, it's a bond. You're
政府。所以，这是一种纽带。你是
you're loaning money to the government
你这是在借钱给政府
and they're promising to repay you plus
他们承诺会偿还你。
interest. Okay. So, less people are
兴趣。好的。所以，人数减少了。
going to do that if they have less trust
如果他们信任度较低，就会这样做。
in the United States. Less trust and
在美国。信任度降低
also less need to do it because they
也不太需要这样做，因为他们
don't have as many dollars that they
他们没有那么多钱
need to invest. Are we heading for a
需要投资。我们是否正走向……
recession? Because I I saw some stats
经济衰退？因为我看到了一些统计数据
earlier on that said the probability of
前面提到过，概率是
a recession has surged by 45% which is
经济衰退加剧了45%，这相当于
the highest since December 2023 because
这是自2023年12月以来的最高值，因为
of the tariffs. That was from Reuters.
关税。以上内容来自路透社。
It's interesting when people point like
当人们指着某事时，这很有趣。
the odds of recession at 45% because
经济衰退的概率为45%，原因如下
they can't be wrong. Like if if there
他们不可能出错。就像如果有的话
isn't a recession, they'd be like,
如果这不是经济衰退，他们会说：
"Yeah, we said it was 45%. We didn't say
“是的，我们说的是45%。我们没说……”
it was going to happen." So I my answer
这件事迟早会发生。”所以我的回答是……
if you said are we heading for a
如果你问我们是否正朝着……
recession would always be yes. If you
经济衰退永远是答案。如果你
asked me a year ago, if you asked me
一年前你问我过这个问题吗？
five years ago, like historically
五年前，就像历史上一样
there's a recession in modern times it's
现代社会存在经济衰退。
been every every four to five years that
大约每四到五年一次。
that it's occurred. And so we shouldn't
这件事已经发生了。所以，我们不应该
pretend that when they happen that
假装当它们发生时
they're this crazy out of the blue
他们突然就变得这么疯狂了
thing. It's an inevitable feature that
事物。这是不可避免的特征
you're always going to have recessions.
经济衰退总是会发生的。
But is this going to cause it? What is a
但这会导致这种情况发生吗？什么是
recession? A recession technically is
经济衰退？从技术上讲，经济衰退是指
when GDP in the economy GDP is just like
当经济体中的GDP就像
economic output. How much the economy is
经济产出。经济状况如何？
is moving. When that declines for two
正在移动。当这种情况持续下降两个小时
quarters in a row, that's the technical
连续四个季度，这是技术层面的。
definition. For most people, you don't
定义。对大多数人来说，你不会
need to worry about technical
无需担心技术问题
definitions because a recession in your
定义，因为经济衰退
mind is when you are feeling worse off
心情不好的时候，你会感觉更糟。
economically for a long period of time.
在经济上长期保持稳定。
When you feel like you can't get a job
当你觉得自己找不到工作的时候
or your neighbors, your roommates can't
或者你的邻居，你的室友也不能。
get jobs and and it's and it's it's
找到工作，而且，而且，而且，而且
starting to hurt on you. It's, you know,
开始让你感到疼痛。你知道，
it's kind of like what's the definition
这有点像是在问：什么是定义？
of being sick? Well, it's when you don't
生病了？嗯，就是当你没有
feel good, but there's, you can get more
感觉不错，但你还可以获得更多
technical than that, but a recession for
技术上来说，这并非全部，但经济衰退……
most people is when you don't feel good
大多数人都是在感觉不舒服的时候。
economically.
经济方面。
You're not concerned about a recession.
你并不担心经济衰退。
I It's not that I'm not concerned, but
并非我不担心，但是……
it would be like saying if you live in
这就像说如果你住在
Florida, are you concerned about uh
佛罗里达州，你们担心……
hurricanes? The answer is yes, you
飓风？答案是肯定的，你
should be concerned about hurricane, but
应该担心飓风，但是
you also know with a 100% certainty that
你也百分之百确定，
they're going to come. If you choose to
他们会来的。如果你选择
live in Florida and you live in Florida
你住在佛罗里达州，我也住在佛罗里达州。
for 40 years, you know you're going to
40年来，你知道你会……
get hit by one. 100% chance. And so it's
被一个击中。百分之百的机会。所以就是这样。
not that I don't worry about it. It's
并不是说我不担心。它是
that I think it is inevitable always, no
我认为这是不可避免的，不。
matter what's going on. This has nothing
无论发生什么。这毫无意义
to do with terrorists with tariffs.
与恐怖分子和关税有关。
That's always been the case. And so this
一直都是这样。所以就是这样
is where at the individual level
就是在个人层面上。
personally like room for error and your
我个人喜欢留有犯错的空间，还有你的
finances is so critical. What I mean by
财务状况至关重要。我的意思是
that is just like savings cushion, being
这就像是储蓄缓冲一样。
scared of debt. It's when everyone is
害怕负债。那时每个人都……
when you're wealth when you're gainfully
当你富有时，当你获得报酬时
employed and you have a good paycheck
你有一份工作，而且薪水不错。
and the stock market's going up and
股市正在上涨，
Bitcoin's going up. Everyone feels
比特币价格上涨了。每个人都有这种感觉
great. You feel amazing. And nobody It's
伟大的。你感觉棒极了。而且没有人是
very rare in that situation that you
在这种情况下，你非常罕见。
want to envision yourself losing your
想想象一下自己失去……
job or losing a job and not being able
失业或失去工作且无法
to find another one for six months or
再找一个六个月或
needing to move or getting divorced or
需要搬家或离婚或
having a medical ill. Like no one wants
患有疾病。好像没人想要
to envision that. But the truth is like
想象一下。但事实就像……
what are the odds that one of at least
至少有一名
one of these will happen to you and I
其中一件事情会发生在你和我身上。
over the next 30 years? Major job loss
未来30年呢？重大失业
or just a major impact in in our
或者只是对我们产生重大影响
businesses? Divorce, cancer, wayward
企业？离婚、癌症、任性
children. I can go on down the What are
孩子们。我可以继续往下说，什么是
the odds that at least one of those will
至少其中一人出现的概率
occur to you and I in 30 years? 100%.
30年后你我是否也会想到这一点？ 100%。
And for a lot of people, they will
对很多人来说，他们会
experience all of those. And so the idea
体验所有这些。所以这个想法
that life is fragile, the economy is
生命脆弱，经济也是如此。
fragile, countries are fragile, is like
脆弱，国家很脆弱，就像
people don't necessarily want to admit
人们未必愿意承认
that because it's hard to get out of bed
因为起床太难了
in the morning if you admitted that to
早上如果你承认这一点的话
yourself. But I think it's inevitable
你自己。但我认为这是不可避免的。
and it doesn't have to be necessarily
而且也不一定非得如此
scary if you have the right like
如果你有权利喜欢它，那就很可怕了。
psychology around it of just yeah, like
围绕它的心理学方面，嗯，就像
when times are good, I don't expect them
顺境的时候，我不指望他们
to last forever. That's not how the
永恒。事情并非如此。
world works. and the right finances
世界运转。以及充足的资金
around it of like, yeah, when times are
围绕着它，就像，是的，当时代是
good, I'm gonna save because I know this
好，我要存起来，因为我知道这一点。
might not last forever. And what I value
可能不会永远持续下去。以及我所珍视的
more than anything with money is
比任何与金钱有关的事情都更重要
independence. It's not flashy cars or
独立。这不是炫酷的汽车，也不是……
homes. I want to be independent so that
房屋。我想独立，这样
when the economy goes south and there is
当经济下滑时，
a recession and things are going bad, I
经济衰退，情况越来越糟，我
want to have a level of control over
希望对……拥有一定程度的控制权
where I work, where I live, what I'm
我的工作地点，我的居住地，我的职业
able to do, my ability to support my
能够做到，我有能力养活自己
family. that's more than that's that's
家庭。那比那还要多，那是
the top of the list. And so when things
榜首。所以当事情发生时
are going well and for a lot of people
进展顺利，对很多人来说都是如此。
they haven't for the last couple years
过去几年他们都没有这样做。
but for a lot of people they did. I
但对很多人来说，事实的确如此。我
think that's always important is like I
我认为始终很重要的一点是，就像我
think I think it's a major psychological
我认为这是一个重要的心理因素。
skill in life in general. This goes
生活技能。就这样
beyond money is recognizing when things
超越金钱的是认识到何时该做什么
are abnormally good and preparing
异常出色，并且正在准备中
yourself for them to go the other way as
你自己让他们朝相反的方向走，
they as they inevitably will.
他们终将如此。
Independence you value it sounded like
独立，你很看重它，听起来像
freedom to me. Yeah. Can you tell me how
对我而言，这是自由。是的。你能告诉我如何
to achieve freedom
实现自由
financially and what I should be
经济上以及我应该如何生活
thinking about in the context of a world
在世界背景下思考
that's changing at such incredible speed
这种情况正以惊人的速度变化。
when we're talking about tariffs and
当我们谈论关税和
recessions and now AI? I've been
经济衰退，现在又是人工智能？我一直
thinking over the last couple of weeks
过去两周的思考
like what should my f personal financial
比如我的个人财务状况应该如何？
strategy be? How should I be thinking
策略是什么？我应该怎么想？
about it? Is it a strategy? Is it a
关于它？这是策略吗？它是
psychology? Is it a mindset? What is it
心理学？这是一种思维方式吗？它是什么？
that I should be thinking about to
我应该考虑一下
survive this area of tremendous change
在这片剧烈变革的土地上生存下去
and Trump economics and get through the
以及特朗普的经济政策，并度过难关
other end with that freedom and
自由的另一端
independence that you and I both
你我都拥有的独立性
desperately value? This sounds like such
极度重视？听起来像是
a a squishy BS kind of answer, but I
一个含糊不清、敷衍了事的回答，但我
think there's a lot of there's a lot of
我觉得有很多，有很多
truth to this and I'll explain in a
这确实属实，我会在下文中解释。
second. It is largely a mindset and that
第二。这很大程度上是一种心态。
that sounds crazy, but I'll explain what
听起来很疯狂，但我会解释的。
I mean. My grandmother-in-law, she
我是说。我的婆婆，她
passed away a couple years ago. She was
几年前去世了。她
92 when when she passed away. She for 30
她去世时享年92岁。她30岁
years she lived off of nothing but
她多年来一无所有地生活着，
social security. I think she got $1,700
社会保障。我认为她拿到了1700美元。
a month from social security and she had
她离领取社保金还有一个月的时间，而且她……
nothing else. No savings, no pension, no
仅此而已。没有积蓄，没有养老金，没有
nothing. She was the happiest person you
没有什么。她是你见过的最快乐的人。
I've met half a half a dozen
我见过六个左右。
billionaires in my life. I'm sure you
我生命中遇到的亿万富翁。我确信你
have as well. None of them were as happy
我也一样。他们都不太高兴。
as she was. And she was technically she
她本来就是这样。严格来说，她就是她
was like financially broke. But she had
当时感觉自己经济拮据。但她有
this level of psychological wealth that
这种程度的心理财富
was like unparalleled. And the reason
简直是无与伦比。原因
was off $1,700 a month. That was all she
每月节省 1700 美元。这就是她全部的感受。
needed. She was perfectly happy toiling
需要。她非常乐意辛勤劳作。
in her garden, watching birds, going for
在她的花园里，看着鸟儿，去
walks, hanging out, reading from books
散步、闲逛、读书
from the library. Perfectly content with
从图书馆借阅。非常满意
all of that. She didn't need anything
所有这些。她什么都不需要。
else. So, she had very little money, but
别的。所以，她当时几乎没什么钱，但是
she wanted even less. And that so like
她想要的更少。就是这样
she had a level of independence that a
她拥有相当程度的独立性。
lot of billionaires do not because if
很多亿万富翁都不这样做，因为如果
you are a billionaire, if you have a
如果你拥有……，你就是亿万富翁。
billion dollars in the bank, but you are
银行里有十亿美元，但你
so encumbered by your business, your
你的生意让你不堪重负，你的
employees, your suppliers, your
员工、供应商、您的
customers, you're waking up at 3 in the
顾客们，你们凌晨3点就要起床了。
morning sweating because you got this
早上出汗是因为你做到了
email and you're stressed out about it.
你因为收到邮件而感到压力很大。
You actually have very little
你实际上拥有的很少。
independence in that situation. Your
在这种情况下保持独立。你的
shareholders or regulators are coming
股东或监管机构即将到来
down on you. I mean, we see this I'm not
瞧不起你。我的意思是，我们看到这一点，我不是。
there's no one in particular here, but
这里并没有特别指谁，但是
we've seen very wealthy people kind of
我们见过一些非常富有的人，他们有点像……
become syncopants to politicians and and
成为政客们的同步者，
the truth is a lot of those ex like mega
事实是，很多前任都像超级巨星一样。
billionaires absolutely rely on
亿万富翁们完全依赖于
politicians and regulators to keep their
政客和监管机构要保持他们的
machine moving. And so my
机器运转。所以，我的
grandmother-in-law on $1,700 a month had
岳母每月收入1700美元。
a higher level of independence than a
比……更高的独立性
lot of those people do. And I that's why
很多人都这么做。这就是原因
I say like a lot of this is a mindset
我觉得很多时候这是一种心态。
because the truth is the vast majority
因为事实是，绝大多数
of people listening to this could have a
听这段音频的人中，可能有……
level of independence. It's not it's not
独立程度。不是，不是
that you can retire tomorrow, but you
你明天就可以退休，但是你
can have a level of financial
可以达到一定的财务水平
independence once you realize that the
一旦你意识到独立的重要性，
key is managing your expectations more
关键在于更好地管理你的期望。
than it is how can I just pile up as
比这更糟，我怎么能就这样堆积起来呢？
much money as I as I possibly can. It's
尽可能多地攒钱。它是
easy to think like how do you become
很容易想到，你如何才能成为
financially independent? Like save a ton
经济独立？省了一大笔钱
of money. And there like there there
钱。就像那里一样
there's truth to that of like like of
确实有类似的说法。
course that's part of it but more of it
当然，这只是其中一部分，但远不止于此。
is just in like what kind of life do you
就像，你想要过什么样的生活？
want to live because if your
想活下去，因为如果你
expectations are growing faster than
期望值增长速度超过预期。
your net worth it's never going to feel
你的净资产永远不会让你感到
like you you'll never be independent.
像你这样的人，永远也无法独立。
Never. You have a hundred billion
绝不。你有1000亿
dollars but if you want more and more
用美元，但如果你想要更多
and more like it's it's never going to
更确切地说，它永远不会发生。
feel like it's enough. Or if if you
感觉够了。或者如果你
enjoy bird watching and reading books
喜欢观鸟和读书
like my grandmother-in-law 1,700 bucks a
就像我岳母一样，1700美元
month you're all set. You're set for 30
一个月后你就一切就绪了。你已经准备好迎接30
years. You're rich. you're rich and
年。你很有钱。你很有钱，而且
free. She was psychologically rich even
自由的。她心理上很富有
if she was financially poor. And I think
如果她经济困难。我觉得
that's that's the biggest thing about
这就是最重要的一点。
it. Adam Smith, who was the greatest
它。亚当·斯密，他是最伟大的
economist to ever live, this was 300
这是有史以来最伟大的经济学家，300
years ago. He once wrote about this. He
几年前。他曾就此写过文章。他
was like, why do people work so hard?
我当时就在想，为什么人们要这么努力工作？
And he he was just like, it's a simple
他当时就说，这很简单
question, but why why do people work so
问题是，为什么人们要如此努力工作？
damn hard? And he's like, it can't just
真难？他就像是，这不可能只是
be for for our sustenance because even
为了我们的生存，因为即使
poor people, as he was writing about it,
他在书中写道，穷人……
had uh homes and adequate food most of
大多数人都有住所和充足的食物
the time. He's like, "There has to be
时间。他就像在说：“必须要有……”
something else." And what that something
还有一些别的东西。”那是什么呢？
else was, he wrote, "Was to be seen by
否则，他写道，“将被看到”
other people." And it was it was like it
其他人。” 事情就是这样。
was attention and admiration. They
是关注和钦佩。他们
wanted to be getting rich so that they
他们想变得富有，这样他们
could have a bigger house and a and a
可以拥有更大的房子，以及一个
nice car. Not in his day, but they they
好车。在他那个年代不是这样，但他们……
wanted to be they wanted attention from
他们想要成为他们想要的那种人，他们想要得到关注。
other people. But he was like, "It's not
别人。但他却说：“不是这样的。”
that you needed the money." Because even
你需要这笔钱。”因为即使
in his day, 300 years ago in in
在他那个时代，300年前的……
Scotland, I think he was, he was like,
苏格兰，我想他是，他就像，
"Look, people have homes and food. Like,
“你看，人们有房子有食物。就像，
what what what are they doing this for?"
他们到底在干什么？他们这样做的目的是什么？
And he was not criticizing then. like
当时他并没有批评。喜欢
his whole point was like they're going
他的重点是，他们要走了
out and innovating or going to have
走出去，进行创新，或者即将拥有
great technology and like it's great to
很棒的技术，而且感觉很棒
go do that but the reason to do it was
去做那件事，但去做这件事的理由是
not because they had to stop. Now of
并非因为他们不得不停下来。现在是
course most people to get shelter and
当然，大多数人需要找到住处。
food do have to keep working but they're
食品行业确实需要继续运作，但他们
working more than they absolutely need
工作时间超过了他们绝对需要的时长。
to because they want something else
因为他们想要别的东西。
besides independence. Is there an
除了独立性之外。是否有
evolutionary basis for this? I was I was
这是进化论的依据吗？我当时
thinking the other day after watching an
前几天看完一个视频后，我在想……
interview with Naval where Naval talks
海军接受采访，海军在采访中谈到
about
关于
how evolutionary perspective humans
人类的进化视角
don't really understand the concept of
不太理解这个概念
wealth because once upon a time when we
财富源于很久以前我们
were cave men and women wealth was what
穴居男女的财富是什么？
you could carry but we do understand the
你可以携带，但我们理解。
concept of status which really meant a
地位的概念，实际上意味着
lot to us in our sort of tribes and was
对我们这些部落来说，很多事情都是如此。
life or death for many of us. So even
对我们许多人来说，这是生死攸关的事。所以即使
though billionaires get all the money in
虽然亿万富翁们获得了所有的钱。
the world the next thing they want to do
世界上他们接下来想做什么
is start a podcast. Yeah. Do you know
开始做播客。是的。你知道吗
what I mean? Right. Right. Because it's
我的意思是？正确的。正确的。因为是
just not enough. Like everyone I know
还不够。就像我认识的每个人一样
what a lot of them do too is when they
他们中的许多人还会这样做，当他们
have all the money in the world, what
拥有全世界的财富，又能怎样呢？
they want is immortality. And you see
他们想要的是永生。你看
these guys trying to live forever kind
这些人试图永生，善良
of thing. So that happens as well.
事物。这种情况也会发生。
That's interesting. But that's linked to
那很有意思。但这与……有关
status because status was longevity.
因为长寿就是地位的象征。
Yes. Like if you had status, you had
是的。比如，如果你有地位，你就会……
food, you had the reproductive potential
食物，你拥有生育能力
once upon a time. Yeah. So it's the same
曾几何时。是的。所以结果是一样的。
evolutionary sort of desire to like live
进化论意义上的渴望，即喜欢生活
survival. Yeah. Harvey uh Firestone who
生存。是的。哈维·费尔斯通
was a a tire magnet a 100 years ago.
一百年前，它曾是轮胎磁铁。
Firestone tires during the explosion in
爆炸期间，凡士通轮胎
cars 100 years ago. He wrote about this
100年前的汽车。他写过关于这件事的文章。
in his biography. He was like every rich
在他的传记中。他就像所有富人一样。
person he knows once they get money buys
他认识的某个人一旦有了钱就会买
a house that is way too big than they
一栋比他们想象中大得多的房子
need. Not not only bigger than they
需要。不仅比他们大
need, bigger than they want because a
需要比他们想要的更大，因为
giant house is just a huge pain in the
巨大的房子简直就是个巨大的麻烦。
ass. The roof is leaking and like
屁股。屋顶漏水，而且
everything's breaking down. It's a huge
一切都崩溃了。这是一个巨大的
pain to manage. So he wrote his
疼痛需要控制。于是他写下了他的
biography, he was like why do we do
写传记的时候，他就像在问，我们为什么要这么做？
this? And he was like I he was he he did
这？他就像我一样，他就是他，他确实
it too. He's like, "I bought a house
也是。他说：“我买了一套房子
that is way bigger than I want and it's
那比我想要的要大得多，而且
a pain. It's a burden, but we all do
真麻烦。这是一种负担，但我们所有人都是如此。
it." And he's like, "Why?" And he's
“就是它。”然后他就问，“为什么？”然后他就
like, "It has to be status. There's no
比如，“这必须是身份象征。没有其他因素。”
utility to a 40-bedroom house. Zero.
为一栋拥有 40 个卧室的房子提供公用设施。零。
There's a lot of downside in upkeep."
维护保养方面有很多弊端。
But he's like, "Every one of us does
但他却说：“我们每个人都这样做。”
it." And he said, "Even Henry Ford, who
“它。” 他说，“就连亨利·福特，他
was like the cheapest sob out there,
简直就是最廉价的哭泣者，
lived in a giant mansion in Detroit." He
他住在底特律的一座巨型豪宅里。
was like, "It's so natural." And he was
当时我就想：“这太自然了。”他就是
like, "It's just because we we we want
比如，“这只是因为我们想要
to show other people. It's not utility.
给其他人看。这不是实用性问题。
It's not making our lives better. It's
它并没有让我们的生活变得更好。它是
actually making our life worse, but we
实际上却让我们的生活变得更糟，但我们
we have this evolutionary desire to show
我们天生就有这种展现自我的欲望
people that we've made it. That's that's
我们已经成功了。就是这样。
the calling card. But if it's hardwired,
名片。但如果它是预先设定的，
then is there much we can do about it? I
那么我们对此能做些什么呢？我
think it's true that virtually everyone
认为几乎所有人都是这种情况。
who I really admire in life, they're by
我生活中真正敬佩的人，他们都在……
and large they're not hugely successful
而且规模很大，但它们并没有取得巨大的成功。
people that you've heard of. They're
你听说过的人。他们是
just people who I've met and they're
只是我遇到的一些人，他们是
ordinary people with ordinary jobs. And
从事普通工作的普通人。和
I'm like, man, you seem like you've got
我心想，老兄，你看上去好像已经……
it all figured out. They took themselves
一切都解决了。他们把自己
out of the system that they were
他们脱离了那个体系。
supposed to be in and they're like, I'm
应该在里面，但他们却说，我是
just gonna go figure out my own way. And
我打算自己想办法。和
there's a a really interesting story, a
这是一个非常有趣的故事，
guy named Chuck Feny, he started a
一个名叫查克·芬尼的人，他创办了一个
company called uh DFS, the uh duty-free
这家公司叫DFS，也就是免税店
stores in airports. He made I think at
机场内的商店。他让我想到
the peak of his wealth, he was worth
在他财富的巅峰时期，他身价高达……
about $9 billion. And this was like in
约90亿美元。这就像在
the '9s when that was a that was a lot
90年代，那真是一段很长的时光。
of money. Still is a lot of money. But
钱。仍然是一大笔钱。但
he uh the the well-known part of Chuck
他呃，查克的著名部分
Feny is that despite that wealth, he
费尼认为，尽管他拥有财富，但他
lived like an ordinary person. and he
过着普通人的生活。而他
lived in a like a one-bedroom apartment.
住在类似一居室的公寓里。
He flew coach. He drove like a a like a
他坐的是经济舱。他开车就像……
a normal car. Lived like a normal guy.
一辆普通的汽车。过着普通人的生活。
And some people criticize that from that
有些人因此批评这一点。
he he gave all of his money to charity.
他把所有的钱都捐给了慈善机构。
He gave nine billion away. Lived like a
他捐出了90亿美元。过着像……一样的生活
monk himself. The less known part of
僧侣本人。鲜为人知的部分
Chuck Feny that I think is is very is is
我认为查克·芬尼非常……
more important is that when he first got
更重要的是，当他第一次获得
wealth, became wealthy in the 1980s, he
他于上世纪80年代积累了财富。
lived the life of a billionaire. He had
过上了亿万富翁的生活。他曾
a fleet of private jets. He had mansions
一支私人飞机队。他拥有豪宅
all over the world. He had a yacht. And
遍布世界各地。他有一艘游艇。和
after doing it for a couple years, he's
做了几年之后，他……
like, "I don't like any of this." He's
比如，“我一点都不喜欢这些。”他是
like, "I I I like being an ordinary,
比如，“我喜欢做一个普通人，
simple person, and so I'm going to go
我是一个简单的人，所以我要走了
live an ordinary life. I don't care what
过平凡的生活。我不在乎什么
the world the world tells me this is
世界告诉我，这就是世界。
what I should want now that I have
我现在应该想要什么？
money." But he's like, "But I don't. I
钱。”但他却说，“但我没有。”我
want simplicity." And what I like about
我想要简单。”而我喜欢的是
that is not that he chose to live like a
那并不是他选择像……那样生活。
monk because I I personally wouldn't
因为我个人不会选择和尚。
want to do that if I had that I I I
如果我拥有那个，我想那样做。
would have a jet if I had that kind of
如果我有足够的钱，我肯定会买一架喷气式飞机。
money. So, it's not to say that he did
钱。所以，这并不是说他确实这么做了。
it right, but what I like that he did is
没错，但我喜欢他做的是……
that he said, "I don't care what the
他说：“我不在乎……”
world tells me to like. I'm I'm I'm
世界告诉我应该喜欢。我 我 我
going to do it on my own terms." And
我要按照自己的方式去做。”
that like that's true independence.
那才是真正的独立。
That's true status. That is that's true
这才是真实情况。没错，确实如此。
status, too. He's like, "I don't care."
地位也很重要。他就像在说：“我不在乎。”
That's the ultimate definition of FU
这就是“FU”的终极定义。
money of like so much money that like I
钱，就像很多很多钱，就像我
don't care like you you tell me I'm
别像你一样在乎，你告诉我我是
supposed to live in a mansion in Beverly
应该住在贝弗利的一座豪宅里
Hills, but I like my one-bedroom
虽然有山丘，但我喜欢我的一居室。
apartment in San Francisco. I like my
旧金山的一套公寓。我喜欢我的
buddies over here. Another person who's
这边有哥们儿。另一个人是
done that to a very real extent is
在很大程度上已经做到了这一点。
Warren Buffett. lives in the same house
沃伦·巴菲特。住在同一栋房子里
today that he bought when he was 27 or
今天，他27岁时买的那件东西
whatever it was. And he's got 100
不管那是什么。他有100
billion or something, right? And of
十亿左右吧？以及
course, he could live anywhere. He could
当然，他可以住在任何地方。他可以
buy anything, but he likes being with
他什么都买，但他喜欢和……在一起
his friends, doing it on, you know,
他的朋友们，你知道，就是这么做的。
likes playing uh bridge with his
他喜欢和他一起玩桥牌
buddies. In the first case, though, that
好朋友。但在第一种情况下，
gentleman had to have his dream fail him
这位绅士的梦想注定要破灭。
first before he realized. And so this
在他意识到之前。所以就是这样
raises another question which is am I
这又引出了另一个问题：我是否……
does the viewer at home have to make the
电视机前的观众需要做出什么决定？
hund00 million and then taste it buy the
一亿，然后尝尝，买下它
mansion to realize that it was never
意识到那座豪宅从未存在过
about the mansion. I think the answer to
关于这座豪宅。我认为答案是
that is yes. Oh gosh. That it's very
是的。我的天哪。确实如此
difficult. You know there's there's a
难的。你知道那里有一个
thing where I I forget who said this but
我忘了是谁说的这句话了，但是
like they're responding to the quote
就像他们在回应这句话一样
money doesn't buy happiness and they're
金钱买不到幸福，而且他们是
like okay but let me go figure that out
好吧，让我去弄清楚。
for myself first. Like if you don't have
首先是为了我自己。如果你没有
a lot of money and you see rich people
很多钱，你会看到有钱人
tripping over themselves and people like
绊倒自己和像
Will Smith saying like I was no happier
威尔·史密斯说，我当时也并不高兴。
at all when I was rich than when I was
当我富有的时候，我比当我贫穷的时候更甚。
poor. Actually, I was happier when I was
贫穷的。事实上，我以前更快乐
poor. If if you are poor, when you hear
贫穷的。如果你很穷，当你听到
that, you're like, "Bullshit. I don't
你会想，“胡说八道。我才不呢。”
believe it. I have to go figure it out
相信我。我得去弄清楚。
for myself." I think a lot of lessons in
就我个人而言。”我认为很多经验教训
life you have to learn firsthand.
人生百态，必须亲身经历才能领悟。
Especially when the all the problems
尤其是当所有问题都出现的时候
staring you in your face are somewhat
直勾勾地盯着你看的东西有点……
associated to money. Like the pain in
与金钱有关。就像疼痛一样
your belly, the bills on your desk, the
你的肚子，你桌上的账单，
threats from the court. I'm thinking of
来自法院的威胁。我在想……
myself here that I was getting the the
我自己在这里表示我正在获得
letters coming through with the red text
字母以红色文字显示出来
on them telling me that my credit cards
他们告诉我我的信用卡
were expo um going to be shut down, the
如果世博会要关闭，
inability to feed yourself, to socialize
无法自理，无法社交
with your friends, the heating in your
和朋友们一起，享受着暖气。
house, the your child's pencil case
房子，你孩子的铅笔盒
costs, all of it seems to circle back to
成本，这一切似乎最终都会回到原点。
money. And so when you
钱。所以当你
hear people who are
听到人们说
wealthy being subjectively honest about
富人主观上诚实地谈论
their own experience and then what's
他们自身的经历，以及接下来会发生什么。
made them happy, it is hard to hear.
听到这话，他们感到很开心，真让人难过。
Yeah. Like I I was just imagining if I
是的。就像我刚才在想象如果我
was hearing this, you know, these
我听到这些，你知道，这些
stories when I was in that situation, I
当我身处那种境地时，我讲述了我的故事。
would still [__] go for it anyway.
即便如此，我还是会他妈的去做。
Right now, let's say there's a there's a
现在，假设有一个
big difference between not being able to
无法做到和能够做到之间有很大的区别
buy food for your kids. Yeah. And making
给孩子买食物。是的。并制作
200 grand per year. Yeah. And and you
每年20万美元。是的。还有你
know, the the the the difference between
知道，这之间的区别
10 grand a year and 200 grand a year is
年薪1万美元和年薪20万美元是
massive. Takes away so many stresses, so
大量的。它能减轻很多压力，所以
many, you know, worries about being
你知道，很多人担心自己会……
evicted and whatnot. But the difference
被驱逐之类的。但区别在于
between 200 grand and 500 grand is not
20万到50万之间并不算什么。
that much. And the difference between
就这么多。以及两者之间的区别
500 grand and 20 million is not that
50万和2000万可不是一回事。
much. And the difference between 20
很多。 20 之间的区别
million and 20 billion is zero. I think
百万和200亿是零。我认为
that's that's a lot of what it comes
这就是它所包含的大部分内容。
down to. And even I think there is such
向下。甚至我认为确实存在这种情况。
thing as like a peak net worth that you
比如你的净资产峰值。
would want in life after which all the
之后，你会想要在生活中做的一切
money that you acrew becomes like a
你所积累的钱就像……
social liability. I mean who has more
社会责任。我的意思是，谁拥有的更多？
social liability or like pressure than
社会责任或类似压力
the mega rich you know Elon Musk, Bill
你认识的超级富豪，比如埃隆·马斯克、比尔·盖茨
Gates, Jeff Bezos. There's a huge amount
盖茨，杰夫·贝佐斯。数量非常庞大
of pressure. like you better donate this
压力。你最好把这个捐出去。
money and you better do a good job doing
钱，你最好好好干。
it kind of thing. And so and I think
就是那种事。所以，我认为
that number of like and at a much lower
点赞数和点赞数都远低于这个水平
like realistic level for people it's
就像现实生活中人们所处的环境一样。
when your friends learn you make a lot
当你的朋友知道你赚了很多钱时
of money and we go out for dinner and
我们用钱出去吃饭
they're like you're you're paying right
他们就像在说，你付的钱对吗？
and that's that's a small thing but it
那虽然是件小事，但是……
can really great on people that like oh
对喜欢“哦”的人来说真的很棒
it's going to change how people think
这将改变人们的思维方式。
about me now that that's a good problem
现在对我来说，这倒是个好问题。
to have of course but it's a thing and I
当然要有，但这确实是一件事情，而且我
think the idea of there is a maximum
认为存在一个最大值的想法
amount of like there is a net worth
净资产的数量就像……
level at which your happiness is going
你的幸福程度
to be maximized and it's probably lower
最大化，而且可能更低
than you think. Do you think it's
比你想象的要好。你觉得是吗？
important for people to have an idea
让人们有想法很重要。
what their number is? I don't think
他们的电话号码是多少？我不认为
anyone really does because I've done
真的有人这么做吗？因为我已经这么做过了。
this in my own life. I'm sure you have
我自己的经历就是如此。我相信你肯定有
too. When I was 19, I was like, "Oh, if
也。我19岁的时候，心想：“哦，如果
my net worth was this amount, I I'll be
我的净资产是这个数额，我将是
happy forever." And then I was fortunate
“永远幸福。”然后我就很幸运了。
enough to get hit that amount and I'm
足以让我损失那么多钱，而我
like, "Okay, but what if what if we got
比如，“好吧，但是如果我们得到……”
over here?" And you just keep going up
这边？”然后你就一直往上走。
the ladder forever. Is there such thing
永远的梯子。真有这种东西吗？
as FU money? Like, is there a number
用这笔钱？比如，有没有一个数字
where you think you've hit FU money? I
你觉得你赚到多少钱了？我
saw some thread on Twitter and it was
在推特上看到一些帖子，内容是
like, "Comment below what you think FU
比如，“在下方评论你的想法 FU”
money is." And it was interesting to see
金钱就是一切。”看到这一点很有意思。
the variation. I have a friend Ben
变化。我有个朋友叫本。
Carlson. He's a great financial writer.
卡尔森。他是一位优秀的财经作家。
He came up, this is very subjective.
他提出了这个想法，但这非常主观。
There's no science behind this, but he
这背后没有任何科学依据，但他
was like a net worth of 7 to10 million
相当于700万到1000万美元的净资产。
is you can live an amazing life in the
你可以过上精彩的生活
United States, have an amazing house
美国，拥有一座令人惊叹的房子
paid for, send your kids to great
付费，送你的孩子去上好学校
schools, go on great vacations, drive
上学、去度假、开车
brand new cars on 7 to10 million. Um,
全新汽车售价700万至1000万。嗯，
and and and he brought that up. Some
而且他还提到了这件事。一些
people might might wse at this, but he
人们可能会对此感到困惑，但他
brought that up of it's a lot less than
提到这一点，它比
people would think because there'd be a
人们会认为，因为会有一个
lot of people who would be like, "Oh,
很多人会说：“哦，
I'm gunned for hundred million." Even if
我的目标是一亿。” 即使
that's just a fantasy, it's a dream. And
那只是幻想，只是个梦。和
$79 million is out of reach for for a
7900万美元对一个人来说遥不可及。
lot of people, no matter how hard
很多人，无论多么努力
they're working. But I think
他们正在工作。但我认为
particularly for young people who their
尤其是对于年轻人而言，他们的
definition of I think about my son a
“我想到我的儿子”的定义
lot. This he watches Mr. Beast. Mr.
很多。他正在观看 Mr. Beast 的节目。先生。
Beast is an amazing guy. He's I think
Beast真是个了不起的人。我觉得他
he's one of the great guys. But because
他是个很棒的人。但是因为
of Mr. It's like my son's definition of
先生。这就像我儿子对……的定义
wealth is a private island, a private
财富就像一座私人岛屿，一个私人的
jet, you know, keep your hand on the
你知道，把手放在喷气式飞机上。
table and win a million dollars kind of
桌上赢一百万美元之类的
thing. It's a it's a different level.
事物。这是一个不同的层次。
Whereas when I was growing up, like
而当我还是个孩子的时候，就像
ordinary people drove dirty pickup
普通人开着脏兮兮的皮卡
trucks and rich people drove clean
卡车和富人驾驶清洁车辆
pickup trucks. That was like that was
皮卡车。就是这样。
the stratification of what I saw growing
我所看到的生长过程呈现出分层现象。
up. And I think because of social media
向上。我认为这是因为社交媒体
and other things, kids have a very
以及其他方面，孩子们非常
different view on what of like financial
对金融等领域的不同看法
wealth actually is these days. Going
如今，财富的本质依然存在。去
back to this issue of tariffs,
回到关税问题上来，
recession, and everything that's going
经济衰退，以及所有正在发生的事情
on at the moment, are there any things
目前有什么事情吗？
practically for those that don't
实际上，对于那些不了解的人来说，并非如此。
understand the economy and economics
了解经济和经济学
generally that we should be thinking
一般来说，我们应该这样想
about to make sure that we don't get
正要确保我们不会……
burnt? This is less advice going
烧焦了？这算不上什么建议
forward, more than just like something
向前，不仅仅是像某种东西
to remember next time, which is that if
下次要记住，如果
you are worrying about if you're worried
如果你担心，你正在担心什么？
about being laid off, if you're a small
关于被裁员，如果你是小
business owner worried about going
企业主担心外出
under, the need for room for error and
其次，需要留出犯错的空间和
cushion and savings and backup plans are
缓冲资金、储蓄和备用计划
were were just as important a month ago
一个月前，它们同样重要。
as they are today. You're just learning
就像他们今天这样。你还在学习中
how important they are today. And I
它们在今天是多么重要啊。我
challenge you to remember that in the
请你记住这一点
future when this is all over, whenever
当这一切结束时，无论何时
it's all over, that when the economy is
一切都结束了，当经济……
going well and you feel stable in your
一切顺利，你感觉很稳定。
job, stable in your career, that is when
工作稳定，事业有成，那时
you also you absolutely need backup
你也绝对需要备份
plans and room for error and savings and
计划、容错空间和节省空间
assuing debt and whatnot. I have a very
发行债务等等。我非常
high level of cash as a percentage of my
现金占我收入的比例很高
net worth and a lot of financial
净资产和大量财务
adviserss would look at that and say
顾问们会审视这一点并说
like, "What are you saving for? Like
比如，“你在攒钱干什么？”
what's what's going on here?" And I'm
这里到底发生了什么事？而我
like, "I I don't know. I'm saving for a
比如，“我不知道。我正在攒钱……”
world that I know is very fragile and I
我所了解的世界非常脆弱，而我
have no idea what's going to happen to
完全不知道接下来会发生什么
me personally or what's going to happen
就我个人而言，或者说将会发生什么？
to the economy. But if you're a lay
对经济而言。但如果你是个外行
student of history, you know that things
作为历史系学生，你应该知道很多事情
break all the time. And and so my advice
经常休息。所以，我的建议是……
to you if you're realizing that for the
如果你意识到这一点，对你来说就……
first time that how fragile the world
第一次意识到世界有多么脆弱
can be and how the job security that you
可以是什么，以及你的工作保障如何。
thought you had might might not have
你以为你可能没有
been as strong, remember this next time.
下次要保持坚强，记住这一点。
how important room for error and backup
容错空间和备份的重要性
plans are. And relative to your personal
计划是。就你个人而言
costs, your personal monthly costs or
费用，您的个人每月费用或
overheads as they call them. How much
他们称之为运营成本。多少
money do you think it's sensible to have
你觉得拥有金钱是明智的吗？
saved? It's so it's so hard for that
已保存？这件事真的太难了。
because everyone's in a I'm sure people
因为每个人都处于一种我确信人们的状态
watching this will be in a massive range
观看这个节目将会是一个庞大的群体。
of of incomes. I I would say this is a a
收入。我会说这是一个
bad answer that no one's going to like,
没人会喜欢的糟糕答案
but as pretty much as much as you can. I
但尽可能多地做到。我
mean, I'll give you one example of this.
我举个例子来说明这一点。
When COVID first hit in March of 2020,
2020年3月新冠疫情爆发之初，
the average restaurant, I heard, had
我听说，平均每家餐厅都有
enough cash on hand to last them for 14
手头有足够的现金，足够他们用14个月。
days and then all of a sudden they were
几天后，突然之间，他们就……
looking at a six-month lockdown. And so
预计封锁将持续六个月。所以
I think one answer to that question is
我认为这个问题的一个答案是
however much you think you you'll need,
无论你认为自己需要多少，
it's probably more. The other more
可能不止这些。另一个更多
practical example of this is in 2008
2008 年就是一个实际例子。
during the financial crisis, a lot of
在金融危机期间，很多
people were losing their jobs not for
人们失去工作并非因为
two weeks or one month, but they losing
两周或一个月，但他们输了
their jobs for 12 months and they got
他们工作了12个月，然后他们得到了
unemployment benefits, but it wasn't
失业救济金，但并非如此。
enough. And so is it practical for to
足够的。那么，这样做是否实际呢？
say like you should have 12 months of
比如说你应该有12个月的
saving? It's probably not practical for
保存？这可能不太实际
a lot of people. But the answer is as
很多人。但答案是：
much as you can while realizing that the
尽可能多地这样做，同时也要意识到……
world is more fragile than you probably
世界比你想象的要脆弱得多。
think it is. The other protagonist of
我觉得是。另一位主角
change at the moment is artificial
目前的改变是人为的。
intelligence. And I've spent a lot of
智力。我花了很多时间
lonely quiet hours in my room thinking
独自一人在房间里，静静地思考着，度过了许多孤独的时光。
about the impact it's going to have and
关于它将产生的影响以及
trying to develop my own thesis and what
我正在尝试发展自己的论文，以及什么
it means as a creator, as a podcaster,
这意味着作为一名创作者，作为一名播客主播，
as a investor. And I wanted to
作为投资者。而我当时想
understand how significant you think
理解你的想法有多么重要
artificial intelligence is and if it at
人工智能是，如果它在
all impacts your thesis around money and
所有这些都会影响你关于金钱的论点
wealth and investing and saving. I'm not
财富、投资和储蓄。我不是
even remotely an expert in AI, but as
即使对人工智能略有涉猎，但作为专家，
someone who has looked at like the
看起来像……的人
history of technology, one thing that
技术史，有一件事是
sticks out clear as day when you study
当你学习时，这一点会非常明显。
technology, when in hindsight when
技术，事后看来
you're looking at a new technology that
你正在了解一项新技术，
you know went on to change the world,
你知道，他后来改变了世界。
the computer, the car, the airplane,
电脑、汽车、飞机
those things, when you know like this
当你像这样了解那些事情的时候
was a turning point in civilization. If
这是文明史上的一个转折点。如果
you go back and look at what the
你回去看看……
optimists were saying at the time, they
当时的乐观主义者们说，他们
massively underestimated it. And that's
严重低估了它。就是这样。
what the optimists were saying. Forget
乐观主义者们说的话。忘记
the pessimists on it. So go back to the
悲观主义者们对此持怀疑态度。所以，回到……
1920s and say what were the optimists
1920年代，乐观主义者们又是什么呢？
saying about the airplane? They were
你在说什么关于飞机的事？他们是
underestimating it by 100fold. What did
低估了100倍。什么
the optimist say about the car? They
乐观主义者对这辆车是怎么说的？他们
underestimated by 100fold. Computers the
低估了100倍。计算机
same. And the Wright brothers themselves
相同的。还有莱特兄弟本人
the first airplane the United States.
美国第一架飞机。
The Wright brothers themselves only
只有莱特兄弟自己
marketed their plane, primarily marketed
他们主要通过市场营销方式销售他们的飞机。
their plane to the US Army because they
他们的飞机被送往美国陆军，因为他们
did not really foresee much use for an
并没有真正预见到它会有多大的用途
airplane outside of the military. They
非军用飞机。他们
knew you could strap a machine gun on it
我知道你可以在上面绑一挺机枪。
and the then the army might like that.
那么军队或许会喜欢这样。
But the did the Wright brothers foresee
但莱特兄弟是否预见到了这一点呢？
Delta Airlines like an Emirates an A380
达美航空就像阿联酋航空的A380一样。
like not in a million years. And so I
绝对不可能。所以，我
think it's true that in a lot of things
我认为在很多方面确实如此。
life I think I think it was Peter Teal
我想，我想那是彼得·蒂尔
who said this. He was like, "When things
是谁说的？他当时说：“当事情发生的时候……”
are going wrong, you underestimate how
如果事情进展不顺利，你低估了……
how bad they're going to get, but when
情况会变得多么糟糕，我们不得而知，但当……
things are going right, you
事情进展顺利，你
underestimate how big it's going to be."
低估了它的规模。
I I may have butchered that quote, but
我可能曲解了那句话，但是
it's something like that. And it's clear
大概就是这样。这一点很明显
that AI is right. And so, it's almost
人工智能是对的。所以，几乎
certainly the case that even the
当然，即使是这种情况
optimists, even the Sam Alman optimists
乐观主义者，甚至包括萨姆·阿尔曼的乐观主义者
are underestimating where it will go.
他们低估了它的发展方向。
And a lot of the reason for that is
造成这种情况的主要原因有很多是：
because new technologies is not what the
因为新技术并非……
inventor, whoever that might be, built.
发明者，无论他是谁，建造了它。
It's what other people go on to
这是其他人接下来要做的事。
manipulate it as. And that's why the
对其进行操控。这就是为什么
Wright brothers come up and play. And
莱特兄弟上来玩。和
now we have the A380 like it's other
现在我们有了A380，就像它的其他机型一样。
people manipulating things along the way
一路上的人们都在操纵事情
to create something just gigantic. One
创造一些极其宏大的东西。一
perfect example of that with AI is open
人工智能领域的完美例证就是开放性。
AI have created this large language
人工智能创造了这种庞大的语言
model which can do all these wonderful
能够做到所有这些美妙事情的模型
things. But then people are using that
事物。但人们正在使用那个
same technology to create AI agents.
采用相同的技术来创建人工智能代理。
Yeah. Which are equally astonishing. I
是的。这两件事同样令人震惊。我
spent the last couple of weeks using AI
过去两周我一直在使用人工智能。
agents to build some software. I'm
代理人开发一些软件。我是
someone that has no ability to code at
完全没有编程能力的人
all. Yeah. But I can sit in my bedroom
全部。是的。但我可以坐在我的卧室里。
and speak to this agent and tell it to
跟这位代理人谈谈，告诉他
build me a new to-do list or a new
帮我创建一个新的待办事项清单或一个新的
website for the podcast that tracks
追踪播客的网站
who's been on the show and follows them
谁上过这个节目并且关注他们
in the new like I can tell it to do
在新的模式下，我可以告诉它该怎么做
anything. And
任何事物。和
for what's probably costing me a dollar
这可能要花我一美元。
a day, it's building me software now.
它现在每天都在为我构建软件。
And we're just at the start of that
而我们才刚刚开始。
exponential curve. So if we now think
指数曲线。所以如果我们现在思考
that these large language models are
这些大型语言模型是
going to be able to create things,
能够创造事物，
create digital things, things on the
创建数字产品，在网络上创建产品
internet, this podcast is on the
互联网上，这个播客可以在……上找到。
internet. We know that it can create
互联网。我们知道它可以创造
podcasts. We know it can create videos,
播客。我们知道它可以制作视频，
images, software.
图片、软件。
I look at that and go, you play this
我看了之后就说，你来玩这个
forward. And if I apply your optimism um
向前。如果我运用你的乐观精神……
analogy, your optimism um lens to it
类比，你乐观的视角
where I go, we're underestimating this
我所到之处，我们都低估了这一点。
curve. It's hard. really hard to see how
曲线。这很难。很难理解为什么
this isn't tremendously disruptive in
这不会造成太大的干扰
the long term. Not even the long term,
从长远来看。即使是长期来看，
but in the short term, I'll give you one
但短期内，我会给你一个
example. You you you talked about coding
例子。你，你，你谈到了编程。
there. We're doing a little remodel on
那里。我们正在对……进行一些改造。
our house right now. And one of the
我们现在的房子。其中之一
things you can do is take a real picture
你可以做的事情之一就是拍一张真实的照片。
of of a room, upload it in. We we use
房间的照片，上传进去。我们使用
Chad GBT for this and said, "Hey, paint
Chad GBT 为此说道：“嘿，画画。”
it this color, remove this wall, put
把它涂成这种颜色，拆掉这面墙，放
this in." It is better than any designer
这比任何设计师都好。”
will be able to do it. And it's right
能够做到。没错。
there, boom, in front of you. seconds
砰！就在你眼前。秒
and you can multiply that story by
你可以将这个故事乘以
10,000 different versions of that
一万个不同的版本
stories for 10,000 different jobs. Um I
涵盖 10,000 种不同职业的故事。嗯，我
I see it as as a writer where I've I I
我觉得，作为一名作家，我……
don't use it to write. I write all my
不要用它来写作。我写下我所有的
own words. But when one thing that I've
原话。但有一件事我……
played around with, I don't really use
试过，但我其实不太用。
this as that much of a of a tool, but
这在很大程度上算是一种工具，但是
just more of an experiment of like I'll
更像是一次实验，就像我会……
upload a chapter from a book that I
上传我所写的一本书的章节
wrote and say, "Hey, give me some
写信说：“嘿，给我一些
feedback on this." And it wasn't that
关于这方面的反馈。” 而事实并非如此。
good a year ago. It's pretty good today.
一年前还不错。今天天气挺好的。
It's pretty good. So, if you're looking
还不错。所以，如果你正在寻找
for like like a writing assistant, it's
就像写作助理一样，它是
amazing. Now, the downside of that is
惊人的。然而，这样做也有缺点：
everyone knows like the high schoolers
大家都知道，就像高中生一样
and the college students who use it to
以及使用它的大学生
write the essay, just write the whole
把文章写出来，全写完。
thing. Yeah. That's that that's that's
事物。是的。就是这样，就是这样，就是这样。
that's probably not great. But if you're
那可能不太好。但如果你是
using it as a helper, it's probably the
把它当作助手来使用，它很可能是
best writing teacher that's out there.
最好的写作老师。
So, right there in my just like tiny
所以，就在我那小小的
little world, if I I I really don't know
世界很小，如果我……我真的不知道
anything about AI, but interior
任何关于人工智能的内容，但室内
designer, editor, and go on down the
设计师、编辑，然后继续往下走
list of jobs that like literally three
类似“三个”这样的工作列表
months ago I would have been like, "Oh,
几个月前我可能会说：“哦，
that's a very valuable job." And all of
这是一份非常有价值的工作。” 以及所有
a sudden you look at this tool for a
突然，你看了看这个工具……
dollar a day as you said you're like
就像你说的，一天一美元，你就像
it's pretty good. What does history tell
还不错。历史告诉我们什么？
us about how this shakes out? Like when
跟我们说说这件事最终结果如何？比如当
these industrial revolutions come along
这些工业革命随之而来
or the technological
或者说是技术方面的
revolutions where does the value acrue
革命的价值从何而来？
and how do I participate in that value?
我如何参与到这种价值创造中来？
I guess one good analogy for my here and
我想，这里一个很好的类比是……
it's probably not as powerful as what
它可能不如……强大。
we're dealing with right now but the the
我们现在正在处理的是，但是……
closest is probably you know it wasn't
最接近的可能是你知道它不是。
that long ago the late 1800s that 80% of
早在19世纪末，80%
Americans were farmers. that that that
美国人曾经是农民。那
that's that's what it was. And then the
原来就是这样。然后是
industrial revolution and the tractor
工业革命与拖拉机
and the combine came along and all of a
联合收割机来了，一切都……
sudden al it was like we we don't need
突然间，一切都好像我们不再需要了
that many farmers doing this. what
很多农民都在这样做。什么
people used to do with shovels and rakes
人们过去常常用铲子和耙子做事
can now be done with a tractor. And a
现在用拖拉机就可以完成了。以及
lot of those people found themselves out
很多人发现自己
of work. And for them it was it was very
工作。对他们来说，这非常
disruptive, but they also the farmer the
具有破坏性，但他们也是农民
farm laborer found himself pretty easy
农场工人发现自己很容易
to go into the factory because they were
因为他们要进工厂，所以
working on they they were good at
他们很擅长做这些事
working with their hands and whatnot.
从事体力劳动等等。
And so to go from that into the factory
所以，接下来就要进入工厂了。
was not an easy transition, but it was a
转型并不容易，但这确实是一个
transition they can make. Now, do you
他们可以进行的转变。现在，你呢？
have that that same transition did not
但同样的转变并没有发生。
take place from manufacturing to
从制造到
technology? The auto worker in Detroit
技术？底特律的汽车工人
could not just learn to code and work at
不能只是学习编程然后就去工作
Google like that. And so, it was it was
谷歌喜欢这样。事情就是这样。
much less seamless. And I think what
远没有那么流畅。我觉得什么
we're dealing with now will be even more
我们现在面临的情况将会更加严峻。
of a disruption. That the people who are
发生中断。那些人
being disrupted out of AI are going to
人工智能领域即将面临颠覆性变革
have like a much more difficult time
感觉会更加艰难。
historically to move in to where the
历史上，人们搬到了……
economy is going next. So the idea that
接下来是经济问题。所以这个想法是
an industry is disrupted and you need to
一个行业正经历变革，你需要……
go figure out something else to do, I
你去找点别的事做吧，我
think has gotten progressively harder
思考变得越来越难
over the last 150 years. And when we
过去150年间。当我们
moved from machines to technology, it
从机器转向技术，它
was a significant leap also for the user
对用户而言，这也是一次意义重大的飞跃。
and for the customer and for the as well
对于客户而言，也对于其他方面而言。
as for the employee. So that transition
至于员工方面。因此，这种转变
took time. But I was reading something
花费了一些时间。但我当时正在读一些东西。
the other day that said now that we're
前几天有人说过，现在我们是
native internet users, we all are.
我们都是互联网原住民用户。
Billions and billions and billions of
数十亿、数十亿、数十亿的
people use the internet. This is like a
人们使用互联网。这就像……
new application on the internet. which
互联网上的新应用。哪个
explains why it's growing so fast that
这就解释了为什么它增长如此迅速：
we haven't had to learn.
我们不需要学习。
So there hasn't been this big jump in
所以并没有出现这种大幅增长
fundamental skills like there was from
基本技能，例如来自
like going from a I don't know from
就像从“我不知道”到
piece of machine to an iPhone. So this
将机器部件连接到 iPhone。所以这
acceleration will be quicker. So
加速会更快。所以
therefore one would assume that the
因此，人们会认为
transition will be more severe. And I
过渡期将更加剧烈。我
think about even things like driving. I
甚至想想开车这样的事情。我
think Tesla are releasing in Austin this
特斯拉好像要在奥斯汀发布这款产品了
month or next month, the first
上个月或下个月，第一个月
autonomous vehicle the cyber taxi. Yeah.
自动驾驶汽车：网络出租车。是的。
The robo taxi, whatever it's called. And
无人驾驶出租车，不管它叫什么。和
it has no steering wheel. Yeah. And the
它没有方向盘。是的。以及
profession of driving from what I
我从事的职业是驾驶。
understand is the biggest profession.
理解是最重要的职业。
The biggest profession truck drivers,
卡车司机是最大的职业群体。
drivers in general. Yeah. On my way here
驾驶员总体情况。是的。我来这里的路上
today, I did not touch the steering
今天，我没有碰方向盘。
wheel. I did not touch the pedals
车轮。我没碰踏板。
because I'm in a cyber truck and there's
因为我坐在一辆赛博卡车里，而且还有
a button on it which auto uh drives you
上面有个按钮，可以自动驾驶你
to wherever you want to go. And
去任何你想去的地方。和
typically I'd probably have got an Uber.
通常情况下，我可能会叫辆优步。
Yeah. But now I can sit there, do my
是的。但现在我可以坐在那里，做我的
work, and it drives for me. It's And
它为我工作，也为我开车。它是和
that's also AI. Yeah. No, it's it's it's
这也是人工智能。是的。不，是，是，是
crazy. And back to the analogy like when
疯狂的。回到之前的比喻，就像……
when the farmer had to go work in the
当农夫不得不去外地干活时
factory, it was it was a transition. He
工厂，那是一个转型期。他
may have had to move, but he but he did
他可能不得不搬家，但他确实搬家了。
it. And that's why he went from 80% of
它。这就是为什么他从80%……
the population were farmers to 2% which
人口中农民占2%，
is what it is today. And but they they
就是它现在的样子。但是他们
were able to to move in. The
他们可以搬进去了。
manufacturer to technology struggled.
制造商向技术转型遇到了困难。
And I think it's going to be now like
我觉得现在的情况会是这样。
the the truck driver to tell the truck
让卡车司机告诉卡车
driver, well, just go get a job at Open
司机，那你就去Open公司找份工作吧。
AAI kind of thing. Like it's funny to
类似人工智能之类的东西。好像这很有趣
even think about because it's it's
甚至想一想，因为它是它的
preposterous. But the thing with Open AI
荒谬。但OpenAI的问题在于……
from what I understand is they have less
据我了解，他们的数量较少。
than 100 employees, right? And the
超过100名员工，对吧？以及
reason they have less than 100 employees
他们员工人数少于100人的原因
is because they're using AI to build to
这是因为他们正在使用人工智能来构建……
do the work to do and they'll
完成该做的工作，他们就会
increasingly do that, especially when
这种情况越来越普遍，尤其是在
they hit AGI, right? They're probably
他们击中了通用人工智能（AGI），对吧？他们很可能
going to four employees. Yeah. And this
员工人数将达到四人。是的。而这
is why I think they have 100 employees.
这就是我认为他们有100名员工的原因。
I think they've purposefully kept it low
我认为他们故意压低了价格。
because they think AGI is around the
因为他们认为通用人工智能（AGI）即将到来
corner which is this very very advanced
这个角落非常非常先进
form of AI which is going to be able to
一种能够……的人工智能形式
like I think they call it selfreinforce
我想他们称之为自我强化
where it teaches itself synthetic data
它自学合成数据
right so h kind of going from there now
对，所以现在就从那里开始吧。
I think if there's an optimistic side
我认为如果存在乐观的一面的话。
it's always been it it was the case that
一直都是这样，情况一直如此。
when farming was being disrupted there
当农业生产受到干扰时
were a lot of people who just said these
很多人都这么说过这些话。
people are never going to find jobs like
人们永远找不到这样的工作
if you if you put the farmer out of
如果你把农民赶出去
business there was it sounds comical
那里的生意听起来很滑稽。
today but there was a big push when the
今天，但当时有一个很大的推动力
car came about to be like no like what
车子出现的方式和以前完全不一样，就像什么？
are all the the horses going to do like
所有的马都会这样做吗？
like like have some like have some
就像拥有一些，就像拥有一些
dignity for the horse and the people who
尊重马匹和人的尊严
are raising horses and whatnot. So it's
他们养马什么的。所以是
always been the case that you cannot
一直以来都是这样，你不能
foresee what's going to happen next. And
预见接下来会发生什么。和
the optimistic side of capitalism is as
资本主义乐观的一面是
messy and as hard and as much personal
混乱、艰难，而且非常个人化。
damage as you can cause to families
你可能会对家庭造成伤害
along the way. Those people will
一路走来。那些人将
eventually figure out something to do.
最终总会找到办法做点什么。
And when people say that, it sounds so
当人们这么说的时候，听起来很……
callous and coarse. And that's why you
冷酷粗糙。这就是为什么你
have so much debate and angst and anger
充满了争论、焦虑和愤怒
and things like with and disagreements
以及诸如分歧之类的事情
like what with what we're dealing with
比如我们正在处理的事情
with tariffs right now. You have your
目前还有关税。你有你的
son in the green room watching us right
儿子在休息室里看着我们呢
now. Yeah. How old is he? Nine. Nine.
现在。是的。他几岁了？九。九。
Okay. So, he's got some decisions ahead.
好的。所以，他接下来需要做一些决定。
He's he he's wincing right now, I'm
他现在正痛苦地皱着眉头，我
sure, now that we're talking about him.
既然说到他了，那当然了。
But what if in terms of him building his
但如果就他建立自己的体系而言呢？
career, acquiring skills, generating
职业生涯、技能获取、创造
wealth, based on everything you know
财富，基于你所知道的一切
about how people have made money through
关于人们如何通过以下方式赚钱
history, what are the prevailing skills
历史沿革，有哪些主流技能
that your son would have to have to
你的儿子就必须……
assure that he makes money regardless of
确保他无论如何都能赚钱
what the industry is? Learn how to
这个行业是什么？学习如何
communicate. Learn how to get along with
交流。学习如何与人相处
people you disagree with. I think that's
与你意见相左的人。我认为那是
that's a very underlooked skill in life
这是生活中一项经常被忽视的技能。
is particularly in a in a social media
尤其是在社交媒体上
driven world where people have very
世界是一个充满活力的世界，人们拥有非常
different views on fundamental topics.
对基本问题的不同观点。
Learn how to get along with people who
学习如何与那些
you disagree with. Learn how to
你不同意。学习如何
communicate. Those would be the top two.
交流。这应该是前两名。
Those are extremely high level. Like I'm
这些都是极高的水平。就像我
I'm not saying go learn calculus 4 kind
我不是说要你去学微积分4。
of thing or go learn engineering, but
要么做这件事，要么去学工程，但是
those are timeless skills and I think
这些都是永不过时的技能，我认为
those two skills can get you pretty far
掌握这两项技能能让你走得很远。
in life. And I I look back at at myself.
在生活中。我回头审视自己。
I don't know if you had a similar
我不知道你是否也有过类似的经历。
example of this, but I I was not a good
举个例子，但我当时做得并不好。
student. My ability to do math is not
学生。我的数学能力并不强。
any good. My ability my grades in
好用吗？我的能力和成绩
science were not any good whatsoever. I
科学一点也不好。我
think if I if there are two skills that
想想如果我有两种技能的话
I was that I I I didn't even know it at
我当时就是那样，我甚至都不知道。
the time. It was not really like
时间。其实并非如此
conscious that I was doing this, but
我意识到自己在这样做，但是
learn how to communicate and don't be a
学会沟通，不要做个……
jerk. Like just learn because that for
混蛋。就像学习一样，因为那样
me as a writer that was like learn how
作为一名作家，我当时就想，这就像是在学习如何写作。
to communicate as writing and in the
以书面和口头方式进行交流
writing business learn how to get along
写作业务学习如何相处
with people so you can move ahead move
与人合作，这样你就可以前进。
your career like be nice to this person
你的职业生涯就像对这个人友善一样
so you can move on up. I think you see
这样你就可以晋升了。我想你明白了
that a lot. What about in terms of money
很多。那么，从金钱的角度来看呢？
making money when you think about great
当你思考如何赚钱时，你会想到很棒
people through history that have accured
历史上积累了……的人
a lot of wealth? What principles would
很多财富？哪些原则会
you instill in him so that he had a
你向他灌输的思想，使他拥有了
money mindset? It's hard for a parent.
金钱观？这对父母来说很艰难。
Uh, I I'm not I'm not filthy rich by any
呃，我，我可不是什么富翁。
means, but I've sold a couple books. And
也就是说，我已经卖出了几本书。和
it's hard as a parent to be like, I want
作为父母，很难说出这样的话：“我想要……”
to use money to give you a good life,
用金钱让自己过上美好的生活，
but I don't want to spoil you. The last
但我不想宠坏你。最后
thing I want is for you to be a spoiled
我希望你被宠坏。
little brat. And it's very difficult for
小鬼。而且这非常困难
a lot of parents to do that. And so, one
很多家长都会这样做。所以，一个
of the things I want him to learn about
我想让他学习的东西
money, and I want him to learn it in a
钱，我希望他能学会如何赚钱。
very stark way, is like learn the
非常直接的方式，就像学习……
scarcity and the value of $1. And I
稀缺性和1美元的价值。我
think the only way to do that is to
认为唯一的方法就是
experience it firsthand. So when he was
亲身体验。所以当他
born nine years ago, I wrote him a
他九年前出生，我给他写了一封信
little letter and I published this on a
我写了一封小信，并把它发表在了……
blog and one of the things I said was,
我在博客里说过，其中一件事是：
"I hope you're poor one day." And I
“我希望你有一天会穷困潦倒。”我
said, "Not not struggling, not broke,
他说：“并非没有挣扎，也没有破产。”
but I hope the only way to understand
但我希望这是理解的唯一途径。
the value of a dollar is to experience
美元的价值在于体验
the power of its scarcity. And I hope
稀缺性的力量。我希望
there's a there's a period when my wife
有一段时间，我的妻子
and I are able to say like look like
我能够说像看起来像
you're never going to fall flat on your
你永远不会失败
face. You're not going to be homeless.
脸。你不会流落街头的。
You're always going to have good
你总会有好运。
healthcare. But I hope you're able to
卫生保健。但我希望你能……
experience the scarcity of a dollar so
体验一下美元的稀缺性吧
you value it. I did. My my parents
你很珍惜它。我做了。我的父母
taught me that in a way that they didn't
他们以某种方式教会了我这一点，而他们并没有。
need to, but they let me be poor for a
需要，但他们让我贫穷了一段时间
while. And most people will experience
尽管。大多数人都会经历
it because they they they have that's
因为他们，他们，他们有那个
that's a situation they were in. So that
这就是他们当时所处的境地。所以……
that's one thing I think about of and I
那是我一直在考虑的一件事，而且
think actually quite a few families deal
我觉得很多家庭都会遇到这种情况。
with that is like how can you help your
那就像你如何帮助你的
kids and it goes beyond money. This is
孩子，而且这不仅仅关乎金钱。这是
uh you know so many the the the
呃，你知道很多……
helicopter parent era is I want to
直升机父母时代，我想……
protect you from downside at all cost
不惜一切代价保护你免受损失
emotional downside. Uh and and I think
情绪上的负面影响。嗯，而且我觉得
money is one of many topics in which
金钱是众多话题之一，
you're going to learn the best by
你将通过以下方式学到最好的东西
experiencing the downside.
体验到负面影响。
For anybody that likes matcha, for
对于任何喜欢抹茶的人来说，
anybody that likes lattes, one of my
任何喜欢拿铁的人，我的其中之一
companies has just launched canned
公司刚刚推出了罐装产品
matcha lattes. And I was speaking with
抹茶拿铁。我当时正在和……
the founder, Marissa, and she said that
创始人玛丽莎说：
creating this product has been no easy
打造这款产品绝非易事。
feat. They tried launching in 2021, but
特色他们尝试在2021年推出，但是
as is often the case in business, the
正如商业中经常出现的情况一样，
development process turned out to be
开发过程最终证明是
extremely complex. So, they've spent the
极其复杂。所以，他们花了……
last four years testing and refining
过去四年的测试和改进
every single detail to create this,
每一个细节都倾注其中，
which is a perfect TED matcha vanilla
这是完美的 TED 抹茶香草
latte and a perfect Ted matcha
拿铁和完美的泰德抹茶
strawberry latte. So, what we have here
草莓拿铁。所以，我们这里的情况是这样的
in these cans is barista quality matcha
这些罐子里装的是咖啡师品质的抹茶。
straight from the can. And it tastes
直接从罐头里倒出来的。它的味道也很好。
like it's just been made from your
就像是用你的……做成的一样
favorite cafe. Naturally sweet and
最喜欢的咖啡馆。天然甜味
naturally creamy in a can. And the
罐装天然奶油。以及
reason why I've invested in this company
我投资这家公司的原因
and I drink matcha is because matcha as
我喝抹茶是因为抹茶……
an energy source gives me lasting energy
能量来源能给我提供持久的能量。
without the big crashes that I get from
没有我遇到的那些大崩溃
other products. Grab their readyto-
其他产品。抓住他们准备好的
drink canned matcha lattes at Waitros,
在 Waitros 喝罐装抹茶拿铁，
Tesco's, and Holland and Barrett and
乐购、荷兰和巴雷特以及
perfected.com where you can use code
perfected.com，你可以在那里使用代码
Steven40 for 40% off your first
使用优惠码 Steven40 可享首次消费 40% 折扣
order. Men are struggling in a variety
命令。男性在很多方面都面临困境。
of different ways and obviously your son
不同的方式，当然还有你的儿子
is going to be a man someday. If I think
他将来会成为一个男人。如果我认为
about some of the stats here, men's
关于这里的一些统计数据，男性的
labor force participation has declined
劳动力参与率下降
dramatically over time. For prime
随着时间的推移，变化非常显著。对于主打
working age men between 25 and 54,
25岁至54岁之间的劳动年龄男性
participation fell from 98% in the 1950s
参与率从20世纪50年代的98%下降到现在的水平。
to about 80 something% in
大约达到 80% 左右
2024. 10.5% of men aged 25 to 54 were
2024年，25至54岁男性中有10.5%的人
neither working nor looking for
既不工作也不找工作
employment compared to with just 2.5% in
相比之下，就业率仅为2.5%。
1954.
1954年。
And we had a study that came out in the
我们有一项研究结果发表在……
UK recently, I think it was the center
英国最近，我认为它是中心
of social justice that showed that for
社会正义表明，对于
the first time in a long time in recent
近来第一次
history, more young men are out of work
历史数据显示，越来越多的年轻人失业。
than young women. And I think it was
比年轻女性更甚。我觉得是
like one in seven men are out of work.
大约七分之一的男性失业。
Yeah. So it's a different world for a
是的。所以，对于一个……来说，这是一个不同的世界。
man, but but we still have the sort of
伙计，但是，我们仍然有那种
prehistoric caveman mindset of being a
史前穴居人的思维模式
protector and a provider. Yes.
保护者和供给者。是的。
Absolutely. The world has changed. Yeah.
绝对地。世界已经改变。是的。
I think it was Scott Galloway recently
我觉得最近是斯科特·加洛韦。
said that like a really aspirational
他说这话听起来很有抱负。
definition of manhood is is wanting to
男子气概的定义是渴望……
procreate, provide, and protect. You
繁衍后代，供养子女，保护家人。你
want to have kids and you desperately
想要孩子，而且你非常渴望
want to provide for your family and
想为家人提供保障，
protect your family. And I I do think
保护你的家人。而且我确实认为
that there Yeah, there's men all over
那里，是的，到处都是男人。
the world to a higher degree than
世界比这更高程度
there's ever been that feel like those
曾经有过那种感觉吗？
three things are out of reach for them.
有三件事是他们无法企及的。
And because of this, a lot of people get
正因如此，很多人都得到了
involved in get-richqu schemes. Yes.
参与快速致富计划。是的。
Crypto coins, meme coins, all this
加密货币、梗币，所有这些
stuff. Daniel Conaman, the great
东西。伟大的丹尼尔·科纳曼
psychologist, passed away last year. He
心理学家，去年去世了。他
had a saying. He was like, "When all of
有一句谚语。他当时说：“当所有……”
your options are bad, you become very
你的选择很糟糕，你会变得非常
risk-taking because you have nothing to
因为你一无所有，所以才去冒险。
lose kind of thing." So, whenever you
类似失去的那种事。”所以，每当你
see people participating in get-rich
看到人们参与快速致富活动
get-rich quick schemes, you know, it's
你知道，那种快速致富的计划，就是
because they feel like all their
因为他们觉得他们所有的
options, all their options are bad. If
他们的所有选择都很糟糕。如果
you knew, if you believed that if you
你知道，如果你相信这一点，如果你
could go to college and learn a or not
可以上大学学习，也可以不上大学。
go to college, but if you can go learn a
去上大学，但如果你能去学习……
skill and go work hard and earn a stable
掌握技能，努力工作，就能获得稳定的收入。
paycheck to provide for your family, 99
挣钱养家，99
out of a 100red men are going to say
100个男人中，有100个会说
that's that's the one I want. But if you
就是这个，我想要的就是这个。但是如果你
believe, whether it's true or not, if
相信，无论真假，如果
you believe that that option is not
你认为这个选项不是
available to you, you're like, let's
如果你有空，你会想，那就这样吧。
throw it all on this this new coin kind
把所有东西都投入到这种新型硬币中吧
of thing. And so I think you that's you
事物。所以我觉得那就是你
see that quite a bit. There's a lot of
这种情况经常发生。有很多
things in life where you see people
生活中你看到人们的那些事
making bad decisions or what you think
做出糟糕的决定或者你的想法
are bad decisions and it's easy to mock
这些都是糟糕的决定，而且很容易被嘲笑。
them or look down upon or to say they're
看不起他们，或者说他们是
idiots, but like deep down there's
一群白痴，但内心深处却藏着……
always a reason that is kind of is
总会有一个理由，那就是
there's there there's a deeper reason
这背后肯定有更深层次的原因
why they're doing it. And for a lot of
他们为什么要这样做？而且对于很多人来说
these things with financial risk
这些都存在财务风险
takingaking, it's it's like a lack of
服用，就像缺乏
not necessarily a lack of self-esteem,
不一定是缺乏自尊，
but a lack of self-confidence in their
但他们缺乏自信。
ability to earn a good dignified stable
有能力获得一份体面稳定的好工作
wage to provide for their family.
他们挣钱是为了养家糊口。
Testosterone plays a role though.
睾酮也起到了一定的作用。
Because if when we think about who
因为如果我们思考谁
becomes gambling addicts and who takes
沉迷赌博的人
the biggest risks with finances through
财务方面最大的风险在于
history, it's often men. Women do seem
历史上，往往是男性。女性似乎确实如此
to be generally better with managing
更擅长管理
money than men. Yeah. W with men. What a
金钱比男人更重要。是的。与男人在一起。真是
lot of it is is the inability to say
很多时候是因为无法表达。
that's enough, particularly with the
这就足够了，尤其是考虑到
risk that they're taking. So you see
他们正在承担的风险。所以你看
this with with a lot of hedge fun. Hedge
这其中蕴含着许多有趣的对冲机会。对冲
funds are just giant investing pools of
基金只不过是巨大的投资池。
money of like rich people on Wall Street
华尔街富人的钱
managing money. They have quite a long
理财。他们有很长一段时间。
history, not a lots of them, but quite a
历史，虽然不多，但相当丰富。
long history of them blowing up. And
它们爆炸的历史由来已久。和
it's because this very smart genius
这是因为这位非常聪明的天才
billionaire Wall Street trader who has a
一位拥有亿万身家的华尔街交易员
PhD from MIT could not say that was
拥有麻省理工学院博士学位的人也不能说那是
enough. They kept taking more risk, more
足够的。他们不断承担更大的风险，更多
risk, more risk until it blew up. And we
风险，不断增加风险，直到最终失败。我们
we we definitely see with women managing
我们确实看到女性在管理方面发挥着重要作用。
money that they tend to not earn as high
他们往往赚不到那么高的钱
returns on any given year, but they
任何一年的回报，但它们
don't blow themselves up, so to speak,
不要自爆，或者说，不要自爆。
financially. So they're like men are
经济方面。所以他们就像男人一样
much more willing to swing for the
更愿意挥杆。
fences and women are much more willing
围栏和女性更愿意
to say I' I'd like to just take a calm
我想说的是，我只想平静下来。
casual swing but I want to keep it going
只是随便玩玩，但我想继续下去。
for a long period of time. Now who's
很长一段时间。现在是谁？
going to do better over the course of a
在接下来的一段时间里会做得更好
lifetime in that situation? Your book
在这种情况下，你的寿命会怎样？你的书
profiles a few scenarios of who does
列举几种可能的情况，看看谁会这样做。
better over a lifetime. And although I
终身受益。虽然我
read your book I think it must have been
我读过你的书，我想它一定是……
four years ago. I will always remember
四年前。我将永远铭记
reading a story about I think it was
读过一个关于……的故事，我想是……
like a stock broker that you write about
就像你写到的那位股票经纪人一样。
in your book. It was Jesse Livermore.
在你的书中。是杰西·利弗莫尔。
Tell me that story. Jesse Livermore was
把这个故事讲给我听。杰西·利弗莫尔是
a a trader a Wall Street stock trader.
一名交易员，一名华尔街股票交易员。
uh about a hundred years ago, did most
大约一百年前，大部分
of his work in the early 1900s through
他在 20 世纪初的工作
about the 1920s and he was the best in
大约在 20 世纪 20 年代，他是最优秀的
the world at getting rich and he had no
世界都在谈论致富，而他却一无所有。
ability whatsoever to stay rich. I think
完全没有保持富有的能力。我认为
he became the equivalent of a
他变得相当于一个
billionaire adjusted for inflation four
亿万富翁（已根据通货膨胀调整）
separate times and went bankrupt four
两次破产，分别破产四次
separate times. He eventually at his end
分开时间。他最终走到了尽头
committed suicide when he went broke for
他破产后自杀了。
I think the fifth time and and in
我想是第五次，而且在
between there he would become and
在那之后，他会变成……
literally the richest man in the world
他是名副其实的世界首富。
at one point but he had no ability to
一度他有这种能力，但他没有这种能力
say that's enough. So when he was the
就说够了。所以当他是
richest man in the world he just kept
他是世界上最富有的人，他一直保持着
taking more risk more risks more risk
承担更多风险，风险更大
and then it blew up and he did it over
然后事情就闹大了，他又重来了一遍。
and over and over and over again until
一遍又一遍，直到
he eventually killed himself.
他最终自杀了。
Damn. It's it's amaz it's a it's an
该死。它太棒了，它真是一个
amazing story because punctuated through
精彩的故事，因为贯穿始终
his story of failure and bankruptcy and
他讲述的失败和破产的故事
eventual suicide is a level of success
最终自杀也是一种成功
that like Steve Jobs could not even
就像史蒂夫·乔布斯那样，甚至都做不到。
fathom. He has no one in history I think
捉摸。我认为他在历史上没有对手。
was better at getting rich than he was
他比其他人更擅长致富
and he he could not keep it. And for
他没能保住它。而对于
most people like a much better situation
大多数人都喜欢更好的处境。
of course is like you don't need to
当然，这就好比你不需要……
become the richest person in the world.
成为世界首富。
You can just make a modest amount of
你只需要制作少量的
money that's gonna support you and your
这笔钱将用于支持你和你的
family, but keep it. Don't keep taking
家人，但要保留它。不要继续服用
more risk that's eventually gonna blow
风险更大，最终肯定会失败。
it up. Just keep it and it's okay. What
把它搞定。留着它就好，没关系。什么
do you think of crypto? I don't own any.
你考虑过加密货币吗？我没有。
So maybe that that's the summary of how
所以，这或许就是对如何……的总结。
I feel about it. But I also think the
我对此有感触。但我认为
only take that I've had on it is like if
我唯一对它的看法是，如果
you don't think that some of it is
你不认为其中一些是
inspiring and then then you're not
你一开始很鼓舞人心，但后来就不是了。
paying attention. But if you don't think
认真听讲。但如果你不这么认为
that 99% of it is a is a joke, then
如果其中99%都是个笑话，那
you're not paying attention. And I I say
你没在认真听。我说
that because most people are one or one
那是因为大多数人都是一个人或一个
or the other. They think the whole thing
或者另一种。他们认为整件事
is is a scam and they don't understand
这是个骗局，他们根本不明白。
any of it. It's a bubble. It's going to
任何一种。这是一个泡沫。它将
burst or it's literally the greatest
爆发，或者说，它简直是最棒的
invention of of human history. And I I
人类历史上的一项发明。而我
think whenever there's a new technology,
每当出现新技术时，都要思考一下。
you're likely to get like those extreme
你很可能会变得像那些极端分子一样。
one of those camps. But also in the
其中一个营地。但也在
history of technology, what you would
技术史，你会怎么做？
see is that 99% of the new players, the
你会发现，99%的新玩家，
new companies, the new products won't
新公司，新产品不会
exist in 10 years. And a couple of them
10年后仍然存在。还有其中几个
will turn into Ford or Microsoft or
会变成福特或微软，或者
whatever it might be. That's always been
不管是什么。一直都是这样。
the case. So you can't envision a world
案件。所以你无法想象一个世界
in 20 years in which crypto is not
20年来，加密货币并非如此
having a big part of the global economy.
在全球经济中占据重要地位。
And I also think you cannot envision a
而且我认为你无法想象一个
world in which in 20 years 99% of what
在这个世界里，20年后99%的什么
exists today doesn't exist anymore.
如今存在的事物已不复存在。
Yeah, I have owned Ethereum for a long
是的，我持有以太坊已经很久了。
time and more recently I just changed it
随着时间的推移，最近我刚刚更改了它
all into Bitcoin because I think Bitcoin
我完全投入比特币，因为我认为比特币
is the safest bet. So it seems to be
这是最稳妥的选择。所以看来是这样
where institutional money has gone to
机构资金流向何处
and I I'm doing the same thing as you.
我和你做的是一样的事。
I've never like traded coins in my life
我这辈子从来没喜欢过交易硬币。
or anything but I think most of it is
或者别的什么，但我认为大部分是
probably going to zero as we've seen.
正如我们所看到的，很可能会归零。
But I think Bitcoin feels like the place
但我认为比特币给人的感觉正是如此。
that the market has decided will be the
市场已经决定，这将是
stablest. But yeah, it's not it's not
最稳定。但是，不是，不是
contradictory in history to say that
在历史上，这种说法是自相矛盾的。
this new technology will change the
这项新技术将改变
world forever. And and at the same time,
世界永恒。而且与此同时，
you're probably not going to make that
你可能不会成功。
much money on it. The best example of
投入了不少钱。最好的例子
that were the railroads, which was
那就是铁路，也就是
probably the most transformational new
可能是最具变革性的新事物
industry in US history. Like to have a
美国历史上的工业。想拥有一个
railroad going from the east coast to
从东海岸到
the west coast, that changed everything
西海岸改变了一切
in such a profound way. And the vast
以如此深刻的方式。以及广阔的
majority of railroad investors lost all
大多数铁路投资者血本无归。
their money. So they you could get it
他们的钱。所以他们就能得到它
right. This is going to change the world
正确的。这将改变世界
forever. It does not mean that you're
永远。这并不意味着你
going to make that much money on it. And
打算靠它赚那么多钱。和
that that that's not to say that most
但这并不意味着大多数
crypto investors No, I actually I I
加密货币投资者 不，实际上我我
would say it's almost certain that most
几乎可以肯定的是，大多数
crypto investors will not make that much
加密货币投资者赚不了多少钱。
money. That's that that's pretty
钱。就是这样，挺不错的。
standard historical. The other thing is
标准历史。另一件事是
in cars in the early 1900s, there were
20世纪初的汽车里有……
2,000 car companies in America and 1,997
美国有2000家汽车公司，1997家
of them went bankrupt. you ended up with
他们中有些人破产了。你最终得到了
GM, Ford, and Chrysler. The rest
通用汽车、福特和克莱斯勒。其余的部分
virtually disappeared. So, it's always
几乎消失殆尽。所以，总是
the case that in a new technology that
这种情况发生在一种新技术中
changes in the world. There's a big gap
世界发生了变化。存在很大的差距
between this is going to change the
这将改变……
world and everyone's going to get rich
全世界都会变得富有。
on this. One of the things that made me
关于这一点。让我成为这样的人的原因之一
question my hypothesis on crypto was
质疑我对加密货币的假设是
Google released this new computer. I
谷歌发布了这款新电脑。我
don't know if you saw it called Willow,
不知道你有没有看到它叫《柳树》
the quantum computer. Yeah. That can
量子计算机。是的。那可以
crack or in theory in the future. I I've
裂缝，或者理论上在未来。我 我已经
talked to people about this that like
和一些人谈论过这件事，他们也喜欢
you can't believe in crypto and quantum
你不能既相信加密货币又相信量子计算。
at the same time. People who are much
同时。那些非常
smarter than me say that's that's not
比我聪明的人会说，那不是那样。
the case. That you can augment the
案件。你可以增强
system. I I I don't really understand
系统。我不太明白
it, but people who are much smarter than
它，但比它聪明得多的人
me say they're not worried about it.
我说他们并不担心。
Google built a powerful new computer
谷歌制造了一台功能强大的新计算机
called Willow that uses quantum
名为 Willow 的量子技术
technology. Some people worry it could
技术。有些人担心这可能会
one day hack Bitcoin by breaking its
有一天，通过破解比特币来攻击它
security system. But right now, Willow
安全系统。但现在，柳树
isn't strong enough to do that just yet.
目前还不够强大，无法做到这一点。
And they pose that quantum computers may
他们提出量子计算机可能
well become strong enough that they'll
他们会变得足够强大，以至于他们会
be able to hack Bitcoin's system that
能够入侵比特币系统
keeps it safe, right? because there is a
这样能保证安全，对吧？因为存在
certain amount of compute that could
一定量的计算能力
affect that doesn't exist right now but
目前并不存在的影响，但
could in the future with quantum
未来或许可以通过量子技术实现。
computers right so like all assets I
电脑对吧，就像所有资产一样，我
mean if you look back through history
意思是，如果你回顾历史的话。
we've used different things as stores of
我们曾用不同的东西作为储存物品
value and many of those things whether
价值以及许多其他方面，无论
it's the tulips or whatever else aren't
是郁金香还是其他什么东西？
our current store of value so it's
我们目前的价值储存手段，所以它是
conceivable to think that bitcoin as a
可以想象，比特币作为一种
store of value does have a shelf life
价值储存手段确实有保质期。
yes but that's I mean that of course
是的，当然，我的意思是……
that could be the case I mean gold which
有可能，我指的是黄金。
has been you know a store of value for
一直以来，你知道，它都是一种价值储存手段。
thousands of years has gone through
数千年过去了
periods where it surged merged and then
它激增的时期合并了，然后
fell 90% and sat there for 20 years. You
下跌了 90%，并且持续了 20 年。你
kind of thing. So even when you have
就是那种事。所以即使你拥有
something that is a historic like you
像你这样的历史人物
know uh you know very objective store of
你知道，你知道，非常客观的商店
value that doesn't mean that you know
价值并不意味着你知道
what the price is going to do next month
下个月价格走势如何？
or next year or even the next 10 years.
或者明年，甚至未来十年。
That's a totally different thing. When
那完全是两码事。什么时候
you look at all these people through
你透过这些目光审视所有人。
history that have made money, lost
历史中那些曾经赚钱、也曾经亏损的故事
money, etc. generated great wealth. Are
金钱等创造了巨大的财富。是
there like certain strategies they've
他们有一些特定的策略。
deployed? Because when I think of like
已部署？因为当我想到“像”的时候
Warren Buffett, I'm like, "Okay, so he
沃伦·巴菲特，我就想，“好吧，所以他
like compounded for like 80 years, blah
就像复利增长了80年那样，呃
blah blah, invested, he was an
巴拉巴拉，投资了，他是一个
investor." Then you've got this other
然后你还有另一位投资者。”
strategy which might be
可能的策略是
entrepreneurship. Yeah. Some incredible
创业精神。是的。一些令人难以置信的
company uh like Elon Musk making SpaceX
像埃隆·马斯克创立的SpaceX这样的公司
or Tesla. Do you have it distilled down
或者特斯拉。你已经把它提炼出来了吗？
into a set of different strategies that
分解成一系列不同的策略
are often deployed to equal wealth? I
通常被用来衡量财富平等吗？我
think if there's one big one that is is
想想看，如果有一个很大的问题是……
applicable to ordinary people, you know,
适用于普通人，你知道的。
you you can come up with like different
你可以想出一些不同的东西
marketing things, but like that's not
营销方面的事情，但那不是……
going to apply to me. hear you. One
适用于我。听到了。一
thing that sticks out that is a common
突出的常见事物
denominator that virtually everyone
几乎所有人的共同点
listening to this could learn from is
听了这段话或许能学到一些东西。
they were way more patient and had way
他们更有耐心，而且……
more endurance and kept it going for
耐力更强，坚持了下来
longer than anyone else. David Senra,
比任何人都坚持得更久。大卫·森拉
who's a great podcaster, right? So, he
谁是位很棒的播客主持人？所以，他
has a podcast called Founders. He he
有一个名为 Founders 的播客。他他
said this one time. He was like he hears
只说过一次。他就像他听到的那样
from entrepreneurs who are like, "Man, I
来自那些创业者，他们会说：“伙计，我
listen to your podcast. I'm a I'm a
听你的播客。我是一个我是一个
founder. I have a company and I'm I'm
创始人。我拥有一家公司，我是……
going to sell my company next year. I'm
明年打算卖掉我的公司。我是
I'm do I'm going to sell it to Google."
我打算把它卖给谷歌。
And David's like, "Did you learn
大卫说：“你学到了吗？”
anything from the historical
从历史到其他任何方面
entrepreneurs of Rockefeller or Steve
洛克菲勒或史蒂夫的创业家
Jobs or Bill Gas? Those people ran their
工作还是账单煤气费？那些人跑了
companies for 50 years. They ran their
公司成立50年。他们跑了
companies until the until they died kind
公司一直经营到他们去世为止
of thing. These are not people who are
事物。这些人并非……
looking to be like, I'm going to create
看起来就像，我要创造
a company and then sell it and I'm going
先成立一家公司，然后把它卖掉，我就要走了
to start another company and sell it."
再创办一家公司，然后把它卖掉。
They keep it going for as long as they
他们会一直坚持下去，直到他们……
possibly can. The big wealth usually
有可能。巨额财富通常
does not come, it almost never comes
它不会来，几乎从不来。
from like a great idea that just surges
就像一个突然涌现的绝妙想法
out of the middle of nowhere. It's
从荒郊野外冒出来。它是
usually like a pretty good idea that you
通常来说，你会觉得这是一个相当不错的想法。
can keep going for 40 years or 50 years.
可以持续40年或50年。
That's that's where the big money comes
这就是巨额财富的来源。
from. If Rockefeller I I wrote this in
从。如果洛克菲勒一世我写下了这段话
the book, 99.9% of Warren Buffett's net
这本书占沃伦·巴菲特净资产的99.9%。
worth was accumulated after his 60th
他的财富是在60岁之后积累的。
birthday. So like if when Warren Buffett
生日。就像沃伦·巴菲特
was 60, he was worth $2 billion. Like
他60岁时身价20亿美元。喜欢
incredible amount of money. He could
数额巨大的钱。他可以
have sold then and sold everything and
当时就把所有东西都卖掉了
retired and had an absolutely amazing
退休后，我过得非常精彩。
life. The reason that he has
生活。他之所以有这个理由
accumulated, if you count the money he's
如果把他积累的钱都算上的话……
given away, 250 billion is because he
捐出的2500亿是因为他
kept it going. So now he's 93 years old
继续下去。他现在93岁了。
and he's still going. Same with, you
他还在继续。你也是一样。
know, Bill Gates could have sold
你知道吗，比尔·盖茨本来可以卖掉的。
Microsoft in the 1970s and made $10
微软在 20 世纪 70 年代赚了 10 美元
million and had a great little life.
拥有百万身家，过着精彩的小日子。
Yeah. But he kept it going and kept it
是的。但他坚持了下来，一直坚持了下来。
going. Yahoo offered Mark Zuckerberg a
去。雅虎向马克·扎克伯格提供了一份
billion dollars cash and he was like 19
他当时只有19岁，却拥有10亿美元的现金。
at the time and he said, "No, I'm going
当时他说：“不，我要走了。”
to keep doing this thing." That's the
继续做这件事。”就是这样。
common denominator that ordinary people
普通人的共同点
can learn from is like endurance and
可以从中学习到耐力之类的东西
longevity is usually where the big
长寿通常是关键所在。
wealth is made. Endurance. Keep it
财富是创造出来的。耐力。留着它
going. Endurance is hard. Yeah. Larry
去。耐力训练很难。是的。拉里
Ellison, who is the the founder of um of
埃里森是um的创始人
Oracle, did an interview in the 1990s
Oracle公司在20世纪90年代进行了一次采访。
and they asked him about Bill Gates, who
他们问他关于比尔·盖茨的事，比尔·盖茨是谁。
was a friend but also rival back then.
当时既是朋友又是竞争对手。
And Larry Ellison was like, "The secret
拉里·埃里森当时说：“秘密就在这里。”
to Bill Gates, yes, he's very smart, but
对比尔·盖茨来说，是的，他非常聪明，但是
there's a lot of smart people out
外面有很多聪明人。
there." And he was like, "No offense,
他就那样说：“别介意，
but there's a lot of people smarter than
但还有很多比他更聪明的人。
Bill Gates out there, but nobody has
比尔·盖茨就在那里，但没人……
more endurance than Bill Gates. He will
比比尔·盖茨更有耐力。他将
outwork you every single time. You
每次都比你更努力。你
cannot he he'll keep it going for as
他不能，他会一直坚持下去。
long as he needs to keep it going to
只要他需要继续下去……
beat you." And that's his that's his
打败你。” 这就是他的，这就是他的
skill. It's not intelligence, it's
技能。这不是智力，这是
endurance. On this point of
耐力。关于这一点
perseverance, why is perseverance so
毅力，为什么毅力如此重要
key? Like, if we break it down into what
钥匙？比如，如果我们把它分解成什么呢？
what's actually happening when you
当你……时，实际发生了什么？
persevere? I think it's two things. It's
坚持下去？我认为有两个原因。它是
one in any endeavor that's going to pay
在任何能带来回报的事业中，这都是一项值得投入的。
off, it's going to be difficult. It's
关掉它，那就难了。它是
going to be ext there's going to be more
还会有更多，还会有更多
roadblocks and speed bumps and collapses
路障、减速带和坍塌
than you want. It's absolutely
比你想要的还要多。绝对是
inevitable. The unofficial model at at
不可避免的。非官方模型位于
Nvidia, the giant chip company, it's one
英伟达，这家芯片巨头公司，是其中之一。
of the most valuable companies in the
最有价值的公司之一
world, is we are always 30 days from
世界，我们总是距离现在还有30天。
going out of business. Now, they're not
倒闭了。现在，他们不是了。
it's one of the most successful
它是最成功的案例之一。
companies in the world, but they
世界上的公司，但是它们
understand what is true for every
理解对每个人来说什么是真理。
business, which is that business is is
商业，也就是商业是
hard. Like every business is a knife
难的。就像每家企业都是一把刀
fight. of every company that you own or
斗争。你拥有的每一家公司或
start is going to be very difficult and
开局会非常困难，
you need the perseverance to get through
你需要有毅力才能坚持下去。
that. That's one element. The other is
那。这是其中一个因素。另一个是
compound interest. That's what builds
复利。这就是建设的本质。
wealth. What compound interest is and
财富。什么是复利？
why it is so powerful like the people
它为何如此强大，就像人民一样。
who get rich from it are not the people
真正从中致富的不是那些人。
who earn very high returns. It's people
那些获得非常高回报的人。是人
who earn good returns for a long period
长期获得良好回报的人
of time. Like all compound interest is
时间。就像所有复利一样
it's like it's it's returns to the power
就像它重新获得了权力一样。
of time. And if you remember like eighth
时间。如果你还记得第八个
grade math, that exponent like time
数学成绩，那个指数就像时间一样
that's doing all the heavy lifting in
它承担了所有繁重的工作。
there. And so in investing, if you can
那里。所以在投资方面，如果你能
be good, merely good, if you can just be
做一个好人，仅仅是做一个好人，如果你能做到这一点的话。
average for an above average period of
在高于平均水平的时期内保持平均水平
time, you do phenomenal. And this is
时间，你做得非常出色。这就是
where this is like the most
这里就像最
misunderstood thing about investing.
关于投资的一个误解。
Most investors are like, "How do I earn
大多数投资者都会问：“我该如何赚钱？”
the highest returns? I want to make the
收益最高？我想制作
best investments, highest returns." And
最佳投资，最高回报。
you can do well doing that. You're much
你这样做会做得很好。你很……
more likely to do well if you're like,
如果你是以下类型的人，则更有可能取得成功：
"Hey, I just want average returns, but I
“嘿，我只想获得平均收益，但是……”
want to be so durable and have so much
想要如此耐用，拥有如此之多
endurance that I can earn average
我能获得的平均耐力
returns for 40 years. And if I can be
40年来持续盈利。如果我能……
average for 40 years, I'm going to end
平均40年，我即将结束
up in the top 1%." How do you make that
跻身前1%。” 你是怎么做到的？
real for someone listening who's making,
对于正在聆听并创作的人来说，这很真实。
you know, $1,000 a month disposable
你知道，每月1000美元的零花钱。
income? So, they've got $1,000 to play
收入？所以，他们有1000美元可以玩。
with a month potentially. How to like
可能需要一个月的时间。如何点赞
how if they've never heard about this
如果他们从未听说过这件事呢？
this idea of compounding interest before
复利的概念以前
and the magic that it can create if left
以及如果放任不管，它所能创造的奇迹。
to its own devices for a long enough
让它自行运转足够长的时间
period of time. What is the like simple
一段时间。简单来说，它是什么？
way to show them the power of it? So
如何向他们展示它的力量？所以
take index funds which are just a very
以指数基金为例，它们非常……
simple collection of businesses at a
简单的企业集合
very low fee. You can buy one stock but
费用非常低。你可以买一只股票，但是
it's a collection of hundreds and
这是一个包含数百个元素的集合
hundreds of different businesses. You
数百家不同的企业。你
own Apple and Amazon and Coca-Cola. you
拥有苹果、亚马逊和可口可乐。你
own you own all the companies in the
你拥有所有这些公司。
world. And so it's the most boring,
世界。所以这是最无聊的，
bland, average way to invest. If you
平淡无奇的投资方式。如果你
invest in that in a very simple way and
以一种非常简单的方式进行投资，
you do that consistently for 20 or 30
你坚持这样做20或30分钟。
years with no skill, with no expertise,
多年来缺乏技能和专业知识
where you're not getting stock tips from
你无法从中获得股票内幕消息
anyone, it's the most boring way to
对任何人来说，这都是最无聊的方式
invest. If you do it consistently for 30
投资。如果你坚持这样做30天
years, you will almost certainly end up
多年以后，你几乎肯定会最终
in the top 1% of investors. you almost
跻身前1%投资者之列。你几乎
certainly beat literally 95% of Wall
当然，它击败了95%的墙。
Street pros who were trying to outsmart
试图智胜街头职业选手
the market, trying to outwit the market
市场，试图战胜市场
and were unable to keep it going for 30
并且无法维持30分钟。
years. And so this is where if you can
年。所以，如果你可以的话，这里就是你的机会。
just be average for an above average
保持平均水平，就能达到高于平均水平的水平
period of time, you'll be amazing. I
一段时间后，你会变得很棒。我
mean, it's it's it's probably similar in
意思是，它可能类似
health that like if you want to be
如果你想拥有健康的身体，那就去做吧。
healthy, yes, you can go out and become
健康，是的，你可以出去走走，成为
the best bodybuilder in the world, the
世界上最好的健美运动员，
best marathon runner in in in the whole
整个马拉松界最优秀的跑者
world. But actually, if you just work
世界。但实际上，如果你只是努力工作的话。
out just like modest workouts a couple
就像进行一些适度的锻炼一样。
times a week for 30 years, you're going
每周几次，持续30年，你就是在去
to be one of the healthiest people in
成为最健康的人之一
your town. If you can work out two or
你的城镇。如果你能算出两个或
three times a week for 30 years
每周三次，持续30年
consistently and eat a good diet
坚持规律饮食并保持良好的饮食习惯
consistently for 30, you'll be one of
坚持30天，你将成为其中之一
the healthiest people that you know. And
你认识的最健康的人。和
it's the same in investing. It's like
投资也是如此。就像
the people who do the best are not the
做得最好的人并非……
geniuses. It's the people who are
天才们。是人。
ordinary for a very long period of time.
很长一段时间都平常无奇。
I was thinking about a a very simple
我当时在想一个非常简单的事情
example. So that there's a coffee in my
例子。所以，我的杯子里有一杯咖啡。
cup today and the coffee might cost $5.
今天一杯咖啡可能要5美元。
Now with the laws of compounding
现在，根据复利定律
returns, if I don't have that coffee
如果我没有那杯咖啡，就退货。
today in 40 years, if I got 8% which is
今天，40年后，如果我得到8%的收益率，那就是
I think the S&amp;P 500 get gives about 8%.
我认为标普500指数的涨幅约为8%。
Then in 40 years time instead of the the
40年后，而不是
coffee that I had every day with an 8%
我每天都喝一杯酒精度为 8% 的咖啡。
interest return, I would have $440,000.
如果计入利息回报，我将拥有 44 万美元。
If you did a coffee every day. Yes. Yes.
如果你每天都喝咖啡的话。是的。是的。
Yes, assuming the coffee costs $5. Now,
是的，假设咖啡售价为 5 美元。现在，
I like coffee. You do, too. I I I I
我喜欢咖啡。你也是。我 我 我 我
don't want people to listen to that and
不想让人们听到那些话。
say, "I should I should stop drinking my
我说，“我应该停止喝酒。”
coffee." But it's a powerful example. Uh
咖啡。”但这的确是个很有力的例子。呃
there's a book called The Snowball,
有一本书叫《滚雪球》，
which is kind of the most detailed do
这算是最详细的了
biography of Warren Buffett, and it
沃伦·巴菲特的传记，以及它
would talk about how when he was on his
他会谈到当他……的时候
adulthood, he wouldn't want to get
成年后，他不想再经历那种生活。
haircuts because in his mind, a haircut
理发，因为在他看来，理发
would cost $10,000 because it was a $2
因为它是2美元的，所以要花费10000美元。
haircut. But if he invested that money
理发。但如果他把那笔钱投资出去的话。
in in the way that he knew he could and
以他知道自己能做到的方式，
leave it alone for 50 years, whatever it
不管怎样，放着不管50年。
would be, he didn't want to get a car
没错，他不想买车。
wash cuz he would tell his wife, he's
洗漱是因为他会告诉他妻子，他是
like, "That's a $5,000 car wash." She's
比如，“这可是价值 5000 美元的洗车服务啊。”她是
like, "What do you mean it costs a
比如，“你的意思是说它要花多少钱？”
dollar?" No, no, no, but if I invest
美元？”不，不，不，但是如果我投资
that money and leave it alone. So, he
把钱留下来，别再动它了。所以，他
was always thinking about not what
一直在想的不是什么
something costs today, but what he could
如今某样东西要花不少钱，但他本可以拥有的。
grow that money into in the future. I
让这笔钱在未来增值。我
was just thinking about Warren Buffett
我刚才在想沃伦·巴菲特
getting his haircuts. So, I thought, how
他去理发了。所以，我想，该如何
old's Warren Buffett now? He's 93. Okay.
老沃伦·巴菲特现在怎么样了？他93岁了。好的。
So let's say for 80 years if Warren
假设沃伦执政80年
Buffett didn't get a say a $5 haircut
巴菲特没资格说自己理发要花5美元
and instead took the put it somewhere in
相反，他把它放在了某个地方。
the S&amp;P 500 an index fund which by the
标普500指数基金，即指数基金，由……
way you can invest in on your
你可以通过这种方式投资你的
phone 80 years later Warren Buffett
80年后沃伦·巴菲特的电话
would have 10.3 million. That's it.
将有1030万。就是这样。
That's it. And that's why he's that's
就是这样。这就是他为什么会那样的原因。
why he's worth a quarter trillion
他为何身价高达2500亿美元
dollars today is because you go through
如今的美元之所以如此之多，是因为你经历了
90 years of thinking like that and it it
90年来一直这样想，而且
really adds up. Now that you always have
确实加起来不少。既然你一直拥有
to preface this by being like please
首先，请允许我这样说。
drink your coffee and get a haircut.
喝杯咖啡，然后去剪个头发。
It's always it's always a balance but
这始终是一种平衡，但
but also understand how incredible it
但也要明白这有多么不可思议。
can be by putting away doing very
可以通过收拾东西来做到非常
ordinary things for a long period of
平凡的事物持续很长时间
time can lead to magic. It is magic as
时间可以创造奇迹。它就像魔法一样
well. That's such a perfect word for it
出色地。这个词用在这里真是太贴切了。
because it seems it's magic because it's
因为它看起来像魔法，因为它……
not intuitive at all. Yes. You don't you
一点也不直观。是的。你不
don't understand it. You're like wait
我不明白。你就像在等
what? I don't I can't understand how a
什么？我不明白，我无法理解……
haircut can turn into $10 million. Yeah.
理发可以赚到1000万美元。是的。
It's not
它不是
intuitive. Like we're we're not there's
直觉的。就像我们不在那里一样
a great example from my friend Michael
我的朋友迈克尔就是一个很好的例子。
Batnneck. He said if I ask you what is 8
蝙蝠领。他说，如果我问你8是多少，
plus 8 plus 8 plus 8? You can figure
加 8 加 8 加 8？你可以想象
that out in your head quickly. But if I
赶紧把这些想法记下来。但是如果我
said what is 8 * 8 * 8 * 8 * 8? Forget
问：8 * 8 * 8 * 8 * 8 * 8 等于多少？忘记
about it. Can't do it. We're not made to
关于它。做不到。我们并非天生如此
think
思考
exponentially. We're not meant to think
呈指数级增长。我们不应该思考
in multiplicative terms because nothing
就乘法而言，因为什么都没有
was exponential once upon a time. That's
曾经呈指数级增长。那是
largely true. Yeah. You know what I
基本属实。是的。你知道我
mean? I can't think of anything that was
意思是？我想不出有什么事是
really exponential before. Yeah. I'm
以前是指数级增长。是的。我是
sure we could come up with a couple
当然，我们可以想出几个例子。
examples in in nature and whatnot. There
自然界中的例子等等。那里
there's there's lots of of compounding
复利效应非常显著。
in nature and that's that's kind of the
在自然界中，这就是某种程度上的
core of of evolution is like things
进化的核心就像事物一样
building upon each other over time.
随着时间的推移，它们在彼此的基础上不断发展。
Yeah. Maybe brushing your teeth or decay
是的。可能是刷牙或蛀牙。
be considered. Yeah. But you know
值得考虑。是的。但你知道
certainly the the stock market is the
当然，股市是……
most pertinent example in most people's
大多数人最相关的例子
lives. But there's also a lot of like
生命。但也有很多类似的东西。
bad habits compound. Smoking one
坏习惯会越积越多。吸烟
cigarette is not not that big a deal.
香烟没那么严重。
Smoking one cigarette every day for 30
每天吸一支烟，持续30天
years, big deal. Smoking two packs a day
几年，没什么大不了的。一天抽两包烟
for 30, big deal. So there are things
30岁？那算什么。所以，有些事情……
that like in small doses they're not
就像小剂量服用时那样，它们并不
that big a deal. But in if you do them
那算什么大事？但如果你这样做的话
consistently for a long period of time,
长期持续，
it leads to negative magic. So what's
它会导致邪恶的魔法。那么，什么是……
your view then on saving money? I you're
那么你对存钱有什么看法？我你是
you're working on a book currently which
你目前正在写一本书，
is being released in October this year
将于今年十月上映
called The Art of Spending Money. Yeah.
名为《花钱的艺术》。是的。
What's your view on saving money? You
你对存钱有什么看法？你
told me to have the coffee cut my hair.
让我去咖啡馆剪头发。
Yeah. I I view savings as one thing most
是的。我认为储蓄是最重要的一件事。
people view saving money as like as idle
人们把存钱视为一种懒惰的行为。
s like like if you're not spending it
如果你不花钱的话，就好像……
it's just sitting in the bank doing
它就放在银行里，什么也不做。
nothing and it's just kind of a it's
没什么，就只是……
just wasted money sitting there. I've
坐在那里白白浪费了钱。我已经
never viewed it like that at all. I view
我从未那样想过。我的看法
savings as little tokens of independence
储蓄是独立自主的象征。
and every dollar that I save is a little
我省下的每一美元都是一点小小的
piece of my time in the future that I
我未来的一部分时间
own and I control. It's just deferred
拥有并由我控制。只是延期了。
spending and I view that as
消费，我认为这是
independence. Like so if you have a lot
独立。比如，如果你有很多
of savings, it's not just like hoarding
储蓄并不等同于囤积。
money and I'm not going to do anything
钱，我什么都不会做。
with it. And it's not even that I'm
和它一起。而且，这甚至还不是因为我
saving this money so that I can spend it
把这笔钱存起来，这样我就可以花掉它。
in the future. If I save a dollar today,
将来。如果我今天存下一美元，
I have a dollar more independence today.
今天我又多了一块钱的自由支配权。
I benefit from that today, right now.
我今天，就在此刻，从中受益。
Like I feel more independent because of
感觉自己因此变得更加独立了。
it. And I am more independent because of
它。正因如此，我变得更加独立。
it. So I view again my my top financial
它。所以我再次查看了我的顶级财务状况。
goal by far and I think this is true for
迄今为止的目标，我认为这是正确的。
most people whether they know it or not.
大多数人，无论他们是否意识到这一点。
What they really want out of money is
他们真正想要的是从钱那里得到的是
independence and autonomy and is be
独立和自主，并且是
being able to do things on their own
能够独立完成事情
terms, live the life that they want to
按照他们想要的方式，过上他们想要的生活。
live. And I view the oxygen of
居住。而我则认为氧气
independence is is savings. And what's
独立就是储蓄。什么？
the opposite of that? Is it debt? Debt.
相反的情况呢？这是债务吗？债务。
Yeah. Debt is a piece of your future
是的。债务是你未来的一部分
that somebody else owns. It's the polar
那是别人的财产。这是极地
opposite of it. When you go into debt,
相反的。当你负债时，
you're saying three years from now, this
你是说三年后，这个
company owns a part of my time. They own
公司占用了我一部分时间。他们拥有
my labor in the future. And savings is
我未来的劳动。而储蓄是
the opposite. Savings is in the future.
恰恰相反。储蓄是面向未来的。
I have this stored up. I have this
我已经把这个存起来了。我有这个
consumption store stored up in the
消费储存在
future. I can do whatever I want with
未来。我可以随心所欲地处置它
it. I think you know you've written a
它。我想你知道你已经写过一篇
book called the psychology of money but
一本书叫做《金钱心理学》，
as you were talking there I was thinking
你刚才说话的时候，我一直在想……
gosh this is all psychology again
天哪，这又是心理学了。
because at the heart of this we all have
因为归根结底，我们所有人都有
our own unique relationship with money
我们与金钱之间独特的联系
and there's lots of people that won't
而且还有很多人不会
even look at their their own bank
甚至看看他们自己的银行
statements. They won't look at their own
声明。他们不愿审视自己。
revolute or Monzo app in the morning.
早上用 Revolute 或 Monzo 应用。
They avoid their credit cards in terms
他们尽量避免使用信用卡。
of like their credit card statements.
就像他们的信用卡账单一样。
And to even start talking about these
甚至开始谈论这些
subjects of saving and spending, we
关于储蓄和消费的主题，我们
probably need to preface it with some
可能需要先加一些说明。
kind of like mindset or mentality
有点像思维模式或心态
towards your relationship with money.
你与金钱的关系。
Yeah. I think the most important is uh
是的。我认为最重要的是……
there are two topics in life that will
人生中有两个话题将会
impact you whether you like them or not.
无论你喜欢与否，它们都会对你产生影响。
That's health and money. It doesn't
那关乎健康和金钱。它不
matter if you not you're not interested
如果你不感兴趣也没关系。
in those topics. Those topics are
在这些主题方面。这些话题是
interested in you and they will impact
对你感兴趣，他们会对你产生影响
your life. You can have a wonderful life
你的人生。你可以拥有美好的生活
not knowing anything about chemistry or
对化学一无所知
meteorology if you don't care about
如果你不关心气象学的话
those topics. You cannot have a good
这些话题。你不能拥有一个好的
life if you don't care about money and
如果你不在乎金钱，生活就会是这样。
and health. And I that's true for
以及健康。对我来说，情况确实如此。
everybody everywhere. And so I think
世界各地的人们。所以我认为
everyone has an obligation to understand
每个人都有义务理解
their own relationship with money. Now
他们自身与金钱的关系。现在
some people are going to be, you know,
有些人会，你知道的，
fanatics about it and other people just
狂热分子和其他人只是
view money as just kind of like a
把金钱看作是一种……
necessary tool that they need to get
他们需要的必要工具
through life. But you have to understand
一生。但你必须明白
how it works and what it's doing to you
它是如何运作的，以及它对你有什么影响。
financially and psychologically. And so
经济上和心理上。所以
much of modern ills have to do with
现代社会的许多弊病都与此有关
envy, jealousy, feel like you're falling
嫉妒、羡慕，感觉自己正在坠落
behind relative to other people. The
相对于其他人而言落后。这
core of that is usually financial. And
其核心通常是财务方面的。和
so even if you're not the kind of person
所以即使你不是那种人
who's like, I I don't care about the
谁会说，我不在乎
stock market and like I don't really
股市，我其实不太了解。
care that much about money. I like
你对金钱有那么大的热情吗？我喜欢
having fun with my friends. That's
和朋友们玩得很开心。那是
great. But there is a huge component of
伟大的。但其中有很大一部分是
sociology and just what's going on in
社会学以及正在发生的事情
the world all the time that is
世界一直如此。
financial. And I think money is like
金融的。我觉得金钱就像
such an interesting window into people's
这是一个了解人们内心世界的绝佳窗口。
lives. You can learn so much about
生命。你可以学到很多关于……
somebody if you understand what they do
如果你了解某人的所作所为，就会明白他们做什么。
with their money, how they think about
他们如何看待自己的金钱
money, how much they talk about money,
他们谈论金钱的频率有多高？
how much they want to show off, how much
他们有多想炫耀，多少
how much attention they're putting into
他们投入了多少精力
their clothes and their cars and their
他们的衣服、他们的车和他们的
jewelry to show other people how much
用珠宝来向别人展示你的财富
money that they have. You learn so much
他们拥有的钱。你学到了很多东西
about someone's psychology. You know, if
关于某人的心理。你知道，如果
I learned about your politics, I I don't
我了解你的政治立场，我不了解。
know what they are, but if I learned
我知道它们是什么，但如果我学会了
about your politics, I might learn
关于你的政治观点，我或许会有所了解。
something about you. But if I sat down
关于你的一些事。但如果我坐下来
and I said, "Tell me everything about
我说：“把所有关于……”
your money. Tell me how much you make,
你的钱。告诉我你收入多少。
how much you spend, what do you value,
你消费多少，你重视什么？
what do you want to do. I learned so
你想让我做什么。我学到了很多
much about your personality. In your
很多都与你的性格有关。在你的
work on the psychology of money, how
研究金钱心理学，如何
much did you think about trauma as a
你对创伤作为一种……思考过多少？
protagonist in the story of one's
故事中的主人公
financial relationships? I think less
财务关系？我觉得少一些
about trauma. That's a component of it,
关于创伤。这是其中的一个组成部分。
but more so it's just that we are all
但更重要的是，我们都是
prisoners of our unique past. No matter
我们独特历史的囚徒。不管
what that is, that's trauma for a lot of
那是什么，对很多人来说都是一种创伤。
people, different forms of trauma. But
人们，不同形式的创伤。但
you grew up in a in a different country
你是在另一个国家长大的
than I did. You have different parents
比我做得更好。你们有不同的父母
than I do, different values. were
与我不同，价值观也不同。是
slightly different ages and so you saw a
年龄略有不同，所以你看到了
different side of the world than I did
与我所在世界的另一端
and that taught you different values. It
那让你学会了不同的价值观。它
taught you to aspire to different things
教会你追求不同的目标
than I did and you and I in a lot of
比我做的还要多，你和我有很多
ways are a lot alike. I think if you if
方法有很多相似之处。我认为如果你
we sat down and like talked about
我们坐下来，聊了起来。
broader topics, we'd agree on 90% of
在更广泛的话题上，我们有90%的意见可以达成一致。
things, but we are different. And so we
但我们不一样。所以，我们
shouldn't pretend that what I want to do
不应该假装我想做什么
with my money is what you should do. And
你应该用我的钱来做这件事。和
I think a lot of times when people argue
我认为很多时候人们争论的时候……
about money and they're like, "Oh,
谈到钱的事，他们会说：“哦，
you're investing wrong or you're you're
你投资错了，或者你是……
you're spending you're you're not
你正在花费你你不
spending enough. You're spending too
花费足够。你花的钱太多了。
much." It's not actually people
很多。”实际上并不是人。
disagreeing with each other. It's people
彼此意见不合。是人
who came from very different backgrounds
他们来自截然不同的背景
talking over each other and they just
他们互相打断对方说话，然后就……
have different aspirations for what you
对你所拥有的东西有不同的期望
want to do. So, everyone is is so
想做。所以，每个人都是如此
different and they're they're a prisoner
不同，他们是囚犯
of of their past. My my brother-in-law
他们的过去。我的姐夫
is a a social worker. And I may have
是一名社会工作者。我可能
brought this up when I the first time I
我第一次提出这个问题时，
was on your podcast, but I think about
我上过你的播客，但我一直在想……
it all the time. And uh in social work,
一直都是这样。呃，在社会工作领域，
when you're working with very
当你与非常
disadvantaged kids, a lot of those kids
很多弱势儿童
who are are homeless and foster children
无家可归的儿童和寄养儿童
behave very poorly at school. They do
在学校表现非常差。他们确实如此
very poorly. Their grades are terrible
非常糟糕。他们的成绩很糟糕。
in school. They're always getting in
在学校里。他们总能进来。
fights. And he said as a social worker,
战斗。他说，作为一名社会工作者，
he said, "We have a saying in social
他说：“我们在社交方面有一句谚语。”
work. It is all behavior makes sense
工作。这一切行为都合情合理
with enough information."
“掌握足够的信息。”
So, you look at this child who is uh
所以，你看看这个孩子，他……
getting into fights on the playground
在操场上打架
and failing all of his classes. And it's
他所有科目都挂科了。而且是
easy for the teacher to be like, "What's
老师很容易会说：“什么？”
your problem? This is not that hard.
你的问题是什么？这并不难。
Just behave. Just stop doing this." And
守规矩点。别再这样做了。”
then you look at what that kid's going
然后你看看那孩子在做什么
through at home. Maybe their parents are
在家完成。也许他们的父母是
beating them. Maybe they're they're
打败他们。也许他们是……
their foster children. They're orphans.
他们的养子女。他们是孤儿。
Once you piece together what's going on
一旦你把事情的来龙去脉拼凑起来
in their life, you're like, I kind of
在他们的生活中，你会觉得，我有点
understand. All behavior makes sense
理解。所有行为都有其道理
with enough information. And I think you
掌握足够的信息。而且我认为你
can apply that to a lot of areas in
可以将其应用于很多领域
life, money especially, where you're
生活，尤其是金钱，你身在何处
like, you see someone driving a yellow
比如，你看到有人开着一辆黄色的车
Lamborghini, there's a story there about
兰博基尼，这里面有个故事……
someone's past. I'm not judging it, but
某人的过去。我不是在评判它，但是
there's a story in there of someone
里面有个关于某人的故事。
being like, I want people to know how
就像，我想让人们知道如何
much money I made. And it's not a
我赚了很多钱。而且它不是
criticism, but there's there's a story.
批评之声不绝于耳，但这背后却有故事。
There's something that happened in your
你身上发生了一些事。
life that that that led you to there.
把你带到那里的，是你的人生经历。
And we all have that's not a criticism
我们都有这种感觉，这不是批评。
because I have bits of my past that
因为我过去的经历中有一些片段……
influence how I manage money today, too.
这也影响了我如今的理财方式。
So, just recognizing that there's no one
所以，只要意识到这一点就行了。
right answer in math. 2 plus two is four
数学中的正确答案。二加二等于四
for me and you. There is a right answer.
为了你和我。有一个正确答案。
Money's not like that. We're all just
金钱并非如此。我们都只是
kind of trying to figure out what works
我正在尝试弄清楚什么方法有效。
given the lens that we see the world
从我们看待世界的视角来看
through. This is a bit of a bizarre
通过。这有点奇怪
question, but it had me thinking as
这个问题让我陷入了沉思。
you're speaking about mortality as it
你谈论的是死亡，就像……
relates to money. Because one of the
与金钱有关。因为其中一个
perspectives on money is
对金钱的看法是
yolo. Yeah. Do you know what I mean? I'm
人生苦短，及时行乐。是的。你明白我的意思吗？我是
only going to live once, so I might as
人生只有一次，所以我或许应该
well have a good time. I think I
祝你们玩得开心。我觉得我
definitely have a more of a bias in that
肯定在这方面更有偏见。
direction, although I'm not fully in
方向，虽然我还没有完全进入。
that direction. And my brother, who's a
那个方向。还有我的哥哥，他是一个
year older than me that went as one that
比我大一岁的那个人，就是其中之一。
gave me your book and has worked as a
你给了我你的书，这本书一直陪伴着我。
stock broker, an actuarial scientist, at
股票经纪人，精算科学家，在
12 years old, he was budgeting his
他12岁的时候就开始做预算了。
pocket money on an Excel document
Excel 文档中的零花钱
whereas I was just spending, spending,
而我当时却一直在花钱、花钱，
spending. and he thinks much more long
开支。而且他思考的时间要长得多。
term. He's like investing in his pension
学期。他就像是在为自己的养老金做投资。
at 21. Yeah. Whereas I was like at the
21岁。是的。而我当时就像……
casino, not the not the literal casino,
赌场，不是指字面意义上的赌场。
a figurative casino. I was taking bigger
一个比喻意义上的赌场。我当时服用的是更大剂量。
risks and just rolling the dice. And my
风险和碰运气。而我的
somewhat illogical way of rationalizing
某种程度上不合逻辑的解释方式
my behavior and not investing as much in
我的行为以及没有投入那么多精力
my pension was I'm only going to live
我的养老金只够我活一段时间。
once anyway, so I might as well just
反正已经有一次了，所以我不妨就这么做吧。
enjoy my life. Yeah. And when we talk
享受生活。是的。当我们谈论
about the coffees and saving and all
关于咖啡、省钱等等
this stuff, a lot of people will be
很多人会喜欢这些东西。
thinking, "Yes, but compounding's fine,
心想，“是的，但是复利没问题，
but I want to enjoy life." Enjoy life. I
但我想要享受生活。享受生活。我
think about a thing when I was I was in
回想一下我当时在……的时候发生的一件事
my early 20s at this point, and I met I
我当时二十出头，遇到了我
there's a co-orker of mine, and he was I
我有个同事，他就是……
don't know 10 years older than me. And
不知道谁比我大10岁。和
um he had $25,000 of credit card debt,
嗯，他有25000美元的信用卡债务。
which I could not fathom at the time.
当时我完全无法理解。
That was such an incomprehensible amount
那真是个难以想象的数字。
of credit card debt that he was paying
他正在偿还的信用卡债务
17% interest on. And at the time I just
年利率17%。当时我只是
thought and and all the debt came from
思想和所有债务都源于
trips that he had taken. He traveled
他曾去过的旅行。他旅行了
Europe and traveled through Asia and had
欧洲，并游历了亚洲，还有
a great time doing it, but he put it all
他做这件事的时候非常开心，但他把一切都倾注其中了。
on his credit card. At the time I
在他的信用卡上。当时我
remember thinking, you idiot. You do you
你还记得当时的想法吗，你这个白痴。你做你自己
understand what this is going to do to
了解这将对……产生什么影响
your future? And then he died when he
你的未来？然后他就去世了。
was about 32. Wow. And now and then and
当时大概32岁。哇。时不时地
then I remember thinking like, I'm so
然后我记得当时我想，我真是太……
glad you took those trips. I'm so glad
很高兴你去了那些地方。我太高兴了
you went into that credit card debt
你背上了那笔信用卡债务
because the truth was at age 32, he had
因为事实是，他32岁时就已经……
seen more and done more than most people
比大多数人见多识广，经历丰富。
would at age 62. And so I think about
62岁时会这样。所以我在想……
that a lot of like it's always a balance
很多时候，这就像是一种平衡。
and the truth is that you and I don't
而事实是，你我并不……
know are we going to live until we're
我们知道我们是否会活到……
110 or die tomorrow. Nobody knows. Of
110，否则明天就死。没人知道。的
course, one thing I think a lot about as
当然，我一直在思考的一件事是……
a parent is that I've been a big saver
一位家长告诉我，我一直很会存钱。
my entire life since I got my first job
自从我找到第一份工作以来，我的整个人生都充满了挑战。
at age 16. I've saved the majority of
16岁时，我存下了大部分钱。
what I made in every job that I've ever
我过去每份工作的收入都一样。
been in. And it would be easy to look at
已经进去了。而且很容易就能看出来。
someone like me and say, "Morgan, if you
像我这样的人会说：“摩根，如果你……”
were on your deathbed tomorrow, you'd
如果你明天就躺在病床上等死，你会
probably regret the vacations you didn't
你可能后悔那些没去的旅行。
take and the the dinners you didn't
拿走，还有你没吃的晚餐
have, right? You'd regret that." My
有吧？你会后悔的。
answer is absolutely not. Because if I
答案绝对是否定的。因为如果我
was on my deathbed tonight, I would take
今晚我躺在病床上奄奄一息，我会……
so much joy knowing that my wife and
知道我的妻子和
kids are going to be okay because of
孩子们会没事的，因为
what I saved. That would that would that
我存下的钱。那将会是那样。
would be the the worst situation I would
这将是最糟糕的情况。
be in is on my deathbed and looking at
躺在病床上，奄奄一息，看着
my wife and kids and knowing you guys
我的妻子和孩子们，还有认识你们。
are screwed. you get I'm leaving I'm
完蛋了。你会明白我要走了。
leaving you debt, you know, and so but
你知道，这会让你背负债务，所以……
that might change as I get older. And so
随着年龄增长，我的想法可能会改变。所以
when my kids are hopefully financially
希望我的孩子经济条件允许的时候
self-sufficient, will I still think
自给自足，我还会这么想吗？
that, you know, will I still have that
你知道，我还会拥有那份东西吗？
need to be like, I need to work and save
我需要像那样，我需要工作和存钱。
to provide for my young kids? That's not
为了养活我的年幼的孩子？那不是
going to last forever. So, it'll change
将会永远持续下去。所以，它会改变。
throughout your life. That is literally
贯穿你的一生。那确实是字面意义上的。
the worst thought in the world, isn't
世界上最糟糕的想法，并非如此。
it? to think that you could be on your
它？想想你可能正在……
deathbed and look over at your family
临终之际，回头看看你的家人。
and know that they're about to struggle
他们知道自己即将面临困境。
with bills and with food and they're
他们有账单要付，有食物要吃，他们……
probably going to have to sell the house
可能不得不卖掉房子了。
and their lifestyle is completely going
他们的生活方式完全改变了
to change when you go. It's I I don't
到时候再换。是我，我不
even have kids yet, but I was just
我甚至还没有孩子，但我只是
thinking about my partner because
因为想到了我的伴侣
there's no there's no there's no worse
没有，没有，没有更糟的了。
nightmare than that. I think there's an
比那更可怕。我认为存在一个
opposite of that, which is in several of
与此相反，这在几个方面都有体现。
the books and studies that have been
已有的书籍和研究
done on on dying. You know, there are
死亡已完成。你知道，有
quite a few people who have very
有不少人非常
peaceful deaths, people who know they're
安详的死亡，那些知道自己正在死去的人
going to die of terminal illness and
即将死于绝症
they're pretty much at ease with it. And
他们对此相当适应。和
when you dig into like what's what is
当你深入探究真相时……
those people's psychology? How do you
这些人的心理状态如何？你如何
know you're going to die in six months
知道自己六个月后就会死
and you're kind of at ease with it? One
你对此感到很自在吗？一
of the big factors is knowing that your
关键因素之一是了解你的
family's going to be okay without you
没有你，家人也会过得很好。
because they are sufficient and they
因为它们足够了，而且
don't rely on you for wisdom and advice
不要指望你能提供智慧和建议
as much. They can take care of
差不多。他们可以照顾好
themselves. But the opposite, if you're
他们自己。但反过来，如果你是
on your deathbed and you're like, "My my
临终之际，你会想：“我的天哪……”
children, my spouse is gonna have a real
孩子们，我的配偶将会有一个真正的
hard time without me." That is that's
没有我的日子不好过。” 就是这样。
the most painful thing you can imagine.
你能想象到的最痛苦的事。
I could also imagine that one of the
我也可以想象，其中一个
great regrets one might have on their
人们可能会对自己的未来感到极大的遗憾
deathbed is just not having lived.
死亡意味着没有真正活过。
Because I was thinking about I sometimes
因为我有时会想我
ponder if I die now, how would I feel?
想想如果我现在就死，我会是什么感觉？
Like if I was given a diagnosis, God
就像如果我被确诊患病一样，上帝
forbid, um how would I feel? And I feel
如果……嗯，我会作何感想？我感觉
like I've really gone for it with my
就像我真的全力以赴了一样
life. Yeah. I feel like I've traveled.
生活。是的。感觉就像旅行过一样。
I've seen things. I've done things. I've
我见过世面。我做过一些事。我已经
met people, I've lived. So, there's a
我见过形形色色的人，也经历过人生百态。所以，这里有一个
certain feeling of there's a certain
某种感觉，好像有某种
smile on my face or gratitude when I
当我脸上露出微笑或表达感激之情时
think about this being the end. Yeah.
想想这就是结局吧。是的。
So, it's a balancing act, isn't it,
所以，这是一种平衡之道，不是吗？
between like
之间就像
between the two, between my friend who
在他们两人之间，在我的朋友之间，
buried himself in credit card debt, even
他甚至让自己深陷信用卡债务之中。
though I'm I'm glad like I'm glad he did
虽然我很高兴，就像我很高兴他这么做一样。
it given his short life versus the
考虑到他短暂的一生
people who save everything for the end.
凡事都留到最后的人。
David Cassidy, who's a very famous
大卫·卡西迪，他是一位非常著名的
childhood actor, had an incredible
童星出身，曾有过一段令人难以置信的经历
acting career. Um he died I don't know
演艺生涯。嗯，他去世了，我不知道。
when he died 10 years ago 15 years ago
他去世的时候是10年前，15年前
whatever it was he his last words were
无论他最后说的是什么，他最后的话是
so much wasted time those were his last
浪费了那么多时间，那是他最后的时光。
words and like you think about and this
文字，就像你思考的那样，还有这个
is someone who was like very rich and
是一个非常富有的人，
famous had like a very enviable life and
名人过着令人羡慕的生活，
you can't think of sadder last words
你无法想象还有比这更悲伤的遗言了。
than so much wasted time and I think
浪费了这么多时间，我觉得
like no matter this is like the the Jeff
不管怎样，这就像杰夫一样。
Bezos philosophy on business was he
贝佐斯的商业哲学是……
started Amazon because he was trying to
他创办亚马逊是因为他想……
imagine himself at age 90 looking back
想象一下他90岁时回首往事
and having the fewest regrets. He was
并且后悔最少。他是
like, "That that should be your
比如，“那应该是你的
framework for life is that when you're
人生的框架是，当你……
on your deathbed, you have the fewest
临终之际，你拥有的最少。
regrets possible." And he did it because
他可能会后悔。”他这么做是因为
he was like, "If I don't start Amazon,
他当时说：“如果我不创办亚马逊，
I'm going to regret it. But if if I do
我会后悔的。但如果我这样做的话
start Amazon and it fails, I won't
亚马逊创业失败了，我不会……
regret that." So, just understanding
对此感到遗憾。”所以，只是理解而已。
like I think that's a good philosophy.
我觉得这是一种很好的理念。
That's probably the the broadest
这可能是最广泛的了。
definition of risk is understanding what
风险的定义是理解什么
you're likely to regret in the future.
你将来很可能会后悔。
And I I I I don't think anyone has a
而且我认为没有人有
perfect calibration on that. Like it's
校准得非常完美。就像这样
there's a good chance that heaven forbid
很有可能，天哪，千万别
if you did get a diagnosis tomorrow as
如果你明天得到诊断结果的话
you just said that yes you would look
你刚才说你会去看
back and say man I really went for it
回去说，伙计，我真的全力以赴了。
but you also might look back and be like
但你回头看时也可能觉得
man and not not not you individually but
人，不是指你个人，而是指你这个人，
any of us would look back and say like
我们中的任何一个人回头都会说：
man I wish I was wish I had done this
我真希望我当时做了这件事
different I wish I was nicer to that
我希望我能对那个人更友善一些。
person I wish I had called this person
我希望我当时给这个人打的电话
more you know worked less right there I
你知道的越多，效果就越差。
think Brony wear found that that
想想Brony穿的衣服，那
palative nurse in Australia when she
在澳大利亚担任临终关怀护士时
interviewed people in their death beds
采访临终病人
that like I wish I'd worked less was
就像我希望自己少工作一点一样。
super high and not a single of those
超级高，而且一个也没有
people looked back in those situations
人们在那些情况下会回顾过去。
on their deathbed when they're 90 years
在他们90岁高龄临终之际
old will look back and say, "I wish I
老人们会回头说：“我希望我……”
worked harder." But virtually every one
更加努力了。”但几乎每个人都……
of them will say, "I wish I spent more
他们中有些人会说：“我真希望我花更多钱。”
time with my kids. I wish I spent more
和孩子们在一起的时光。我真希望我当时多花点钱。
time with my family. I I I I wish I was
与家人共度的时光。我希望我是
nicer to myself. I wish I'd let myself
对自己好一点。我真希望我当时能放手一搏。
be who I actually was." I think the top
“做真正的自己。”我认为最棒的
regret of the dying from her work was
她因工作而死，对此深感遗憾。
that I wish I'd lived a life more true
我希望自己能过上更真实的生活。
to myself, which I kind of interpret as
我对自己说，我大概是这样理解的：
like I wish I'd done something else. And
我真希望自己当初做了别的事。和
this gets back to the Chuck Feny idea of
这又回到了查克·芬尼的观点。
the billionaire who said, "I I don't
那位亿万富翁说：“我不……”
want to I want to live my way." Like
我想，我想按照自己的方式生活。就像
being independent is so core to people's
独立自主对人们来说至关重要。
happiness and as I said earlier like we
幸福，就像我之前说的，就像我们
come from different backgrounds we have
我们来自不同的背景
different aspirations but independence
不同的抱负，但都独立自主
is a very human natural universal
是一种非常人性化的自然普遍现象。
aspiration to be able to live life in
渴望能够过上这样的生活
your own way. I'm not sure if we talk
用你自己的方式。我不确定我们是否交谈过。
about this much but for that person who
差不多就是这样，但对于那个人来说
doesn't have financial independence
不具备经济独立性
because they're entrenched with debts
因为他们深陷债务泥潭
and bills and all these kinds of things.
还有账单以及所有这类事情。
How does one get out of that situation?
如何才能摆脱这种困境？
Because we can't
因为我们做不到
necessarily just save our way out of
未必只是为了省钱而逃
that situation, can we? People do. It's
这种情况可以吗？确实有人这么做。它是
difficult because it's likely that the
困难之处在于，很可能
mindset and psychology that got you
让你成功的心态和心理因素
there is going to be very difficult to
这将非常困难
break. Extremely difficult to break. I
休息。极难打破。我
heard this statistic one time that this
我曾经听过这个统计数据，那就是……
is a completely different topic, but I
这是完全不同的另一个话题，但是……
think this applies to a lot of things
我认为这适用于很多事情。
that the statistic that will is most
最能说明问题的统计数据是
predictive on whether you will cheat on
预测你是否会出轨
your spouse is how many people you slept
你配偶的人数就是你睡过的人数
with before you got married. The
在你结婚之前。这
implication being it's very difficult to
言下之意是，这非常困难
just flip a switch and say I'm a
只需拨动一下开关，然后说我是一个
different person now. And I think that
现在是另一个人了。而且我认为
that idea can apply to a lot of
这个想法可以应用于很多方面
different things in life. And the
生活中各种各样的事情。以及
psychology of I spend way more than I
我花的钱远远超过了我的预期。
make and I don't care about money and
赚钱，我不在乎钱。
debt, debt, debt. Some people can wake
债务，债务，债务。有些人可以醒来
up one day and say no more of that. I'm
有一天突然醒悟过来，不再说这些话了。我是
going I'm going to run in the other way.
我打算往反方向跑。
A lot of people find it very difficult
很多人都觉得这很难。
to do. I think one of the hard things
待办事项。我认为其中一件难事
about money that's hard to admit for a
关于金钱，有些事很难承认。
lot of people, but there's truth to it
很多人都这么说，但其中确实有道理。
is that on the nature nurture spectrum,
是在先天与后天关系的谱系中，
a lot of it does lean towards nature.
其中很多都与自然有关。
That some people are just wired, your
有些人天生如此，你的
brother was wired to plan and save and
哥哥天生就善于计划和储蓄，
you were wired to take entrepreneurial
你天生就具备创业精神
risks in in maybe a way that he wasn't.
他可能以某种方式承担了风险，而他并非如此。
And so a lot of it is yes, you can
所以很多时候，答案是肯定的，你可以。
learn. Yes, you can learn from others
学习。是的，你可以向他人学习。
and learn new ideas to think about. But
并学习新的思考方式。但
we shouldn't pretend that we can
我们不应该假装我们能
fundamentally rewire who we are.
从根本上重塑我们自己。
The hardest conversations are often the
最难的对话往往是
ones we avoid. But what if you had the
我们会避免的。但如果你拥有……
right question to start them with? Every
应该从哪个问题开始问他们呢？每一个
single guest on the diary of a co has
一位同事的日记里有一位单身客人
left behind a question in this diary.
日记里留下了一个问题。
And it's a question designed to
这是一个旨在……的问题。
challenge, to connect, and to go deeper
挑战、联结、深入探索
with the next guest. And these are all
和下一位客人一起。这些都是
the questions that I have here in my
我在这里提出的问题
hand. On one side, you've got the
手。一方面，你有……
question that was asked, the name of the
所提出的问题，即名称
person who wrote it, and on the other
写它的人，以及另一方面
side, if you scan that, you can watch
侧面，如果你扫描一下，就可以观看
the person who came after who answered
后面回答的人
it. 51 questions split across three
它。 51道题，分为三部分。
different levels. The warm-up level, the
不同层次。热身强度，
open up level, and the deep level. So,
打开层面，以及深层层面。所以，
you decide how deep the conversation
你决定谈话的深度。
goes. And people play these conversation
走了。人们会参与这些对话
cards in boardrooms at work, in
在工作场所的会议室里，人们玩扑克牌。
bedrooms, alone at night, and on first
卧室里，夜晚独自一人，以及最初
dates, and everywhere in between. I'll
日期，以及介于两者之间的任何时间。患病的
put a link to the conversation cards in
在文本中添加指向对话卡片的链接
the description below and you can get
以下描述可供参考，您可以获取
yours at the
您的
diary.com. Just to close off on this
diary.com。最后再补充一点。
point of saving money, are there any
省钱的要点是什么？
tactics or tricks or ways to think about
策略、技巧或思考方式
how to save for for those people that
如何为那些人储蓄
might be working in a factory and that
可能在工厂工作，而且
don't have a ton of excess income every
并没有很多多余的收入
month? I think if you view savings as I
月？我认为如果你把储蓄看作是……
need to save for something in the
需要攒钱买某样东西
future, that's hard for people to do. If
未来，这对人们来说很难做到。如果
you have a little bit of a a mindset
你有点……心态
shift and say, "I'm gonna save so I can
转变态度，说道：“我要存钱，这样我就可以……”
become more independent so that if I
变得更加独立，这样如果我
lose my job, I don't have to panic and
即使丢了工作，我也不必惊慌。
go find the first one that's available.
去找第一个能找到的。
I can take my time and find another
我可以慢慢找另一个。
one." That's independence. If you have a
一。“这就是独立。如果你有
medical emergency, you you're going to
医疗紧急情况，你要去
have some options on how to treat it and
有一些治疗方案可供选择，
where to go. That's independence.
去哪儿？这就是独立。
Viewing every dollar that you save as a
把省下的每一美元都看作是
token of independence, I think, is a
我认为，独立的象征是……
mindset shift that get makes it a lot
思维方式的转变会带来很多好处。
easier for people to do versus if
对人们来说，这比如果更容易做到的话
they're just saying, "I need to save to
他们只是说，“我需要存钱……”
buy a new car." I asked this because
买辆新车。”我这么问是因为
earlier on I looked at the most googled
之前我查看了谷歌搜索量最高的关键词。
questions around saving and the most
关于储蓄和最重要方面的问题
popular question is how to save money.
常见问题是如何省钱。
Yeah, how to save money. Now they might
是啊，怎么省钱。现在他们或许
be be asking like what to do with my
会问，我该怎么办
savings. Do I put it in a checking
节省。我应该把它放在支票账户里吗？
account? Do I put it in a savings
帐户？我应该把它存起来吗？
account? Do I invest it? That might be
帐户？我该投资吗？那或许是
part of it. Or it might be as similar as
其中一部分。或者它可能与此类似
you're saying with tariffs. People
你是说要征收关税。人们
genuinely don't know what it means. The
我真的不知道它是什么意思。这
second most googled is what is a high
谷歌搜索量第二高的问题是：什么是高
yield savings account? Yeah. And this I
收益储蓄账户？是的。而我
think that those questions they're not
认为这些问题并非如此
bad questions. There's no there's no bad
糟糕的问题。没有坏事。
questions. I was asking those questions
问题。我当时问的就是这些问题
at at one point in my life, too. But it
我人生中的某个阶段也是如此。但是它
gets to the point of like you have an
到了那种地步，就好像你有一个
obligation to understand how money works
有义务了解金钱运作方式
and what it's going to do to you and how
以及它会对你造成什么影响，以及如何
to manage it. It's not a nice to have.
管理它。这不是一件锦上添花的事。
Everyone's going to have to deal with
每个人都将不得不面对这个问题
these topics whether they like it or
无论他们喜欢与否，这些话题
not. I love this quote from your book
不是。我很喜欢你书中的这句话。
where you say, "One of the most powerful
你说，“最强大的之一”
ways to increase your savings isn't to
增加储蓄的方法并非只有
raise your income. It's to raise your
提高收入。这是为了提高你的
humility." Yeah. I think you get there
谦逊。” 是的，我想你会达到那种境界。
when you realize like nobody's looking
当你意识到好像没人看着你的时候
at you as much as you are and nobody
你和其他人一样，都对你抱有极大的热情。
cares about your Range Rover and your
关心您的路虎揽胜和您的
Rolex as much as you did. They may have
就像你一样，戴劳力士也一样。他们可能拥有
meant a lot to you, but no one else was
对你来说意义重大，但其他人却并非如此。
thinking about them that much because
之所以如此频繁地想起他们，是因为
they were busy thinking about
他们正忙着思考……
themselves. They were busy thinking
他们自己。他们正忙着思考
about their own car. And you realize how
关于他们自己的车。然后你意识到
much modern spending, and this has
现代消费很大程度上也是如此，而且这已经……
increased in the social media age the
社交媒体时代增长了
last 10 or 15 years, is trying to get
过去10到15年里，一直在努力获得
strangers attention. It's trying to put
引起陌生人的注意。它试图放置
on a show, put on a performance for
在节目中，表演
people that you think are paying
你认为那些付钱的人
attention to you, but they're absolutely
他们会关注你，但他们绝对不会。
not. They're not paying any attention to
不是。他们根本没注意到
you whatsoever. And so, like lowering
你不管怎样。因此，就像降低
your or like raising your humility is is
你的谦逊，或者说提升你的谦逊，是
one way to think about it. But it's also
一种思考方式。但它也是
just realizing like who do you want
突然意识到，你想要谁
attention from? It's different for
关注来自哪里？情况有所不同。
everybody. For me, I want my wife, my
所有人。对我来说，我想要我的妻子，我的
kids, my parents, and like three friends
孩子们、我的父母，还有三个朋友
to love me. And I I desperately care
爱我。我非常在乎
about their attention. I desperately
关于他们的关注。我迫切地
care what my kids and my wife and my
关心我的孩子、我的妻子和我
parents think of me and it's it's
父母会想到我，而且……
fundamental to my happiness. And from
对我幸福至关重要。以及
there it declines real quick. You know,
那里的气温下降得很快。你知道，
there's a couple really close friends
有几个非常要好的朋友
who are in there and then there's some
里面的人，还有一些
like colleagues and whatnot and it
比如同事之类的，还有它
declines very quickly from there. And
从那以后，情况迅速恶化。和
strangers, the person driving down the
陌生人，开车的人
street could not care in the slightest.
街上的人丝毫不会在意。
And maybe that sounds obvious, but so
也许这听起来显而易见，但事实就是如此。
much of what we do with money is a
我们用钱做的很多事情都是
performance to impress that guy who's
为了给那个人留下深刻印象而表演
not paying any attention to you
没理你
whatsoever. And so I want to put a lot
任何。所以我想投入很多。
of effort into fostering the
努力促进
relationships with those six or seven
与那六七个人的关系
people. I want to put tremendous effort
人们。我想付出巨大的努力
into that and very little every from
进入那个，而且几乎每个都来自
there. And here's the thing, if I got a
那里。问题是，如果我得到一个
Ferrari, would my wife love me more?
法拉利，我老婆会更爱我吗？
Like no. Would my kids admire me more?
绝对不行。我的孩子会更崇拜我吗？
No. Mh. And so the people who I want to
不。嗯。所以，我想邀请的人
love me are not impacted by the fancy
爱我的人不会受到花哨装饰的影响。
things that I would buy. So what do you
我会买的东西。所以你呢？
spend your money on? We live a a pretty
你把钱花在什么地方了？我们住在一个相当不错的地方。
decent material life, but I also spend a
过着体面的物质生活，但我也花费了……
lot of money. So the biggest expense
很多钱。所以最大的开支
that I have, what I spend my money on is
我拥有的，以及我把钱花在的地方是
independence. And I view that as a thing
独立。而我则认为那是一件事情。
I'm spending money on. I spend money on
我正在花钱。我把钱花在
controlling my calendar. I spend money
掌控我的日程安排。我花钱
on the ability to say no to work that I
关于我拒绝工作的能力
don't want to do. I view it as I'm
不想做。我认为我是
financially independent and so I can do
经济独立，所以我可以这样做
the work that I want to do. And I've
我想做的工作。而且我已经
been working on that for 25 years. What
我为此努力了25年。什么
what what else do I spend money on?
除了这些，我还会把钱花在什么地方？
Here's what's interesting. My son back
有趣的是，我儿子回来了
in the green room, you asked about him.
在休息室里，你问起了他。
There's a thing I I was thinking about
我一直在想一件事
just a couple weeks ago. I grew up as a
就在几周前。我从小就……
skier. I was a ski racer in Lake Tahoe.
滑雪者。我曾是太浩湖的一名滑雪运动员。
And always, particularly when I was
而且总是，尤其是我
younger, there were always people on my
年轻的时候，总有人在我身边。
ski team who had better gear than me.
他们的滑雪队装备比我好。
They had the newer skis and newer boots
他们有新款的滑雪板和滑雪靴。
and cooler gear and whatnot. I always I
还有更酷炫的装备等等。我总是
hated it. Made me so insecure. I hated
讨厌它。这让我非常没有安全感。我讨厌
it. And one of the things that I did was
它。我做的其中一件事是
when my son started skiing a couple
当我儿子开始滑雪的时候
years ago, I was like, I'm going to buy
几年前，我就想，我要买
you the best stuff because I was
你得到了最好的东西，因为我
insecure and I'm going to I'm I'm going
缺乏安全感，我要……我要……
to make up for that little chip on my
为了弥补我身上那小小的缺口
shoulder. I'm going to buy you the best
肩膀。我要给你买最好的。
gear. And here's the thing, he couldn't
齿轮。问题是，他做不到。
care less about it. He could not care
别太在意。他毫不在乎
less about the fancy stuff that he has.
不太在意他拥有的那些花哨的东西。
Couldn't care less about it. So,
我一点也不关心。所以，
everyone's different in that. And it
每个人的情况都不一样。而且它
also gets back to like a lot of spending
也跟大量的消费有关。
is based off of a a story or a scar that
是根据一个故事或一道疤痕改编的
you had from earlier in your childhood.
你小时候就有了。
And where is your your capital
你的资金在哪里？
allocation today? We spoke about this a
今天分配？我们谈到了这件事。
little bit last time, but in terms of
上次稍微有点，但就……而言
percentages, you have a ton of cash. You
按百分比算，你有很多现金。你
said roughly what percentage of your uh
大概说了你呃的百分比
uh 20 25% maybe. We own a house outright
呃，大概20%到25%吧。我们拥有一套完全属于自己的房子。
and then the rest in stocks. It's a very
其余部分则以股票形式持有。这是一个非常
simple our entire net worth is a house,
我们全部的净资产就是一栋房子。
cash, Vanguard index funds, and shares
现金、先锋指数基金和股票
of Markeel where I'm on the board of
我在Markeel董事会任职。
directors. That's it. That's my entire
导演。就是这样。这就是我的全部
net worth. It's as simple and boring as
净值。它既简单又无聊
bland as you could possibly get. And
乏味至极。和
what I want to do with that, the reason
我想用它做什么，原因
I keep it so boring is the variable that
我让它变得如此无聊，这就是变量。
I want to maximize for is endurance, as
我希望最大限度地提高耐力，因为
we spoke about earlier. So if my
我们之前谈到过。所以如果我
finances are so simple, then I can spend
财务如此简单，我就可以花钱了。
all of my like mental energy, all of the
我所有的精力，所有的
strategy is, how can I make sure that I
策略是，我如何确保我
can just keep this going for as long as
可以一直这样下去，只要
I possibly can? So for someone that
我有可能吗？所以对于某个人来说
doesn't know what a Vanguard index fund
不知道什么是先锋指数基金
is, if you had to explain it to your
也就是说，如果你必须向你的……解释它
son, he probably knows, doesn't he? But
儿子，他可能知道，对吧？但
to someone of your son's age, how would
对于像你儿子这个年龄的人来说，会是什么样的呢？
you explain a Vanguard index fund?
你能解释一下先锋集团的指数基金吗？
Because you said you got cash. People
因为你说你有现金。人们
understand that people understand a
明白人们理解
house. Vanguard index fund. So an index
房子。先锋指数基金。所以，索引
fund is a collection of hundreds if not
基金是由数百个（如果不是）组成。
thousands of businesses. So when you buy
数千家企业。所以当你购买时
an index fund, you're owning a little
如果你持有的是指数基金，那么你拥有的份额就很少。
bit of Apple, Amazon, Google, Facebook,
苹果、亚马逊、谷歌、脸书的一些元素
all of them, every public company that's
所有这些公司，每一家上市公司
available, you're owning a tiny slice of
只要有现货，你就拥有了一小部分。
them. One way to think about it is when
他们。一种思考方式是当
you buy an index fund, you're owning a
你购买指数基金，就相当于拥有了一只指数基金。
little slice of American capitalism. And
美国资本主义的一小部分。和
which index funds do you invest in and
你投资了哪些指数基金？
why? There's lots of them. Lots of I
为什么？有很多。很多我
mean, there's tons of them that are are
意思是，有很多这样的人
equally good. So there this is not to
同样好。所以，这不是……
say that there one is better necessarily
说其中一种必然更好。
better than the other. You must have a
比其他的要好。你必须拥有一个
thesis. Most of what I buy is called the
论文。我买的大部分东西都叫做
Vanguard Total Stock Market Index ticker
Vanguard Total Stock Market Index 股票代码
is VTI. Not a recommendation for others,
是VTI。不建议他人尝试。
but it's it's a it's the broadest index.
但它是覆盖面最广的指数。
It basically owns every stock that's
它基本上拥有所有股票。
available to buy in the world and it
全世界均可购买，而且
does it at a very very low fee. And so
收费非常非常低。所以
I'm not making any bet on AI. I'm not
我不会对人工智能做任何投资。我不是
making any bet on this industry or that
对这个行业或那个行业进行任何投注
company. You're owning a little bit of
公司。你拥有一点点
slice of American business. And what
美国商业的缩影。还有什么
what has that yielded as on average over
平均而言，这产生了什么结果？
the last couple of years? If you look at
过去几年？如果你看一下
like like a good historical uh
就像一部优秀的历史作品
comparison to what it would be, which is
与它原本的样子相比，那就是
like the the S&amp;P 500, if you go back,
就像标普500指数一样，如果你回顾一下，
you can go back a hundred years, there's
你可以追溯到一百年前，那里……
a guy from Yale University named Robert
一个来自耶鲁大学名叫罗伯特的人
Schiller who has data going back to the
席勒拥有可以追溯到……的数据
1880s on US stocks. And basically what
1880年代的美国股市。基本上是什么
it shows is over time on average, which
它显示的是随着时间的推移而平均下来的情况，这
that that phrase is doing some heavy
这句话意义重大。
lifting here, but on average 8 to 10%
这里提升幅度较大，但平均为 8% 到 10%。
per year. And why that is like there's a
每年。而为什么会这样，就好像……
big asterisk there is you almost never
这里有个大星号，你几乎从不
earn eight or 10% in any given year.
每年赚取 8% 或 10%。
You're much more likely to be up 30% or
你更有可能获得 30% 的收益。
down 15%. And it averages out to eight
下降15%。平均下来是八
or 10% per year. But it's always chaos
或每年 10%。但那里总是一片混乱。
in in any individual year. And is there
在任何一年中。是否存在？
a reason why you don't just bet on
你不能只是下注的原因
technology for example? Well there's a
例如科技？嗯，这里有一个
lot of technology in that index fund.
该指数基金包含很多技术成分。
That's the highest weight because those
这是最高的权重，因为那些
are the those are the biggest companies
这些是最大的公司吗？
in America. Amazon, Google and whatnot.
在美国。亚马逊、谷歌等等。
But there's also tremendous amount of
但也有大量的
value that can be created by a company
公司能够创造的价值
like Proctor and Gamble selling
就像宝洁公司销售一样
toothpaste and deodorant. And there can
牙膏和除臭剂。而且可以
actually be more value in those kind of
实际上，这类产品更有价值。
companies than technology. Because I
比科技公司更胜一筹。因为我
would bet good money that in 30 years
我敢打赌，30年后
people will still be using Old Spice
人们仍然会使用老香料
deodorant. I would not bet good money
除臭剂。我不会拿真金白银去赌。
that in 30 years Google is going to be
30年后谷歌将会是
the dominant way that people find
人们找到的主要方式
information. And so companies that sell
信息。因此，销售的公司
the same product for a long period of
同一产品长期使用
time, have endurance and longevity, like
时间，拥有耐力和长寿，就像
can actually create a ton of value for
实际上可以创造巨大的价值
their investors. You mentioned the other
他们的投资者。你提到了其他方面。
thing is houses. Um, you have a house.
问题在于房子。嗯，你有一套房子。
Yep. House sales in 2024 total just 4
是的。 2024年房屋销售总量仅为4套
million. The lowest rate since 1995.
百万。 1995年以来的最低利率。
Yeah. I mean, it's it's it's one of the
是的。我的意思是，它是其中之一
biggest social problems. And it is it's
最大的社会问题。的确如此。
so much bigger than housing and so much
比住房大得多，而且如此之多
bigger than money. I think you can tie
比金钱更重要的事。我认为你们可以打成平手。
everything from homelessness to heroin
从无家可归到海洛因
to suicide to the fact that we in
从自杀到我们身处其中的事实
America and a lot of areas around the
美国及其周边许多地区
world have not built enough homes in the
世界各国建造的房屋数量不足。
last 50 years that has pushed the price
过去50年推高了价格
higher and higher and higher and it's
越来越高，越来越高，越来越高，它就是
pushed out what was a small sliver and
挤出了一小片东西，
now a growing large chunk of society who
现在，社会中越来越多的人
rightly feels like they cannot afford a
他们确实觉得自己负担不起
basic middle-ass home. And it's a hu
普通的中档住宅。而且它很……
it's probably the biggest one of the
它可能是最大的一个
biggest societal problems that we face
我们面临的最大社会问题
right now is a housing shortage that has
目前存在住房短缺问题。
pushed housing out of affordability for
住房价格上涨，导致住房负担不起
tens of millions of people. Do you
数千万人。你
recommend people try and buy houses or
建议人们尝试购买房屋或
is it just to rent those houses?
只是为了租这些房子吗？
Here's what So I've purchased three
事情是这样的，我已经买了三个。
homes in my life. Yeah. Every one of
我生命中的家。是的。每一个
those three homes I don't feel like I
那三套房子我都感觉不像我
got a good deal. It wasn't like oh this
买到了便宜货。事情并不是这样的，哦，就是这样。
is a bargain. Got to this is a great
非常划算。能做到这一点真是太棒了
deal. This is none none of the three
交易。这三者都不是。
were like that. I bought them. I could
就是这样。我买了它们。我可以
afford them. They were in my in my I was
他们买得起。它们在我体内，我当时
not going, you know, doing something
不去，你知道，做点什么
that I should not have been doing
我不应该那样做
financially. But the reason I bought
经济方面。但我购买的原因
them is because they were a good
之所以选择他们，是因为他们很优秀。
safe home for my my family in a
为我的家人提供一个安全的家
community that we wanted to live in. And
我们想居住的社区。
I was not thinking about is this going
我当时并没有考虑这件事会如何发展。
to have be a house that I can make a
拥有一栋我可以建造的房子
make a fortune on? Is this going to go
靠什么发大财？这要进行吗？
up in value? Is this going to go down in
价值上涨？这件事会就此结束吗？
value? That was never part of the
价值？那从来都不是……的一部分
equation. it was, yes, I can afford this
方程。是的，我负担得起。
and it's not imperiling my finances at
而且它并没有危及我的财务状况。
all, but the reason I'm doing it is
所有这些都是原因，但我这么做的原因是
because it's a a safe, good place for my
因为对我来说，那是一个安全、好的地方。
family to live. And I think generally
一家人要一起生活。而且我认为总体而言
that's the way to do it. And once people
就该这么做。一旦人们
start thinking through the lens of is
开始从“是”的角度思考。
this a good investment? Is this going to
这是一笔好的投资吗？这会是吗？
go up? Are home prices going to fall?
上？房价会下跌吗？
Maybe I should wait six months because
或许我应该再等六个月，因为
they're going to fall. That's when
它们要倒下了。那时
you're just you're shooting yourself.
你这是在自取灭亡。
You're you're just rolling the dice at
你这纯粹是在掷骰子。
that point. And it's a and people get
这一点。而且人们会得到
into a lot of trouble doing that when
这样做会给自己惹来很多麻烦
they're like, "Oh, I know like I'm going
他们会说：“哦，我知道，就像我要去……”
into a ton of debt, but I think home
背负巨额债务，但我认为家
prices are going to double in the next
价格将在下一个季度翻一番。
three years, so it's okay." That's like
三年了，所以没关系。”这就像
that should not be ever be part of the
那绝不应该成为……的一部分
equation. It should be I can afford this
方程。我应该能负担得起。
and this is where I want to raise my
这就是我想抚养我孩子的地方
family for the next five or 10 years. I
未来五到十年，这个家庭都将如此。我
think that's that's the formula. So,
我想这就是公式。所以，
it's more about freedom and security
这更多的是关于自由和安全。
than making a quick return. Absolutely.
而不是快速回笼。绝对地。
Here's here's what's interesting, like
这里有趣的是，比如
the psychology of housing, too. Um, we
住房心理学也发挥着作用。嗯，我们
we bought a new house eight months ago
八个月前我们买了一套新房子。
and sold our previous house. And that
我们卖掉了之前的房子。而那
house, the house that we just sold, we
房子，我们刚卖掉的那栋房子，我们
we did end up making a little bit of
我们最终还是做了一点……
money on because Seattle real estate has
因为西雅图房地产市场有资金投入。
gone crazy in the last five years. And
过去五年里他变得疯了。和
really interesting something that
真是一件很有趣的事
happened. This is just eight months ago
发生了。这距离现在才八个月。
when we sold the house. The day that we
当我们卖掉房子的时候。我们的那一天
closed on selling that house and I got
房子卖出去了，我拿到了
the proceeds wired to me in my bank
款项已汇入我的银行账户
account, logged in my bank account. I
账户，已登录我的银行账户。我
see that number from selling the house.
看看卖房子赚的钱就知道了。
The numbers meant nothing to me. But the
这些数字对我来说毫无意义。但是
house that we sold meant everything to
我们卖掉的那栋房子对我们来说意义非凡。
me. It was like my daughter took her
我。就像我女儿带走了她
first steps at the bottom of those
迈出第一步，从最底层开始
stairs. My son had his first day of
楼梯。我儿子第一天上学
kindergarten, Christmases,
幼儿园，圣诞节，
Thanksgivings. Like, and it was like
感恩节。就像，感觉就像
these numbers don't mean anything to me.
这些数字对我来说没有任何意义。
These numbers are just going into the
这些数字即将进入……
new house. But that house that I left
新房子。但我离开的那栋房子
behind meant everything to me. So that
对我来说，背后意味着一切。以便
gets back to like don't think of it as a
回到正题，别把它想成……
as a financial transaction. It should be
作为一项金融交易。应该是
this is where you want to raise your
这就是你想提升自己的地方
family and build some memories. How does
和家人一起创造美好回忆。如何
it compare to investing in that Vanguard
与投资先锋集团相比，这简直太划算了。
thing? If we look at the returns on
事物？如果我们看一下收益率
housing, I have no memories of my
住房方面，我没有任何记忆。
daughter's first steps in my Vanguard
女儿在我的先锋号上迈出的第一步
index funds. You know, that that that
指数基金。你知道，就是那个
that's really it. It's you you are
就是这样。就是你。
investing in a Vanguard index fund
投资先锋指数基金
because you think you're going to make
因为你认为你会成功
money over time, whereas you should not
随着时间的推移，你会赚到钱，而你不应该这样做。
have that mentality when you buy a
购买商品时要抱有这种心态
house. It should be within your
房子。它应该在你的范围内
financial means, but you should be doing
经济能力有限，但你应该这样做
it because it's a good place to raise
因为它是个适合养育孩子的好地方。
your family for a long period of time.
你的家人会长期陪伴你。
It does beg a question for for younger
这确实引出了一个关于年轻人的问题。
people who are thinking about building
正在考虑建造的人
their wealth because the first thing and
他们的财富是因为第一件事和
the most common thing we're taught as it
我们最常被教导的就是……
relates to wealth creation is to go buy
与财富创造相关的就是去购买
a house. Like it's the thing that
一栋房子。就像是……
everybody knows. You leave university,
人尽皆知。你离开大学，
you get a job and you save as as much
你找到工作，尽可能多地存钱。
money as you can to put that deposit
尽可能多地拿出钱来存入这笔定金
down. Yeah, that was true in previous
向下。是的，以前确实如此。
generations because if you go back to
因为如果你追溯到几代人以前
the
这
1950s,60s7s, we were building so many
20世纪50年代、60年代、70年代，我们建造了很多东西。
more homes than we are today that they
比我们今天拥有的房屋数量更多。
were much cheaper. even when interest
价格便宜得多。即使利息
rates were higher, they were much
利率更高，而且高得多。
cheaper. And so the advice of, hey, you
更便宜。所以，有人建议说，嘿，你
got an entry-level job, you should go
找到一份入门级工作，你应该去
buy an entry-level house probably made
买一套入门级住宅可能
sense in the 60s and 70s in a way that
以某种方式来说，这在六七十年代是一种意义。
it doesn't today. The other element here
现在并非如此。这里的另一个因素
that is very easy to overlook in the
这一点很容易被忽略。
housing problem, the housing debate is
住房问题，住房辩论是
that the homes that we found adequate in
我们发现的这些房屋都足够好。
the 50s and 60s, we would not find
在五六十年代，我们找不到
adequate today. So Levittown in New York
如今已足够。所以，纽约的莱维敦
was is like the prototypical example.
就像一个典型的例子。
That's when like end of World War II,
那时大约是第二次世界大战结束的时候，
build big like like build the middle
建造大型建筑，就像建造中间层一样
class community, build this huge new
班级社区，建设这个巨大的新
community called Levittown in New York.
纽约州莱维敦社区。
And that was like the the typical white
那就像典型的白人
picket fence middle-ass home that we
我们那带木栅栏的中等大小的房子
like long for today. And they were
就像今天这样漫长。他们是
cheap. They were affordable. The average
便宜的。它们价格实惠。平均
new house in Levittown, was 700 square
位于莱维敦的新房子，面积700平方英尺
feet. It had two two bedrooms for an
脚。它有两个卧室。
average of a family of five or six
平均而言，一个五六口之家
moving into it. One bathroom for those
搬进去。只有一个浴室供这些人使用
six people, no air conditioning, no
六个人，没有空调，没有
garage. It would be a house that if I
车库。那将是一栋如果我……的房子
showed you today, you would be like it's
今天给你看了，你会觉得……
a junk. It's a to to to it's a crack
垃圾。这是一个裂缝
house. Like nobody like would say that
房子。好像没人会这么说似的。
is a beautiful middle-ass house. So
这是一栋漂亮的中等房子。所以
expectations over time have increased
随着时间的推移，人们的期望值不断提高。
tremendously. So now the average new
非常大。所以现在平均新
middle class house is 2200 square feet
中产阶级住宅面积为2200平方英尺
where it used to be 700. So like what an
以前是700。所以，这算什么？
entry-level house is, the definition of
入门级住宅的定义是：
that has expanded tremendously over
已经大幅扩展了
time. And if your children come to you
时间。如果你的孩子来找你
and they say, "Dad, I'm 25 years old and
他们说：“爸爸，我25岁了，
I've just got some excess cash here.
我这儿正好有点多余的现金。
I've got $20,000, $40,000. I'm thinking
我有2万美元，4万美元。我在想
of putting a deposit down for a house."
支付房屋定金。
My wife and I rented for years. And
我和妻子租房住了很多年。和
looking back at the time and looking
回首往事，展望未来
back, it was the best thing that we ever
回想起来，那是我们做过的最棒的事。
did. We rented for, I don't know, 10
做过。我们租了，我不知道，大概10年吧。
years before we bought a house because
几年前，我们买房时就因为……
we lived in five different cities and we
我们曾在五个不同的城市居住过，而且我们
could just easily just pack up and go.
完全可以收拾东西走人。
And they would, we weren't tied to
他们会的，我们并没有被束缚。
anything. We had flexibility. And it was
任何事物。我们拥有灵活性。确实如此。
pretty much the week that our son was
差不多就在我们儿子出生的那一周
born, when we had our first kid, that it
出生时，我们有了第一个孩子，那时它……
was like a switch in my head. I was
就像我脑子里突然切换了一个开关。我当时
like, I I I need to go have my own house
比如，我需要拥有自己的房子
because the flexibility that I enjoyed
因为我享受这种灵活性。
when we were childless, it was the
当我们没有孩子的时候，就是
opposite. I was like, I I value
对面的。我当时就想，我重视
stability now. I want a stable house for
现在稳定了。我想要一个稳定的家
for my family. And it was like instantly
为了我的家人。就像瞬间发生的那样
that switched. And so that was not a
转变了。所以那并不是一个
financial decision of like I need to go
我需要做出财务决定
out and buy because I have some extra
出去买吧，因为我手头还有一些闲钱。
savings. It was like, I want I want my
节省。感觉就像，我想要，我想要我的
house that is mine and it's not there's
那是我家，但它不在那里。
not going to be a landlord that sends me
我不会成为那种把我赶出去的房东。
a letter and says, "Oh, sorry, you're
一封信上写着：“哦，对不起，你是……”
you're evicted." Or, "Sorry, we're we're
你被驱逐了。”或者，“抱歉，我们……”
we're selling the building. You need to
我们要卖掉这栋楼。你需要
leave. This is my house." That's that
离开。这是我的房子。”就这样。
that that was the shift for me. It feels
对我来说，那就是一个转折点。感觉
like when we rent, we're wasting money,
比如我们租房，就是在浪费钱。
though. But it's not in the slightest. I
尽管。但事实并非如此。我
mean, for anyone who's owned a house,
也就是说，对于任何拥有过房子的人来说，
you know, the expenses that go into a
你知道，投入到……中的费用
house, it's not just the mortgage. It's
房子，不仅仅是房贷。它是
the It's the broken water heater. It's
是热水器坏了。它是
replacing your roof. It's the the
更换屋顶。这是
expenses that go into it. Like you want
相关的费用。就像你想要的那样
to talk about throwing your money away,
谈论浪费钱，
try replacing your roof on a house that
尝试更换你家的屋顶
you own. That feels like throwing money
你拥有。感觉就像在扔钱。
away.
离开。
And it's hard for the brain to conceive.
而且，这对于大脑来说很难构思。
You know, that renting might be the same
你知道，租房可能也是一样的。
as buying a house when you when you net
就像买房一样，当你净收入时
out and you factor in opportunity cost
算出来，还要考虑机会成本。
and flexibility, the ability to get on a
以及灵活性，能够上车
plane and go to London to to do that job
乘飞机去伦敦做那份工作
and you can't quantify that flexibility.
这种灵活性是无法量化的。
So my wife and I lived in five different
所以，我和妻子一共住过五个不同的地方。
cities. Some of those were because we
城市。其中一些原因是因为我们
got jobs that that we didn't you know in
我们找到了一些我们以前不知道的工作。
different cities we had to move. You
我们不得不搬到不同的城市。你
can't quantify that flexibility or it's
无法量化这种灵活性，或者说，它是
very hard to but in the moment it was
很难做到，但当时确实做到了。
everything. It was I remember when my
一切。我记得当时我的
wife got into grad school and it was
妻子考上了研究生院，然后……
like great pack up this city and move to
就像收拾行囊搬到这座城市一样。
this city and there just like no
这座城市，还有那里，简直就像没有
handcuffs just get up and go versus if
戴上手铐就起身走，而不是……
you own your house like anyone's tried
你拥有自己的房子，就像任何人尝试过的那样。
to sell a house like it's a nightmare
把卖房子这件事搞得像噩梦一样
and so you can't quantify that but it
所以你无法量化它，但它
meant everything in the world to us now.
现在它对我们来说意义非凡。
My brother said this to me he's a very
我哥哥跟我说过，他是一个非常……
smart guy now. Now now I reflect upon
现在他可真是个聪明人了。现在我回想起
it. He said this to me when I was
它。他当时对我说这番话。
younger cuz I think at 25 when I got
比较年轻，因为我觉得我25岁的时候就……
some money. I was telling him maybe I'll
一些钱。我告诉他，也许我会
buy this house. We should look at this
买下这栋房子。我们应该看看这个
house. And he explained to me in simple
房子。他用简单的语言向我解释道
terms that the flexibility that I had to
我所拥有的灵活性体现在以下条款中：
get up and move was actually worth so
起身活动实际上是值得的。
much more than maybe some of the equity
远不止某些股权那么简单。
that I might acrue from buying a house.
我可能从买房中获得的收益。
And now I look back on it from that day
现在回想那天，我感到无比惋惜。
onwards. I then moved to New York and I
继续。然后我搬到了纽约，我
lived there for 3 days. Then I the
在那里住了3天。然后我
pandemic happened and I suddenly quit my
疫情爆发后，我突然辞职了。
job out of the blue unexpectedly and I
这份工作来得猝不及防，我
moved to Portugal then went to Germany
先搬到葡萄牙，然后去了德国
then went to Bali for several months
然后去了巴厘岛待了几个月。
then flew back to the UK London now I've
然后飞回英国伦敦，现在我已经
just moved to LA. Yeah. And that's all
刚搬到洛杉矶。是的。就这些了。
in the space of four years. Incredible.
短短四年时间。极好的。
And I've gone with the opportunity. So
我抓住了这个机会。所以
when the opportunity comes knocking and
当机会来敲门时
oh the podcast starts doing well and
哦，播客开始做得不错了，
then this happens and then Dragon's done
然后就发生了这件事，然后龙就完蛋了。
this. I've just moved with the
这。我刚搬过来
opportunity. And if id bought a house
机会。如果我买了一套房子
you'd be locked down. There are so many
你将被封锁。太多了。
people today who bought homes in 2021,
今天在2021年购买房屋的人，
2022, and their mortgage rate was two or
2022年，他们的抵押贷款利率是两倍或
three percent. They have a two or three
百分之三。他们有两三个
percent mortgage. And a lot of those
抵押贷款百分比。而且很多都是这样
people want to move today because they
人们今天想搬家是因为他们
can get a better job in another city.
在其他城市可以找到更好的工作。
They want to move and they feel like
他们想搬家，他们感觉
they can't because because they're they
他们不能，因为他们是他们
have golden handcuffs for the super
给超级英雄准备金手铐
cheap mortgage because if they sold
抵押贷款便宜，因为如果他们卖掉
their house and bought a new one, their
他们搬走了原来的房子，买了一套新房子，他们的
new mortgage rate would be 7 and a
新的抵押贷款利率将为7%和a
half%. And so those are people who like
一半％。所以，这些人喜欢
a lot of those people look back and when
很多人回顾往事时
they bought in 2021, they're like, "We
他们在2021年买的，他们会说：“我们
won the lottery, 2% mortgage. This is
中了彩票，抵押贷款利率2%。这是
amazing." And looking back, they're
太棒了。” 回首往事，他们……
like, "Gosh, we would have been so
比如，“天哪，我们本来会……”
better off renting if we did, if we had
如果我们有条件的话，还不如租房。
the flexibility to move." So
行动的灵活性。”
interesting. So much of economic
有趣的。很多经济
prosperity over history is your ability
超越历史的繁荣是你的能力
to move. And that that's been true for
移动。事实的确如此。
hundreds of years. Like if you want to
数百年。如果你想的话，就点赞吧
see like a a basic measure of how
看起来像是对某种基本方法的衡量
wealthy any economy is, like how often
任何经济体的富裕程度，就像它的频率一样。
do people move? Because moving is
人们会搬家吗？因为搬家是
usually a symbol of opportunity. And the
通常象征着机遇。以及
more that they're locked down and feel
更多的是因为他们被困住了，感觉
like they can't move, the more stagnant
就像他们动弹不得一样，越是停滞不前
and like sclerotic that economy is going
就像硬化症一样，这种经济正在走向
to be. What's this idea that you have of
存在。你对这个有什么想法？
asking $3 questions? I heard you talking
问一些价值 3 美元的问题？我听到你在说话
about that. I stole that from an author
关于那件事。我从一位作家那里偷来的。
named named Rammit Si. Oh, a very
名为 Rammit Si。哦，非常
well-known author. And he says, "Too
知名作家。他说：“太……”
many people ask $3 questions when they
很多人在提问时都会问一些价值3美元的问题。
should be asking $30,000 questions."
应该问一些价值三万美元的问题。
What he means by that are when people
他的意思是，当人们
say, "How can I save more money?" They
问：“我怎样才能省更多钱？”他们
say, "I should stop drinking coffee."
我说：“我应该停止喝咖啡。”
That's a $3 question. And that does not
这是一个价值3美元的问题。但这并非如此。
make any difference to you. What you
对你来说有什么影响吗？你
should be asking are $30,000 questions
应该问的是价值 3 万美元的问题
like where should I go to college?
我应该去哪所大学？
Should I go to the cheap school or the
我应该去那所便宜的学校还是
expensive school? Where should I live?
昂贵的学校？我应该住在哪里？
The cheap city or the expensive city?
是选择物价低廉的城市还是物价昂贵的城市？
Should I rent or should I buy? Those are
我应该租房还是买房？那些是
$30,000 questions. And we spend a lot of
价值 3 万美元的问题。我们花费了大量时间
mental energy on $3 questions that
耗费脑力回答价值 3 美元的问题
actually that don't move the needle that
实际上，那并不会改变什么。
much in our in our finances. For most
在我们的财务方面有很多。对于大多数
people, they're only a couple of expense
这些人，他们只是几个费用而已。
items that actually matter to your
对你来说真正重要的物品
finances. that is your housing payment,
财政。那是你的住房付款。
either rent or mortgage, your car
无论是租房还是还贷，你的车
payment, child care, uh healthcare, and
支付、儿童保育、医疗保健，以及
that that's pretty much it. And and yes,
差不多就是这样了。是的，
you're going to spend money on on other
你打算把钱花在其他方面。
things, but those four, that's the vast
事情很多，但那四件事，就占了很大一部分。
majority of what people spend money on.
人们花钱的大部分都花在了这些地方。
But when you hear people talk about how
但当你听到人们谈论如何
do you save money? It's like, oh, well,
你存钱吗？感觉就像，哦，好吧，
stop stop going to Starbucks. You can
别再去星巴克了。你可以
like pack your own lunch to work. It
比如自己带午餐上班。它
doesn't make that much of a difference.
差别不大。
It's those big four things. So am I
就是这四件大事。我也是
right in thinking that you think we
你认为我们的想法是对的
should
应该
avoid either extreme end of the
避免走向任何极端
financial like approach that people
人们采取的类似金融方法
take? So you got yolo on one end and
拿？所以，一方面你可以尽情享受人生，另一方面……
you've
你已经
got caring about every coffee on the
开始在意每一杯咖啡
other end spectrum. I think those are
另一端光谱。我认为那些是
what are you are most likely to end up
你最有可能最终会变成什么样？
regretting. What do you mean? There are
后悔了。你是什​​么意思？有
a lot of people in the fire movement.
消防运动中有很多人。
Fire stands for financial independence
火代表财务独立
retire early. It's this big movement
提前退休。这是一场声势浩大的运动
started 10 or 15 years ago of people who
始于10到15年前，由一群人组成
are like, I'm going to save as much
就像，我要尽可能多地存钱。
money as I can in my 20s, learn how to
趁着20多岁，尽可能多地赚钱，学习如何……
live as cheaply and frugally as I can
尽可能过上节俭、低消费的生活
and retire at age 27 with, you know, 600
27岁退休，拥有600美元。
grand in the bank and that's I'm going
银行里有一大笔钱，我就到此为止了。
to retire off of that. And it was a huge
靠那笔钱退休。而且这非常巨大
movement. So many of those people ended
移动。这些人中有很多最终都离开了。
up regretting it because they retired at
后来他们后悔了，因为他们退休了。
27 and six months later they're bored
27岁零6个月后，他们感到无聊了。
out of their mind, if not depressed,
他们要么精神失常，要么抑郁。
because they they wake up and they're
因为他们醒来后，他们
like, "What what do I do now? Do I I
比如，“我现在该怎么办？我该怎么做？”
just go for I go play golf or something
你就去吧，我去打高尔夫什么的。
like all all my friends are out working.
我的朋友们都出去工作了。
What do I do now? And so I think the
我现在该怎么办？所以我认为
extreme ends of like oh yolo I'm just
极端情况，比如“哦，人生苦短，及时行乐，我只是……”
going to spend all live for today. I'm
今天我要把所有时间都花在生活中。我是
going to spend it all. I'm going to go
打算把钱全花光。我要走了
party and travel and whatnot. There's
聚会、旅行等等。有
there's a somewhat of a chance that
存在一定的可能性
you're going to end up regretting that
你最终会后悔的。
because you didn't save enough for a
因为你没攒够钱买
time in your life when you want to
人生中你想要……的时刻
retire and you can't. On the subject of
退休了你就不行了。关于……
retirement, me and my friend Jack over
退休后，我和我的朋友杰克……
there, we were talking about people who
当时，我们正在谈论那些人
retire and the impact it can have on the
退休及其对……的影响
individual. And I I think I'd be quite
个人。而且我觉得我会相当
scared to retire because there seems to
害怕退休，因为似乎……
be lots of data that suggests that once
有大量数据表明，一旦
we retire, it's quite it's downhill from
我们退休了，生活就此走下坡路。
there in many respects for many people
在许多方面，对许多人来说都是如此
in terms of purpose and meaning and
就目的和意义而言
connections. How do you think about
联系。你如何看待这个问题？
retirement? Is that something we should
退休？这是我们应该做的吗？
be aiming at? My dad, I think, retired
目标是？我想，我爸爸退休了。
and went back to work three different
然后又回去工作了三次，每次都不同。
times. We eventually had to tell him
次数。我们最终不得不告诉他。
like, "No more retirement parties." Like
比如，“不再举办退休派对。”喜欢
you like you only get one. But he would
你喜欢你只能得到一个。但他会
retire and then and then a month later
退休，然后，一个月后
he'd be like, "Man, I I I really miss
他会说：“唉，我，我真的很想念你们。”
work." And in his line of work, he could
工作。”而且在他的工作领域，他可以
go back. He could go back part-time and
回去。他可以回去兼职工作，
what not. So that it all worked out for
什么都没有。所以一切都朝着好的方向发展了。
him. But I think he starkly saw what a
他。但我认为他清楚地看到了……
lot of people overlook, which is how
很多人都忽略了这一点，这就是原因。
much of his identity was his job and how
他的身份认同很大程度上取决于他的工作以及如何……
much like when he retired the first time
就像他第一次退休时一样。
and he like woke up and looked in the
他就像醒了过来，往里看了看。
mirror and said, "I'm not I'm not the
对着镜子说：“我不是，我不是……”
person who I used to be. I used to be a
曾经的我。我曾经是
a a this and but I'm not anymore." And
“啊，这个，但我现在不是了。”
and it he didn't like it. And I was
他不喜欢这样。而我当时
like, it's easy. Like look, every job
很简单。比如你看，每份工作
has downsides that are stressful and you
它也有一些令人压力大的缺点，而且你
don't want to do them and they're a pain
我不想做这些事，而且它们很麻烦。
and you hate them and you can't wait to
你恨他们，你迫不及待地想……
live a world where you don't have to do
生活在一个你不必做什么的世界里
the stressful parts of your job. But for
工作中压力最大的部分。但是……
a lot of us, like what we really want to
我们很多人，都喜欢我们真正想要的东西
do in our soul is like be productive in
我们灵魂深处的行动就像是在做一件富有成效的事
the world and add value to the world,
为世界创造价值，并为世界增添价值。
add value for our family, add value to
为我们的家庭增添价值，为……增添价值
the world. And one of the the quickest
世界。而且速度最快之一
ways to become depressed is to be very
导致抑郁的方法之一是非常
productive and then immediately stop.
然后立即停止并保持高效。
That's a quick path to depression for a
对一个人来说，那是通往抑郁的捷径。
lot of people. And so some people are
很多人。所以有些人是
very good at retirement. My my my mom on
非常擅长退休。我的妈妈
the other hand was very good at
另一方面，他非常擅长
retirement. She retired, never looked
退休。她退休了，再也没有……
back and had a very has a very full life
回来后，他过着非常充实的生活。
in retirement. She keeps herself very
退休后。她非常注重保护自己。
busy with hobbies and friends and
忙于爱好和朋友聚会
whatnot. So some people are very good at
什么的。所以有些人非常擅长
it. Other people who found their
它。其他发现他们的人
identity in their work, that's a lot of
在他们的作品中体现身份认同，这很重要。
people. That's me. I think that's
人们。这就是我。我认为那是
probably you would would go crazy if if
如果这样的话，你可能会疯掉。
if we ended up retiring. You can't say
如果我们最终退休了。你不能说
your own book, but if you had to
你自己的书，但如果你必须……
recommend a book that would equipped us
推荐一本能让我们掌握相关知识的书
to understand money, wealth creation,
了解金钱、财富创造
and all these kinds of things, what book
以及所有这些事情，什么书
would you recommend? Oh, I would say my
你会推荐吗？哦，我会说我的
own book. No. Um, no, I think a couple
自己的书。不。嗯，不，我想是几个
that were really important for me, you
那些对我来说非常重要的东西，你
know, it's not bedtime reading, but a
要知道，这不是睡前读物，而是一个
guy named Benjamin Graham wrote a book
一个名叫本杰明·格雷厄姆的人写了一本书
called The Intelligent Investor. He
名为《聪明的投资者》。他
wrote it in the 1930s, so it is written
写于 20 世纪 30 年代，所以才这样写。
in 1930s English. And he was a
20世纪30年代的英语。他是一个
professor, so it's written, it's not
教授，上面是这么写的，但实际上并非如此。
quite a textbook, but it's not bedtime
简直就是一本教科书，但现在还不是睡觉时间。
reading. But there is more wisdom about
阅读。但其中蕴含着更多智慧。
investing in that book than any other
投资那本书比投资其他任何书籍都更值得。
book that's been written in the last
过去一年里写成的一本书
hundred years. And even though he wrote
一百年。即使他写道
it almost 100 years ago, 90% of it is
大约100年前，其中90%是
timeless. You know, he he says certain
永恒的。你知道，他说肯定
things that are obviously dated, but
一些明显过时的东西，但是
there's more wisdom in there than
里面蕴含的智慧比
anything else that's ever been written.
任何其他曾经写过的东西。
That's why the book still sells a lot 90
这就是为什么这本书至今仍然畅销的原因。
years after it's been written. That was
多年之后。那是
that was a big one. Learning about World
那可是件大事。了解世界
War II and the Great Depression was very
二战和大萧条非常
influential to me and many other people
对我以及许多其他人来说，这些人很有影响力。
because both of those events,
因为这两件事，
particularly World War II, saw the
特别是第二次世界大战，见证了
highest range of human emotions that I
我所感受到的人类情感的最高境界
think has ever been documented from the
认为有史以来从未有记录的
most agony and despair and torment to
最深切的痛苦、绝望和折磨
the most like like
最像
elation and happiness that it's over.
终于结束了，我感到无比欣喜和快乐。
like so many the the the fullest range
就像很多东西一样，最全面的范围
of human emotions were documented during
在研究过程中，人类的情感得到了记录。
that period from probably 1929 to 1945.
那段时期大概是从 1929 年到 1945 年。
Mhm. Those 16 years I think if you learn
嗯。我认为，如果你在那16年里学会了什么，你就会明白。
about what happened in the United States
关于美国发生的事情
and all over the world of course you
当然，全世界都是如此。
learn so much about humanity like World
了解了世界等人类的方方面面
War when you study World War II you're
当你研究第二次世界大战时，你就会明白战争的意义。
not really learning about military
并没有真正了解军事方面的事情。
tactics even though that's part of it.
战术固然重要，但这只是其中的一部分。
You're learning about the psychology of
你正在学习心理学
how people deal with uncertainty, dread,
人们如何应对不确定性、恐惧、
risk, doubt, fear. you could learn more
风险、疑虑、恐惧。您可以了解更多
about those topics during that 15- year
在那15年间，我一直关注这些话题。
period than anything else. One of the
比其他任何事情都重要。中的一个
things that I I learned from listening
我从聆听中学到的东西
to your podcast, which is fantastic. I
你的播客太棒了，值得一听。我
highly recommend people go listen to the
强烈推荐大家去听听
Morgan Hustle podcast, was you were
Morgan Hustle播客，你当时在吗？
talking about the dangers of rapid
谈论快速行驶的危险
growth. Yeah. And I
生长。是的。我
actually I I took something that you
实际上，我拿了你的东西
said in the podcast around the danger of
在播客中谈到危险时
rapid growth and I sent it to my CEO and
快速增长，我把它发给了我的首席执行官。
my chief revenue officer because it's a
我的首席营收官，因为这是一个
cautionary tale for a generation of
对一代人来说，这是一个警世故事。
entrepreneurs who are obsessed with
痴迷于……的企业家
growth at all costs to slow things down.
不惜一切代价追求增长，而不是放慢速度。
Yeah. What in your view what is the and
是的。你认为什么是“和”？
this could be the the dangers of rapid
这可能是快速增长的危险所在。
growth in any field. It could be someone
任何领域的增长。可能是某人
running a podcast or someone building a
运营播客或有人在搭建播客
business or or anything someone
商业或任何人
investing money. Why do we need to be
投资理财。我们为什么需要
cautious about rapid growth? There's a a
对快速增长持谨慎态度？有一个
really interesting analogy that I like
这个比喻真有趣，我很喜欢。
with tree growth in nature that if you
自然界中树木的生长，如果你
plant a tree out in the middle of an
在草地中央种一棵树
open field, it because it's out in the
开阔的田野，因为它位于户外
middle of an open field, it's gorging on
在一片开阔的田野中央，它正狼吞虎咽地吃着东西。
sunlight because there's no other trees
因为没有其他树木，所以阳光充足。
shading it. It's just gorging on
给它上阴影。它简直是在暴饮暴食
sunlight. Because it gorges on sunlight,
阳光。因为它吸收了大量的阳光，
it grows very, very fast. It can grow
它生长速度非常非常快。它可以生长
like 10 times faster than a tree that's
比树快十倍
covered in shade. So, you might think
阴凉处。所以你可能会想
like that's great. That's amazing. It's
那太好了。太棒了。它是
growing so quickly. If you're a farmer,
增长速度真快。如果你是一名农民，
you love that. But when a tree grows
你喜欢那样。但是当一棵树长大后
that quickly, it never has a chance to
这么快，它根本没有机会……
grow dense and hard. It never has a
变得致密坚硬。它从来没有
chance to grow a very established root
有机会培育出非常发达的根系
structure. And so those trees, even
结构。所以那些树，甚至
though they grow very quickly, they die
虽然它们生长迅速，但它们会死亡
very quickly. They're very susceptible
很快。他们非常容易受到影响
to rot because they never have a chance
腐烂是因为它们根本没有机会。
to grow hard. It's just kind of like
变得坚硬。感觉就像……
mushy, soft wood inside. And if you see
内部是软绵绵的木头。如果你看到
a lot of the lumber that is harvested
大量采伐的木材
these days and you compare it to lumber
如今，你把它比作木材。
from like old growth forests, you might
例如，从原始森林中，你可能会
as well be looking at a completely
同时还要考虑一个完全
different tree. A lot of the wood that
不同的树。很多木材
we harvest today that was grown very
我们今天收获的作物长势非常好。
quickly is soft and weak compared to the
与……相比，它迅速变得柔软而脆弱。
old dense hardwood that they used to
他们过去常用的那种老旧致密硬木
make. And I think that's a good analogy
制作。我觉得这个比喻很贴切。
that like fast growth is fun. It's
快速增长的感觉很有趣。它是
exciting. But there's always it's like
令人兴奋。但总会有那么一种感觉……
speed always comes at the expense of
速度总是以牺牲……为代价的
durability always. There's a theory in
始终经久耐用。有一种理论是
finance is kind of like a
金融有点像……
tongue-in-cheek theory that however fast
半开玩笑的理论，无论速度多快
you grow that's the halflife for how
你生长，那就是半衰期，如何
quickly you can die. So like the faster
你很快就会死去。所以就像速度更快的那种。
you grow the f the quicker you can die
你越长大，死亡速度就越快
as well. M and you see that in nature.
也一样。 M，你在自然界中也能看到这一点。
You see it with businesses as well. The
在企业中也能看到这种情况。这
hard thing is that if you're an
难就难在你是一个
entrepreneur, if you're the CEO or
企业家，如果你是首席执行官或
working at a company, there is nothing
在公司工作，什么都没有
more thrilling and exciting and and gets
更加惊险刺激，而且越来越精彩
you up in the morning than fast growth.
你早上起床比快速成长更重要。
You love it. You love every second of
你喜欢它。你热爱每一秒
it, even if it's a danger. You just
即使它很危险，也要买它。你只是
reminded me of an idea I wrote about in
这让我想起了我之前写过的一个想法。
my last book about the music industry
我上一本关于音乐产业的书
where they found the same thing. The
他们在那里发现了同样的东西。这
faster a song went to number one in the
一首歌登上排行榜榜首的速度更快。
charts, the quicker it came out.
图表显示，发布速度越快越好。
Absolutely. because people get in bored
绝对地。因为人们会感到无聊
of it basically very very quickly. It's
基本上很快就完成了。它是
everywhere. It's on every radio station
到处。每个广播电台都在播。
everywhere and then it falls out the
到处都是，然后就掉出来了。
chart all the time the same speed and
图表始终保持相同的速度，并且
and the companies that can like produce
以及那些能够生产这类产品的公司
tons and tons of money. Even like look
数不胜数的钱。甚至看起来像
at Apple was created in the 1970s didn't
苹果公司成立于 20 世纪 70 年代，但并非如此。
really find its stride so to speak until
真正找到节奏，可以说，直到
the mid200s and so it's not it's it's
200年代中期，所以不是，是，是
it's like sometimes there like there's
有时候就像……
companies like Facebook I guess that and
我想，像Facebook这样的公司也是如此。
OpenAI that found product market fit
OpenAI 找到了产品市场契合点
found like incredible success virtually
几乎发现取得了令人难以置信的成功
overnight the day that they were
一夜之间，他们……
invented. But one of the problems with
发明。但其中一个问题是
with rapid growth too is that the
快速增长的另一个方面是
difference between building a product
构建产品之间的区别
that's going to grow very quickly. That
它会发展得非常迅速。那
is a very different skill than managing
这是一种与管理截然不同的技能。
a company that now has a thousand
一家现在拥有一千家公司的企业
employees. Those are night and day
雇员。那简直是天壤之别
different skills. And so you might be a
不同的技能。所以你可能是一名
very talented entrepreneur who can build
非常有才华的企业家，能够建立
a product and get thousands of people to
推出一款产品，并吸引成千上万的人
buy it. That does not necessarily mean
买吧。这并不一定意味着
that you have the skills to manage a 50
你具备管理50个项目的技能
person team or a thousand person team.
无论是单人团队还是千人团队。
How does your work all dovetail with the
你的工作是如何与……衔接的？
subject of happiness Morgan? Because at
幸福的主题是摩根吗？因为在
the very heart of it, clearly everyone
问题的核心，显然是每个人
who's clicked on this conversation and
谁点击查看了这段对话？
got this far, although they might be
虽然他们可能已经走到这一步了，但他们
thinking it's money that they're looking
以为他们看中的是钱。
for or wealth that they're looking for,
为了他们所追求的财富，
probably at the end of the day, they
或许到最后，他们
just want to live a happy life. They
只想过上幸福的生活。他们
think money or wealth is a pathway to a
认为金钱或财富是通往……的途径
happy life. With all the work that
幸福生活。所有这些工作
you've done and the people that you've
你所做的一切以及你所接触的人
studied through history and all that
通过历史研究等等
you've
你已经
written, what is your current view on
书面上，你目前对……的看法是什么？
how to live a happy life? Yeah. What's
如何才能拥有幸福的生活？是的。是什么
interesting is that like when you say
有趣的是，就像你说的
hap, when anyone says happy, you're
hap，当有人说happy时，你就是happy。
like, how can you disagree with that?
你怎么能不同意呢？
Everybody wants to be happy.
每个人都想快乐。
A lot of why people run into problems
很多人遇到问题的原因有很多
when they're seeking happiness is
当他们追求幸福的时候
because happiness is not the emotion
因为幸福不是一种情绪
that you want to go for. Happiness is
你想去的地方。幸福是
always a fiveminute emotion. It comes
总是持续五分钟的情绪。它来了
and goes. You experience it, but it's a
然后就走了。你会经历它，但这只是
thrill and then it kind of wears off
一开始很兴奋，但那种感觉很快就消退了。
very quickly. If you hear a funny joke,
很快。如果你听到一个好笑的笑话，
you go to a comedy show, it's funny. You
你去看喜剧表演，觉得很好笑。你
laugh at at a joke for 20 seconds and
笑一个笑话20秒钟
then it's not that funny anymore. What
那样就不好笑了。什么
you want to go for, I think, is
我认为，你想要追求的是
contentment. And a lot of people like
满意。很多人都喜欢
money can buy a good life, but when you
金钱可以买到美好的生活，但当你
imagine yourself with the new house, the
想象一下你住进了新房子，
new car, the nice vacation, when you
新车，美好的假期，当你
dream about those making you happy, what
梦见那些让你快乐的人，什么
you're actually envisioning is yourself
你真正想象的其实是你自己。
being content with those things. You
满足于现状。你
envision yourself on the beach in Maui
想象一下自己身处毛伊岛的海滩上。
being content with it. And that's why it
对此感到满足。这就是它的原因。
feels so good. The feeling that you
感觉真好。你那种感觉
want, the feeling that you're actually
想要，那种感觉，你实际上
chasing, whether you know it or not,
无论你是否意识到，都在追逐。
it's not happiness, it's contentment.
这不是快乐，而是满足。
And I think that little shift too is
我觉得这种小小的转变也是
because most people are out there
因为大多数人都在那里
seeking happiness, but they're like, I'm
他们都在追求幸福，但他们却说，我是
not I'm not I don't feel that much
不，我不是，我没那么在意。
better than I used to because what you
比我以前好多了，因为你
actually want to seek is what my
我真正想寻求的，是我的
grandmother-in-law had, which was being
婆婆有，那是
content with the little bit that she
她对拥有的那一点点东西感到满足。
had. And that's why she was so happy.
有。这就是她如此高兴的原因。
And may maybe again that's the wrong
或许这又是错误的。
word, but she was content. She was
她说了些什么，但她很满足。她
perfectly content with her very simple,
她对自己的简单生活感到非常满足。
very basic, boring life. Boring in other
非常普通、乏味的生活。其他方面很无聊
people's eyes. She was content. And
人们的目光。她很满足。和
that's why a lot of people would look at
这就是为什么很多人会关注……
her, including me, with a sense of envy
她，包括我在内，都带着一丝羡慕之情。
is probably the right word. How did you
这或许是恰当的词。你是怎么做到的？
do that? How were you so happy? It's
这样做吗？你为什么那么高兴？它是
because she was content with what she
因为她对自己拥有的一切感到满意。
had.
有。
I was thinking about the goals that I
我一直在思考我的目标。
wrote in my diary at 18 years old where
我在18岁时的日记里写道：
I said that I wanted to be a
我说过我想成为一名
millionaire, girlfriend, Range Rover,
百万富翁、女朋友、路虎揽胜
six-pack. And actually, when I
六罐装。事实上，当我
envisioned that life, what I envisioned
我设想的那种生活，我所设想的
was contentment. Yes, I
是满足。是的，我
imagine yourself driving in the Ferrari
想象一下你驾驶着法拉利
and you're like, "Ah, that would be so
然后你会想，“啊，那真是太好了。”
great." What you're actually imagining
太好了。” 你实际想象的是什么？
yourself is yourself in a Ferrari being
你就是你，驾驶着法拉利
content with that Ferrari. But what ends
对那辆法拉利很满意。但结局如何呢？
up happening is when if you are in the
突发事件是指当你身处……
Ferrari, you're like, "Oh, look at that
你会说：“哦，看看那辆法拉利！”
Lambo. Oh, that's nicer than mine, isn't
兰博基尼。哦，那比我的好多了，不是吗？
it?" You're not content with it. When I
它？你并不满足于此。当我
get the Lambo, I will be content, right?
买到兰博基尼我就心满意足了，对吧？
And then you want the Rolls-Royce,
然后你想要劳斯莱斯，
whatever it is. Like you're always,
不管它是什么。就像你一直那样，
whether you know it or not, that's what
不管你知不知道，那就是……
you're actually seeking is you just want
你真正想要的，只是你想要
to be content with what you have because
要对你所拥有的感到满足，因为
that's true joy. How does one be
那才是真正的快乐。如何才能成为
content? Now, people have been talking
内容？现在，人们都在谈论这件事。
about that for thousands of years. The
关于这件事已经持续了几千年。这
philosopher Arthur Schopenower has this
哲学家亚瑟·叔本华有这样一段话
quote that I love. He said, "If you only
我喜欢的一句名言。他说：“如果你只
want to be happy, that is very easy to
想要快乐，这很容易。
achieve, but people want to be happier
人们追求成就，但更渴望幸福。
than other people, and that is much more
比其他人多得多，这才是最重要的。
difficult." I think that's that's what
很难。”我想这就是原因。
it is. It's like so much of it is just a
这是。感觉很多东西都只是……
comparison game. And for for a lot of
对比游戏。而且对于很多人来说
people, it's like, I don't necessarily
人嘛，就好像，我不一定
want a a nice house. What I want a house
想要一栋漂亮的房子。我想要一栋房子
is a house that's nicer than yours. I
是一栋比你家更好的房子。我
don't necessarily want an expensive car.
不一定想要一辆昂贵的车。
I want a car that's more expensive than
我想要一辆比这更贵的车
yours. That's that it's a weird thing to
你的。所以说，这是一件很奇怪的事。
say, but at the core, that's what a lot
比如说，但归根结底，很多事情都是这样。
of people want. And so being content, to
人们想要。因此，要知足常乐。
answer your question, is moving from the
回答你的问题，正在从
external benchmark of comparing myself
外部基准与自己进行比较
to you and others and towards the
对你和其他人，以及朝着
internal benchmark of, as I said
正如我所说，内部基准是……
earlier, the only thing that's actually
早些时候，唯一真正是
going to make me happy in life is my
能让我人生快乐的是我的
family, my health. That that's that
家庭，我的健康。就是这样。
that's pretty much it. I I could end it
差不多就是这样了。我可以结束这一切
right there and put a period there and
就在那里，打个句号。
say that's what's going to make me
说那就是让我……
happy. It's the internal benchmark. It's
快乐的。这是内部基准。它是
not comparing what I have to what you
不拿我拥有的和你拥有的比较
have. It's just if nobody else was
有。就好像没有其他人一样。
looking, would I be happy with this?
仔细想想，我会满意吗？
Because the truth is nobody else is
因为事实是，其他人都不是
looking. Another really interesting
正在寻找。另一个非常有趣的
example is just if everyone else was
举个例子，如果其他人都是
made extinct on planet Earth and it was
在地球上灭绝了，而且
just you, right? What would you do? What
只有你一个人，对吧？你会怎么办？什么
kind of life if nobody was watching,
如果没人看着，这就是我的生活。
what kind of life would you live? And I
你想过怎样的生活？我
think in that life, would you want a
想想在那种生活中，你会想要什么？
Ferrari or would you want a Toyota
法拉利还是丰田？
pickup truck that has utility that
具有实用性的皮卡车
actually like makes your life easier
实际上，它能让你的生活更轻松
kind of thing. There's a a great like a
就是那种事。有一个很棒的
a thing that I heard a couple years ago,
几年前我听过一件事，
which is that a high-end Toyota is a
也就是说，高端丰田车是……
much nicer car than an entry-level BMW.
比入门级宝马好得多。
Oh, yeah. Because a high a high a
哦，是的。因为高高
high-end Toyota is like you got the
高端丰田就像你拥有了
cushy seats and the moon roof and the
舒适的座椅、天窗和
good sound system. An entry-level BMW is
音响效果很好。入门级宝马是
just status or the appear like you think
只是地位或者看起来像你认为的那样
it's status. It's just you're buying it
这是它的地位。你只是在买它而已。
for the chance that you're going to
为了你即将……
influence somebody else's view of who
影响他人对“谁”的看法
you are. And people like massively
你是。很多人喜欢
overestimate how much it's going to
高估了它将要达到的程度
actually influence other people. Do you
能够真正影响他人。你
not think there's something hardwired
别认为有什么硬性规定
into humans that makes us want to strive
使人类渴望奋斗
though? Yeah. Because life is always a
尽管？是的。因为生活总是如此
competition for resources. It always has
资源竞争。一直如此
been of there's a limited amount of
数量有限
food, a limited amount of land, a
食物、有限的土地、
limited amount of mates, a limited
配偶数量有限，有限
amount of potential. And so what has
潜力巨大。那么，究竟发生了什么？
mattered historically is not whether I'm
从历史角度来看，重要的不是我是否
a good hunter, it's whether I'm a better
一个优秀的猎人，关键在于我是否更胜一筹。
hunter than you. And the reason I'm here
比你更像猎人。而我来这里的原因是
now is because my ancestors outco
现在是因为我的祖先……
competed everybody else in that
在这方面，他和其他所有人都竞争过。
situation. Yes. So I was I have
情况。是的。所以，我当时是……
competition in my DNA. Absolutely. And
我的DNA里流淌着竞争的基因。绝对地。和
always will you we're never going to get
永远都是你，我们永远也得不到。
to a world this is what Adam Smith wrote
这就是亚当·斯密写给世界的信。
about 300 years ago. He's like if people
大约300年前。他就像是……人们
just needed basic food and shelter they
他们只需要基本的食物和住所。
could stop right now because virtually
现在就可以停止了，因为实际上
everybody has those. But we keep going
每个人都有。但我们会继续前进
because we want to be seen by the people
因为我们想被人们看到
who are we're competing with and showing
我们的竞争对手是谁？我们要向谁展示我们的实力？
you look I'm better than you. I made
你看，我比你强。我做了
more money than you. I'm more worthy for
比你有钱。我更值得
a spouse or attention than you are. It's
比你更需要配偶或关注。它是
always a
总是
competition. It's kind of a a a sad
竞赛。这有点令人难过
thing to think about. And of course, I
值得思考一下。当然，我
think people are intelligent enough to
认为人们足够聪明
know how silly that game can can be and
我知道那游戏有多么愚蠢，
to take themselves out of the game to
主动退出比赛
some extent, but it's we're never going
某种程度上是这样，但我们永远不会去
to be at a time when that's not the
到了那个时候，情况就不同了
case. It's that's definitely hardwired
案件。这是与生俱来的。
in us.
在我们身上。
What is the most important thing we
我们最重要的事情是什么
didn't talk about that we should have
我们没有讨论过我们应该讨论的事情。
talked about? Is there anything comes to
谈过吗？有什么事发生吗？
mind?
头脑？
for the person at home that's dealing
对于在家处理事情的人来说
with all of this tariff craziness, AI,
在所有这些关税乱象中，人工智能，
all of this stuff. It might seem like
所有这些东西。这看起来可能
the world is more uncertain today than
当今世界比以往任何时候都更加不确定。
it's ever been. And I I don't think
一直以来都是如此。而且我不认为
that's the case with tariffs and AI. It
关税和人工智能就是这种情况。它
it has been more uncertain at many
很多时候情况都更加不确定。
points in the past. It just doesn't feel
过去的关键点。就是感觉不对劲
that way because we know how the story
那样做是因为我们知道故事的走向。
ended in the past and we don't know how
已经过去了，我们不知道是怎么回事。
this story is going to is going to end.
这个故事即将结束。
So, it's always the case that the world
所以，世界总是如此。
that we're living in today feels
我们今天所生活的这种感觉
especially fragile and especially
特别脆弱，尤其
uncertain. And I think historically it's
不确定。我认为从历史角度来看是
it's not it's it's it's uncertain and
不是，是，是，这是不确定的，而且
fragile in its own unique new way. But
它以一种独特的方式变得脆弱。但
it's always the case that it feels like
总是感觉好像
the world used to be great. We used to
世界曾经很美好。我们过去常常
have it and now it's not anymore.
我曾经拥有它，现在却没有了。
There's a great John Stewart quote where
约翰·斯图尔特有一句很棒的名言
he says the reason the world felt like a
他说，之所以感觉世界像……
better place during your childhood is
你童年时期更好的地方是
because you were a child. And just
因为你当时还是个孩子。就
because we know how the story ended, it
因为我们知道故事的结局，所以
it it makes it feel like today is a very
这让我感觉今天是一个非常
uncertain place. even if it's kind of
地点不明。即使它有点像
part for the course historically. We
从历史角度来看，这是课程的一部分。我们
have a closing tradition where the last
有一个结束的传统，最后一个
guest leaves a question for the next not
客人给下一位客人留下了一个问题。
knowing who they're leaving it for. And
知道他们要把房子留给谁。和
the question left for you is what is one
留给你的问题是：什么是“一”？
thing you valued starting out that you
你最初重视的那件事
no longer value?
不再有价值？
One thing that I this was not
有一件事我并不认同。
necessarily changing my mind as it was
我必然会改变主意。
just kind of growing as an adult was
就像长大成人一样
when I was in my 20s, I really valued
我二十多岁的时候，非常重视
travel and getting out and seeing the
旅行，走出去看看
world as you should in your 20s. When I
像你20多岁时那样看待世界。当我
became a father, I valued being at home
成为父亲后，我更加珍惜待在家里的时光。
with my kids. And it's almost like in my
和我的孩子们。这几乎就像在我的
20s, a terrible night would be at home
二十多岁的时候，在家度过一个糟糕的夜晚会是什么样？
on the couch. That that's a failed
在沙发上。那是一个失败的
night. And in my 30s, there's nothing or
夜晚。到了我三十多岁，什么都没有了。
in my 40s now, there's nothing better
我现在四十多岁了，没有什么比这更好了。
than being at home on the living room
比待在家里的客厅里更舒服
floor playing Legos with my kids.
我和孩子们在地板上玩乐高。
Nothing better. So, that was a shift in
没有比这更好的了。所以，那是一个转变……
values, but it wasn't because I changed
价值观，但这并不是因为我改变了什么。
my mind. It's just a different state of
我的思绪。这只是另一种状态而已。
life. Morgan, thank you for doing what
生活。摩根，谢谢你做了什么
you do. It's um so incredible because
你做。真是太不可思议了，因为
you know you referenced that book, The
你知道你引用过那本书，《
Intelligent Investor. I tried reading
精明的投资者。我试着读了
that book and I just bounced off it
那本书，我读了之后就完全没感觉了。
straight away. It's really, really
马上。真的，真的
tough. Yeah. But your book, the one that
艰难的。是的。但是你的那本书，那本
my brother gave to me all those years
我哥哥给了我那么多年
ago, has probably made me millions and
很久以前，它可能已经让我赚了数百万美元。
millions of pounds because I read it
因为我读了它，损失了数百万英镑。
when I was young enough because it
当我还年轻的时候，因为
helped me to have a lens and a framework
帮助我找到了合适的视角和框架。
to think about a lot of this tempting
仔细想想这些诱人的事
get-richqu investing mentality that you
那种一夜暴富的投资心态
see today. I wouldn't even call it
今天就来看看。我甚至都不会这么称呼它。
investing. It helped me to understand
投资。它帮助我理解
the emotional elements of saving,
储蓄的情感因素
spending, investing. Um, and ultimately
消费，投资。嗯，最终
it gave me a strategy for what to do if
它给了我一个应对策略，以防万一。
I ever made money. And although it's a
我从来没赚过钱。虽然这是一个
boring strategy, it's a timeless one.
虽然策略老套，但却是永恒的。
And that is part of the reason why so
而这正是部分原因所在。
much of my money currently is in really
我目前的大部分资金都投资在了房地产上。
safe places like index funds. Yeah. And
投资于像指数基金这样的安全场所。是的。和
it it's so important to read books like
阅读这类书籍非常重要。
this
这
because when you read it and you hear
因为当你读到它，听到它的时候
the stories of these individuals and
这些人的故事以及
what happened and what didn't happen to
发生了什么，以及什么没发生
them, whenever you experience an emotion
每当你感受到某种情绪时，就告诉它们
that is similar or you find yourself in
类似，或者你发现自己处于
like a similar situation where you can
类似情况，你可以
relate to one of these characters in the
与以下某个角色有关
story, you have a a blueprint for what
故事里，你有一个蓝图，可以做什么？
happens next.
接下来会发生什么？
And so you ultimately can like ident oh
所以你最终可以像识别哦
my god that was like that guy in the
我的天啊，那简直就像电影《X战警》里的那个人。
book who couldn't stop um gambling even
这本书讲述了一个无法停止赌博的人的故事。
after he'd won or he had predicted the
在他获胜之后，或者在他预测之后
stock market correctly once and then he
他正确地判断了一次股市，然后他就……
predicted it incorrectly the next time
下次预测错误
and then ended up killing himself and
然后他最终自杀了。
it's and it's it's for so many moments
是，而且是，在很多时刻
in my life whether it was crypto or
在我的生活中，无论是加密货币还是其他方面
investing in certain particular stocks
投资某些特定股票
when I used to like pick stocks or
我以前喜欢选股票的时候
starting businesses it's given me this
创业给了我这个
wonderful framework and same as ever is
框架很棒，一如既往。
the book that I wish I had written
我希望自己能写出这样一本书
myself and it's written in a style that
我自己就是作者，而且它的写作风格是……
I wish I'd written myself and in fact my
我希望是我自己写的，事实上我的
last book which um which many of my
最后一本书，嗯，其中很多都是我的
listeners would have um listened to was
听众们本应该……听过……
very very much inspired by your writing
你的文字给了我极大的启发。
style because it is it it is so
风格，因为它就是这样，它就是这样
accessible. It is so story driven and
无障碍。它非常注重故事情节，
it's so the the subjects you talk about
正是你谈论的这些话题
in this book are so diverse but they're
这本书里的内容非常多样化，但它们……
so pertinent to everything all the time
始终与所有事情都息息相关
and it's there so such wonderful books.
那里有很多很棒的书。
You're the author I admire the most of
你是我最欣赏的作家。
all authors that I've ever met. That
我认识的所有作者。那
means the world to me because of the way
对我来说意义非凡，因为……
you write your books. So Well, thank
你写你的书。好的，谢谢
you. That means the world to me and I
你。这对我意义重大，我
think you're the absolute best in the
你认为自己是绝对最棒的
world at what you do. Keeping a keeping
世界为你所做的一切而惊叹。保持
a conversation going for a couple hours
持续了几个小时的对话
is an unbelievably difficult skill and
这是一项极其困难的技能，
there are virtually no one else in the
几乎没有其他人了。
planet who can do it better than you.
星球上还有谁比你做得更好。
So, thank you, Stephen. I hope everybody
所以，谢谢你，斯蒂芬。我希望大家
goes and gets your books. Thank you so
去把你的书拿过来。非常感谢
much, Morgan. We'll see you again soon.
摩根，非常感谢。我们很快会再见面。
This has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信。
bit. 53% of you that listen to the show
少量。 53% 的听众收听了该节目
regularly haven't yet subscribed to the
经常还没有订阅
show. So, could I ask you for a favor
展示。所以，我能请你帮个忙吗？
before we start? If you like the show
开始之前？如果你喜欢这个节目
and you like what we do here and you
你喜欢我们在这里做的事情，你
want to support us, the free simple way
想支持我们吗？免费又简单的方式！
that you can do just that is by hitting
你可以通过点击来做到这一点。
the subscribe button. And my commitment
订阅按钮。我的承诺
to you is if you do that, then I'll do
对你来说，如果你那样做，那么我也会那样做。
everything in my power, me and my team,
我和我的团队将竭尽全力
to make sure that this show is better
为了确保这个节目更好
for you every single week. We'll listen
每周都为您准备。我们会听的。
to your feedback. We'll find the guests
感谢您的反馈。我们会找到客人。
that you want me to speak to, and we'll
你想让我跟谁谈谈，我们就会
continue to do what we do. Thank you so
继续做我们正在做的事情。非常感谢
much.
很多。
[Music]
[音乐]
Where?
在哪里？